<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-07T13:08:03Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4202771" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4202771</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-11-10</datestamp>
        <setSpec>indhealth</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ind Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ind Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">INDHEALTH</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Industrial Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0019-8366</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1880-8026</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health, Japan</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4202771</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4202771</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4202771</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24292880</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24292880</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2013-0169</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2486/indhealth.2013-0169</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Sleep Polysomnography and Reported Stress Across 6 Weeks</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>ÅKERSTEDT</surname>
                    <given-names>Torbjörn</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
                    <sup>*</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>LEKANDER</surname>
                    <given-names>Mats</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>PETERSÉN</surname>
                    <given-names>Helena</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>KECKLUND</surname>
                    <given-names>Göran</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>AXELSSON</surname>
                    <given-names>John</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Stress Research Institute, Stockholm University,
Sweden</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institutet,
Sweden</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label> To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:href="torbjorn.akerstedt@stress.su.se">torbjorn.akerstedt@stress.su.se</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2013</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>52</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>36</fpage>
              <lpage>42</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>20</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>29</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>©2014 National Institute of Occupational Safety and
Health</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>Despite the common notion that stress impairs sleep there is little published data
showing that sleep (polysomnography (PSG)) is impaired across several sleep episodes in
individuals who complain of daily stress during the same period. The present paper aimed
at investigating such a connection. 33 subjects had 3 sleeps recorded with PSG at home
across 6 weeks and kept a sleep/wake diary each day, including 3-hourly ratings of stress
(scale 1–9). The stress ratings and the conventional PSG parameters were averaged across
time. A stepwise multiple regression analysis showed that the best predictors of stress
were Stage 1 sleep (beta = 0.49), latency to Stage 1 sleep (0.47) (adjusted for anxiety
and age). Other sleep continuity variables had significant correlations with stress
(reversed) but did not enter the multiple regression analysis. The correlation between
stress before the start of the study and PSG data was not significant. It was concluded
that moderately increased stress over a longer period of time is related to moderate signs
of disturbed sleep during that period. This may be of importance when considering stress
as a work environment problem.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Polysomnography</kwd>
                <kwd>Subjective ratings</kwd>
                <kwd>EEG</kwd>
                <kwd>Diary</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>The international classification of sleep disorders (ICSD<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><sup>)</sup> lists stress as the main aethiologicial factor behind primary
(psychophysiological) insomnia. A relationship between sleep and stress is also supported by
cross-sectional questionnaire studies<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><sup>)</sup> as well as by prospective studies<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p>
              <p>With regard to polysomnography (PSG − electroencephalography, electro-oculography, and
electromyography) and stress the state of knowledge is less clear. Some early studies
involving unpleasant films before sleep did not show much effect other than intensifying
rapid eye movement (REM) sleep<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><sup>)</sup>. Among studies of
real life stress, the effect of losing a life partner involved increased REM intensity<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><sup>)</sup>, an impending exam resulted in reduced
TST<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><sup>)</sup> (and SWS in the latter study) or increased REM<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><sup>)</sup> and an impending coronary by-pass operation led to
increased sleep fragmentation<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><sup>)</sup>.
Beaumaster <italic>et al.</italic><xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><sup>)</sup>, on
the other hand, found no effect on PSG variables in unexperienced sky divers the night
before the first jump.</p>
              <p>Only a few studies have looked at real work stress. For example, it has been shown that
marine officers being on call (on nights without actual calls to duty) have reduced SWS and
increased stage 2 as compared to being off duty<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><sup>)</sup>. In another study early morning flights shortened sleep duration
and reduced SWS. The latter was related to self-rated apprehension of the early awakening
(measured at bedtime)<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><sup>)</sup>. In a field study in a real life setting a day with
moderately increased stress ratings showed reduced sleep efficiency, and increased Stage 0,
and latency to stage 3<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><sup>)</sup>. In a similar
real life study a week with moderately increased work stress (compared to a low stress week)
showed decreased sleep efficiency<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p>
              <p>All available studies thus far have focused on effects of acute stress, whereas the stress
behind the diagnosis of insomnia refers to extended periods of stress. Thus, it seems
necessary to investigate whether individuals that report stress across a longer period of
time also exhibit indications of impaired sleep. The present study was designed to provide
such information on real life stress and sleep and focused on three home PSG recordings over
a period of six weeks and stress ratings daily across the same weeks. To the best of our
knowledge, this is the first study of its kind.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>A total of 52 subjects were approached, 46 accepted to participate and 33 subjects
completed the full protocol. The loss of the 13 subjects were mainly due to not completing
the polysomnographic recordings because of minor disease, travel, work schedules,
technological problems, etc that interfered with participation. All were recruited through
advertisements and contacts. All subjects were in good health and did not complain of
insomnia. They received an economic compensation of approximately $180. The ethical
committee of Karolinska Institute approved the study. All participants gave written informed
consent.</p>
              <p>Every participant filled in a self-administered questionnaire which included questions
about social and demographic background, working/not working, smoking (yes/no), alcohol
consumtion (no, occasionally, 2–4 times/month, 2–4 times per week or more, scored 0–3), use
of pain killers / fever reducing medication (never − almost every day, range 0–4), physical
activity (almost never, seldom, light physical activity, heavy training, competition level
training, range 0–4), subjectively rated health (SRH) range 1–5, very poor − excellent)<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><sup>)</sup>. No participant used sedatives/hypnotics
or antidepressants while four used anti-hypertensive medication. They also filled out the
Hospital Anxiety/Depression scale<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><sup>)</sup>,
which is a less clinically oriented scale than other similar scales, and better suited for
normal populations. It still retains a good correspondence with traditional clinical
scales<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><sup>)</sup>. In the questionnaire was also
included a rating scale for habitual (last 6 weeks) work stress and home stress on a scale
from 1–5 (from none to very stressful). The two stress scales were averaged to form a
habitual overall stress value. In addition, the well-established work demand scale of
Karasek and Theorell<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><sup>)</sup> was used. The
latter included questions on having too much to do, having to exert too much effort at work,
etc.</p>
              <p>The mean age was 44 years (range 28–69), 75% worked (the remainder were students or
retired), 87% were married/cohabiting and 28% had small children (&lt;7 years old), 51%
lived in their own house (49% in an apartment), 40% had a university education, 66% were
blue collar workers, all except one person worked daytime (5 participants occasionally
worked evenings). The occupations represented were: nurse (3), physician (1), teacher (2),
minister, social worker (2), research assistants (4), administrator (8), guard (2), and
factory worker (2), students (adult education − 4), unemployed (2), retired (2). Mean
bedtime was 23:22 (range 22:40–00:30) and mean time of rising 07:01 (range 5:00−9:24). 25%
were smokers: Means for physical activity was 2.0 ± 0.7 (mean ± SD; range: 0–3), alcohol
intake = 1.7 ± 0.9 (0–3), pain killers = 3.6 ± 1.1 (1–5), Body mass index (BMI) = 24.5 ±
0.45 (20.5–29.7), subjective health = 3.9 ± 0.9 (1–5), habitual stress = 3.4 ± 1.2
(1–5).</p>
              <p>Diary data were collected daily over a period of 6 weeks. To obtain information on stress
levels participants filled in a scale of momentary stress every three hours during
wakefulness<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><sup>)</sup>. The scale (one item)
ranges from 1 to 9, with 1 = no stress whatsoever and 9 = maximum stress imaginable. This
scale has also been used in a study of longitudinal everyday work stress and cortisol<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p>
              <p>Ambulatory polysomnographic recordings were carried out in the subject’s home on two
different occasions between two working days and one night after a working day and before a
day off. Sleep was recorded using ”Embla” recorders (Flaga HF<sup>®</sup>) with two EEG
derivations C3–A2 and C4−A1, one chin electromyographic (EMG) derivation and two
electro-occulogram (EOG) oblique derivations. Ag/AgCl electrodes were used. The sampling
rate was set at 100 Hz. To reduce the impact of low frequency artifacts a 0.8 Hz high-pass
filter was applied for one channel during scoring. This was carried out for all recordings
to ensure that the amount of SWS would not be affected. Epoch-to-epoch correlation with the
filter set at 0.5 and at 0.8 Hz respectively was r=0.94, range: 0.91–0.97. The changes
mainly included less stage 4, replaced with slightly more stage 3 epochs, and also slightly
more REM instead of wake. Sleep stages were scored visually in 30-s epochs according to
Rechtschaffen and Kales<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p>
              <p>Arousals were scored using the ASDA (American Sleep Disorders Association) criteria<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><sup>)</sup>. For an arousal to be scored it had to
last for more than 3 s and for less than 15 s. At least ten seconds of uninterrupted sleep
were required before every arousal for it to be scored, even if there were more than one
arousal in the same epoch. An arousal was defined as an EEG shift to at least alpha activity
from stages 2–4 or REM. During REM sleep also an increase in EMG-activity was required.</p>
              <p>Multiple stepwise regression analyses were used to predict the average stress levels (mean
of momentary stress ratings done every third hours awake for 6 wk). Only variables that
showed a significant univariate relation to momentary stress levels were included. In
addition, well-known confounders, such as age, depression, anxiety and gender were tried as
predictors. Also, habitual stress at the start of the study was tried as a dependent
variable to investigate if one early stress rating could substituted for the daily stress
ratings.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Figure 1</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Mean diurnal pattern of three-hourly stress ratings across all days of the six weeks (
± SE).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-52-036-g001"/></fig> shows the mean diurnal pattern of rated
stress for all days across the 6 weeks. The effect of time of day was highly significant
(F<sub>7,32</sub> = 20.8; <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001; Huyhn-Feldt epsilon = 0.75), with
highest ratings in the forenoon that fell towards the evening.</p>
              <p>The mean momentary stress ratings were correlated with all background variables, but none
of the correlations became significant except for HAD anxiety (positive) and subjective
health (negative) (<xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
<table-wrap id="tbl_001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Mean ( ± SE) and range for all variables, correlations of PSG variables with
average momentary stress adjusted for age, and results from the stepwise multiple
regression analysis of PSG vs. mean momentary stress</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">range</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>&lt;</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress momen.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26 ± 0.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–4.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.4 ± 12.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28–69</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.035</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HADanxiety</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.23 ± 4.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRH</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84 ± .85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377 ± 52.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">276–529</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Eff %</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 ± 6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70–93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage 0 min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.4 ± 33.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17–169</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">St1 min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9 ± 9.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3–43.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">St2 min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226.5 ± 31.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159.6–287.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SWS min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3 ± 26.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–98.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.4 ± 20.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5–134.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9 ± 4.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1–18.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arousals</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0 ± 27.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1–165.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–0.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Awakenings</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 ± 3.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3–22.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lat St1 min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 ± 8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4–50.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lat St2 min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 ± 3.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6–22.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lat St3 min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1 ± 11.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2–60.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lat REM min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.5 ± 19.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2–131.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>MT=movement time, SWS=slow wave sleep (stages 3+4), REM=Rapid Eye Movement sleep,
Lat=latency, min=minutes, BMI=body mass indes, SRH=subjectively rated health,
mom=momentary, r=unadjusted correlations, <italic>p</italic>=level of significance,
b=adjusted regression weight, beta=standardized adjusted regression weight,
R2=proportion of variance accounted for</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>). None of the
background variables correlated significantly with the PSG variables except for age and HAD
anxiety (<xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
              <p><xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents the mean and dispersion
measures for all parameters in the multiple regression, as well as their intercorrelations
with mean momentary stress ratings (controlling for age). Age was included as a control
variable because of its strong relation to many sleep parameters<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><sup>)</sup>. The average stress levels showed significant correlations
with total sleep time (TST), minutes of Stage REM, minutes of Stage 0, minutes of Stage 1,
minutes of Latency to Stage 1, and HAD-anxiety.</p>
              <p><xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> also shows that the stepwise multiple
regression, after inclusion of the significant variables as predictors (age was forced into
the analyses), yielded Stage 1 and latency to Stage 1, plus age and HAD anxiety as
significant predictors (F<sub>5</sub>,<sub>25</sub> = 9.78, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001).
Higher stress was associated with higher levels of Stage 1, a longer Latency to Stage 1,
higher anxiety, and lower age. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Figure 2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Plot of average stress vs Stage 1 sleep after adjustment for age, together with best
fitting regression line.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-52-036-g002"/></fig>
illustrates the relation between Stage 1 and momentary stress ratings with control for age.
The effect of age on each variable was removed through regression analysis and the resulting
residuals around the regression lines (0 on the axes) entered in the new regression in the
figure. The correlation amounted to r=0.47, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01.</p>
              <p>Since a single questionnaire question on habitual stress might be an economical way of
predicting later polosymnography also this potential relation was investigated. Habitual
stress was also tried as predictor in the multiple regression analysis in addition to the
significant parameters but did not become significant. It was also tried as an alternative
dependent variable with the PSG variables and age as predictors. The only significant
correlation was with mean number of awakenings (r=−0.36, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) and in
the stepwise multiple regression analysis the beta coefficient was β=0.32 with age β=0.44.
The measure of habitual stress correlated r=0.56 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) with the
average of momentary stress across the six weeks.</p>
              <p>For further help in understanding the results, product moment correlations were computed
for some variables. Thus an increasing age was correlated with a reduced TST (r=−0.38,
<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05), more Stage 0 (r=0.50, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), more
Stage 1 (r=0.47, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001, less SWS (r=−0.74, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001), and less REM
(r=−0.48, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01), but not with Latency to Stage 1 (r=0.09). Latency to
Stage 1 and amount of Stage 1 did not correlate significantly (r=0.23, ns) but the two
correlated significantly with Stage 0 (r=0.60, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001 and r=0.51,
<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01, respectively).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Rated momentary stress showed moderate mean levels across time, with higher ratings during
the morning and the afternoon, and reduced levels in the evening. The correlation analysis
showed that the higher momentary subjective stress level was related to higher amounts of
Stage 1 sleep, a longer latency to Stage 1, and anxiety. The higher amount of Stage 1 and
the extended sleep latency seem to suggest that perceived momentary stress is related to a
moderate sleep disturbance.</p>
              <p>In a previous study we found increased levels of stage 1 sleep and increased sleep latency
in burnout (stress related) patients on long term sick leave (together with increased sleep
fragmentation and decreased SWS)<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><sup>)</sup>. Even
if there is very little consensus on polysomnographical criteria for disturbed sleep<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><sup>)</sup>, increased sleep latency is one of the
most well established indicators of disturbed sleep according to the International
Classification of Sleep Disorders (ICSD 10)<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><sup>)</sup>. In two meta-analyses it has been suggested that a self-reported
sleep latency of&gt;30 minutes is a reasonable indicator of disturbed sleep<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><sup>)</sup>. It is not clear if there is a “critical level” of the amount of
Stage 1, but the level is increased in many situations of disturbed sleep<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><sup>)</sup>. It should be emphasized that momentary
stress was also related to more Stage 0 during sleep (or WASO) in the univariate analysis.
It is thus possible that Stage 0 is an equally interesting sleep variable in relation to
stress as is Stage 1. In our previous study comparing high and low stress nights, wake after
sleep onset (WASO, which corresponds to the amount of Stage 0) and was significantly
increased, and sleep efficiency decreased, on the stressed night<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><sup>)</sup>. However, there is a possibility that disturbed sleep
could cause an increased perception of stress<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref><sup>)</sup>. However, the direction of causality was not possible to address
with the present design.</p>
              <p>SWS was not related to stress in the present study, nor in the two previous studies<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><sup>)</sup>. Possibly more severe stress is required to affect SWS. Another
observation is that REM sleep was positively correlated with stress in the univaariate
analysis but was not strong enough to enter the multiple regression.</p>
              <p>Total sleep time (TST) did not enter the multiple regression, but the initial correlation
with momentary stress was rather high. This seems to be in conflict with the common notion
that stress reduces sleep duration. But, there are no empirical data supporting the latter
view. In fact there are some indications to the contrary. Thus, Dahlgren <italic>et
al.</italic><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><sup>)</sup> found increased during a
week of increased stress, presumably, reflecting a need for sleep. Horne <italic>et
al.</italic><xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><sup>)</sup> found increased levels
of SWS after a day of visual and mental stimulation. It may also be of interest to consider
the results of Meerlo <italic>et al.</italic><xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref><sup>)</sup> who demonstrated increased “high intensity” sleep in rats after
social stress. Kripke <italic>et al.</italic><xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref><sup>)</sup> have argued that increased sleep duration is an indicator of
problems or disease, whereas short sleep may be the opposite. This seems to suggest that the
increased TST in the present study could be a compensatory response to stress, and its
resulting impairment of sleep. However, one could also argue that the increased amounts of
Stage 1 (and Stage 0) could result from an attempt to extend sleep beyond its natural
limits. This might be true since such an extension would result in difficulties maintaining
sleep, thus resulting in the appearance of superficial sleep, awakenings etc. One should
remember that the setting was naturalistic and that the subjects could regulate their sleep
duration at will, at least within the confines of work and other commitments.</p>
              <p>The modest signs of disturbed sleep in this study may be due to the stress levels in the
present population being rather moderate, and hence only having limited effects on sleep. As
discussed previously, there is no well-established method of quantifying stress in absolute
terms and there are no criteria for what levels of stress that might result in sleep
impairment. This seems to be an important topic for future research.</p>
              <p>Previous studies of stress and PSG also show rather modest links. This is probably in the
nature of naturalistic studies; to be allowed into individuals’ homes in periods of intense
work stress (or other stress) may not be practically or ethically feasible. However, it has
been demonstrated that being sick listed after long periods of work stress is associated
with similar, but stronger sleep impairment<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><sup>)</sup>. Possibly, modest increases of reported work stress or disturbed
sleep can be used as warning signals by employers.</p>
              <p>One limitation of the present study is the modest number of participants and the study
needs replication in a larger sample. Another problem is its cross-sectional character,
which makes it impossible to infer causation. However, important factors like age, gender,
anxiety, depression, physical activity, BMI, SRH, use of alcohol, smoking, and use of pain
killers were controlled for or left out because of non-significant correlations with the
dependent variable. Interestingly, baseline HAD anxiety added to the prediction of mean
momentary stress of the sleep variables, without forcing them out of the regression. Thus,
traitlike anxiety at the start of the study was not involved in the PSG relation to
momentary stress. Habitual stress at the start of the study had a significant correlation
with mean momentary stress, which was expected, and explained 25% of the variance. Still, it
failed to enter the multiple regression against momentary stress. Furthermore it was only
related to one PSG variable (awaknenings/h) and rather weakly. Thus, it
seems unlikely that mean momentary stress represents trait-like stress, but rather temporary
stress during a certain time period. And, levels during this time period seem to reflect
physiological sleep impairment during the same time span.</p>
              <p>The present study used a sample of convenience and is probably not representative of the
average individual. However, care was taken to include a reasonable age range, both genders
and to use no restrictions with respect to other background factors. Real-life studies of
the present type will always require a compromise between feasibility and
representativeness. The study also took into account a number of possible confounders. There
might be other confounders not accounted for, but the results leave the impression that a
state of (moderate) stress during a certain time period is associated with impaired
physiological sleep during that same period. Causation cannot be determined with the present
design but studies comparing sleep physiology between a single day with low stress with a
day with moderate stress show similar impairment due to stress<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p>
              <p>In summary, the present study has shown that higher average stress across a 6-week period
was related to a longer sleep latency, an increased amounts of Stage 0 and Stage 1 sleep,
and a slight increase of total sleep time. Thus, a modest increase of stress is related to a
mild sleep impairment. Longitudinal studies are, however needed in order to describe the
effect of varying periods of stress on sleep.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="r1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book">AASM (<year>2005</year>) ICSD −
International classification of sleep disorders, revised: Diagnostic and coding manual.
American Academy of Sleep Medicine, Chicago.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Urponen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuori</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Partinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) Self-evaluations of factors promoting and disturbing
sleep: an epidemiological survey in Finland. Social Science &amp; Medicine
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Characteristics of insomnia in the
United States: results of the 1991 National Sleep Foundation survey. I</article-title>.
<source>Sleep</source><volume>22</volume> (Suppl
2), <fpage>S347</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10394606</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>de Lange</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kompier</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taris</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Geurts</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckers</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Houtman</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A hard day’s night: a longitudinal
study on the relationships among job demands and job control, sleep quality and
fatigue</article-title>. <source>J Sleep Res</source><volume>18</volume>,
<fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19493298</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerholm</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kecklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Predicting changes in sleep complaints
from baseline values and changes in work demands, work control, and work
preoccupation—the WOLF-project</article-title>. <source>Sleep
Med</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22177346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Baekeland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Koulack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>Effects of a stressful presleep
experience on electroencephalograph-recorded sleep</article-title>.
<source>Psychophysiology</source><volume>4</volume>,
<fpage>436</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5662813</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Eye movements during REM sleep: the
influence of personality and presleep conditions</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc
Psychol</source><volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1090</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">175146</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Goodenough</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Witkin</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koulack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>The effects of stress films on dream
affect and on respiration and eye-movement activity during rapid-eye-movement
sleep</article-title>. <source>Psychophysiology</source><volume>12</volume>,
<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">168607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>CF</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Buysse</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Houck</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlernitzauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasternak</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kupfer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Sleep after spousal bereavement: a
study of recovery from stress</article-title>. <source>Biol
Psychiatry</source><volume>34</volume>, <fpage>791</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8292683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Holdstock</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Verschoor</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Student sleep patterns before, during
and after an examination period</article-title>. <source>J
Psychol</source><volume>4</volume>,
<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Burch</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dossett</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Nocturnal EEG-GSR profiles: the
influence of presleep states</article-title>.
<source>Psychophysiology</source><volume>3</volume>,
<fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6038667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Becker-Carus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Stress-Wirkungen in Labor- und
Realsituationen in Abhängigkeit von REM-Schlaf und psychophysiologischer
Aktivation</article-title>. <source>Z Exp Angew Psychol</source><volume>XXVI</volume>,
<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">220808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Edéll-Gustaffson</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Insufficient sleep, cognitive anxiety
and health transition in men with coronary artery disease: a self-report and
polysomnographic study</article-title>. <source>J Adv Nurs</source><volume>37</volume>,
<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11843979</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Beaumaster</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>The sleep of skydivers: a study of
stress</article-title>. <source>Psychophysiology</source><volume>15</volume>,
<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">208094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Torsvall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Disturbed sleep while being on call. An
EEG study of apprehension in ships’ engineers</article-title>.
<source>Sleep</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3363267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kecklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Morning work: effects of early rising
on sleep and alertness</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source><volume>20</volume>,
<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9178917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kecklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Apprehension of the subsequent working
day is associated with a low amount of slow wave sleep</article-title>. <source>Biol
Psychol</source><volume>66</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15041138</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Akerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kecklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Impaired sleep after bedtime stress and
worries</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychol</source><volume>76</volume>,
<fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17884278</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kecklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Onofrio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Stress vulnerability and the effects of
moderate daily stress on sleep polysomnography and subjective
sleepiness</article-title>. <source>J Sleep Res</source><volume>22</volume>,
<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22835074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Undén</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreasson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elofsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brismar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronnelid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lekander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Inflammatory cytokines, behaviour and
age as determinants of self-rated health in women</article-title>. <source>Clin Sci
(Lond)</source><volume>112</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17094770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lisspers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nygren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Söderman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scaale
(HAD): some psychometric data for a Swedish sample</article-title>. <source>Acta
Psychiatr Scand</source><volume>96</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9350957</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Theorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) The Demand-Control-Support Model for Studying Health
in Relation to the Work Environment: An Interactive Model. In: Orth-Gomér K, Schneiderman
N (Eds.), In: Behavioral Medicine Approaches to Cardiovascular Disease Prevention, 69–85,
Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, New Jersey.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetmore</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Korczykowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinges</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Detre</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Perfusion functional MRI reveals
cerebral blood flow pattern under psychological stress</article-title>. <source>Proc
Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>102</volume>, <fpage>17804</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kecklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Different levels of work-related stress
and the effects on sleep, fatigue and cortisol</article-title>. <source>Scand J Work
Environ Health</source><volume>31</volume>, <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16161710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Rechtschaffen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kales</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>) A manual of standardized terminology, techniques and
scoring system for sleep stages of human subjects. US Department of Health, Education and
Welfare, Public Health Service, Bethesda.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">ASDA (<year>1992</year>)
<article-title>EEG arousals: scoring rules and examples</article-title>.
<source>Sleep</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11032543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Prinz</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Age impairments in sleep, metabolic and
immune functions</article-title>. <source>Exp Gerontol</source><volume>39</volume>,
<fpage>1739</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15582290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ekstedt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soderstrom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Sleep physiology in recovery from
burnout</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychol</source><volume>82</volume>,
<fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19699775</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Littner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirshkowitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushida</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loube</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodson</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Practice parameters for using
polysomnography to evaluate insomnia: an update</article-title>.
<source>Sleep</source><volume>26</volume>, <fpage>754</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14572131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book">AASM (<year>2001</year>)
International classification of sleep disorders—diagnostic and coding manual.
AASM.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lichstein</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Durrence</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Riedel</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Quantitative criteria for
insomnia</article-title>. <source>Behav Res Ther</source><volume>41</volume>,
<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12643966</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichstein</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Durrence</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reidel</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology in insomina, depression,
and anxiety</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source><volume>28</volume>,
<fpage>1457</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16335332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Wesensten</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balkin</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Belenky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Does sleep fragmentation impact
recuperation? A review and reanalysis</article-title>. <source>J Sleep
Res</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10646163</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Minkel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>McNealy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gianaros</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Drabant</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Manuck</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hariri</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Sleep quality and neural circuit
function supporting emotion regulation</article-title>. <source>Biol Mood Anxiety
Disord</source><volume>2</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23216889</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r35">
                <label>35</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Minard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Sleep and sleepiness following a
behaviourally “active” day</article-title>.
<source>Ergonomics</source><volume>28</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4018009</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r36">
                <label>36</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Meerlo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pragt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Daan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Social stress induces high intensity
sleep in rats</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source><volume>225</volume>,
<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9143013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="r37">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kripke</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Do we sleep too
much?</article-title><source>Sleep</source><volume>27</volume>,
<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14998231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
