<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-07T13:08:00Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4017272" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4017272</identifier>
        <datestamp>2014-05-13</datestamp>
        <setSpec>taylorfranopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dev Neuropsychol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dev Neuropsychol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">hdvn</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Developmental Neuropsychology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">8756-5641</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1532-6942</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4017272</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4017272</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4017272</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24742310</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/87565641.2014.886691</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Functional Impairments in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder: The Mediating Role of Neuropsychological Functioning</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sjöwall</surname>
                    <given-names>Douglas</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Thorell</surname>
                    <given-names>Lisa B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="A1">Department of Clinical Neuroscience and Stockholm Brain Institute, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="COR1">Correspondence should be addressed to Lisa B. Thorell, Division of Psychology, Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institutet, Nobels Väg 9, 171 65 Solna, Sweden. E-mail: <email>lisa.thorell@ki.se</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2014</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>39</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <fpage>187</fpage>
              <lpage>204</lpage>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Douglas Sjöwall and Lisa B. Thorell</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://www.informaworld.com/mpp/uploads/iopenaccess_tcs.pdf">
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.informaworld.com/mpp/uploads/iopenaccess_tcs.pdf">Supplemental Terms and Conditions for iOpenAccess articles published in Taylor &amp; Francis journals</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is associated with multiple neuropsychological deficits and the present study aimed to investigate to what extent these deficits are related to the functional impairments associated with the disorder. The results showed that all executive functioning deficits and reaction time variability acted as mediators in the relation between ADHD and academic achievement. However, only the effect of working memory for language skills, and the effects of reaction time variability and working memory for mathematics, remained significant when studying independent effects. Regulation of anger was a significant mediator for peer problems. Gender or symptoms of oppositional defiant disorder (ODD) or conduct disorder (CD) did not moderate these findings.</p>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p>In addition to the three major symptoms of the disorder—hyperactivity, impulsivity, and inattention—children diagnosed with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) often encounter problems in daily life, such as poor academic achievement (e.g., <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Daley &amp; Birchwood, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Loe &amp; Feldman, 2007</xref>) and problematic peer relations (e.g., <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">Hoza, 2007</xref>, and <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">McQuade &amp; Hoza, 2008</xref> for reviews). As these functional impairments are associated to such a large extent with ADHD, theoretical models should be able to explain not only the symptoms of ADHD but also the functional impairments associated with the disorder. At the neuropsychological level, ADHD has been described as a heterogeneous disorder (e.g., <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">Nigg, Willcutt, Doyle, &amp; Sonuga-Barke, 2005</xref>) that involves deficits in multiple functions such as executive functions (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Barkley, 1997</xref>), delay aversion (e.g., <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">Sonuga-Barke, 2002</xref>), reaction time (RT) variability (e.g., <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Castellanos, Sonuga-Barke, Milham, &amp; Tannock, 2006</xref>), and emotional functioning (e.g., <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">Martel, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">Sjöwall, Roth, Lindqvist, &amp; Thorell, 2013</xref>). However, it is not known to what extent this neuropsychological heterogeneity can explain why some individuals with ADHD develop functional impairments, whereas others manage relatively well in their daily life. In the present study, we therefore investigated a large range of neuropsychological deficits as possible mediators in the relation between ADHD and two of the most central aspects of daily functioning in childhood: academic achievement and peer problems.</p>
            <sec id="s2">
              <title>ADHD, ACADEMIC ACHIEVEMENT, AND NEUROPSYCHOLOGICAL FUNCTIONING</title>
              <p>Most previous studies examining the link between ADHD and academic achievement have not taken the neuropsychological heterogeneity in ADHD into account, but have instead focused exclusively on executive function (EF) deficits. For example, <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Biederman and colleagues (2004)</xref> found that ADHD children with EF deficits performed worse than ADHD children without EF deficits, but a more recent study using the same analytical design showed no such differences (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">Lambek et al., 2010</xref>). In addition, some studies have used dimensional measures of EFs and found independent effects on academic performance, when controlling for ADHD (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Barry, Lyman, &amp; Klinger, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Diamantopoulou, Rydell, Thorell, &amp; Bohlin, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Miller &amp; Hinshaw, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">Miller, Nevado-Montenegro, &amp; Hinshaw, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">Rogers, Hwang, Toplak, Weiss, &amp; Tannock, 2011</xref>). One limitation of the studies mentioned above is that no formal mediation analyses were conducted, which means that they failed to investigate to what extent the relation between ADHD and academic achievement was significantly reduced when the effect of EF deficits was taken into account. When conducting such analyses, it was found that EF deficits partially mediated the relation between inattention and both language skills and mathematics in a non-clinical preschool sample (<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">Thorell, 2007</xref>). A second limitation of previous studies is that executive functioning has often been analyzed as a composite of several functions. However, specific EFs may be differentially related to functional impairments. Non-clinical studies have shown, for example, that working memory appears to be of most importance for academic achievement (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">Lan, Legare, Pontiz, Li, &amp; Morrison, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">Thorell, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">Thorell, Veleiro, Siu, &amp; Mohammadi, 2013</xref>). Other possible mediators of the relation between ADHD and academic achievement have not been examined, although a few non-clinical studies have shown that motivationally based functions, such as delay aversion and delay of gratification, are not significantly related to academic achievement when EF deficits are controlled for (e.g., <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Brock, Rimm-Kaufman, Nathanson, &amp; Grimm, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">Thorell, 2007</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3">
              <title>ADHD, PEER PROBLEMS, AND NEUROPSYCHOLOGICAL FUNCTIONING</title>
              <p>Regarding the relation between ADHD, EF deficits, and peer problems, almost all previous studies have used broad measures of social functioning and/or composite EF measures. One exception is the study by <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Miller and Hinshaw (2010)</xref>, which showed a small, but significant, effect of commission and omission errors on a continuous performance task on measures of peer acceptance. However, most other studies (but see <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Rinskey &amp; Hinshaw, 2011</xref>) have found that EF deficits are not significantly related to more general measures of social functioning when the effect of ADHD symptoms is taken into account (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Biederman et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Diamantopoulou et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Huang-Pollock, Mikami, Pfiffner, &amp; McBurnett, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">Scholtens, Diamantopoulou, Tillman, &amp; Rydell, 2012</xref>). With regard to other neuropsychological functions besides EF deficits, <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">Scholtens and colleagues (2012)</xref> included RT variability, which was found to be related to social acceptance, but not when symptoms of ADHD were controlled for.</p>
              <p>Altogether, the previous findings presented above indicate that EF deficits and RT variability are not strongly associated with social functioning, although there is a need to investigate independent effects of different EF functions in relation to specific aspect of social functioning such as peer problems. In addition, the effects of other neuropsychological functions have to be taken into account. In the present study, we therefore included measures of emotional functioning, as this has been acknowledged to be of importance in ADHD (e.g., <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">Martel, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">Nigg, 2006</xref>). We have chosen to focus on two aspects of emotional functioning that have been linked to ADHD in previous research: emotion recognition (e.g., <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Kats-Gold, Besser, &amp; Priel, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">Sinzig, Morsch, &amp; Lehmkuhl, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr">Yuill &amp; Lyon, 2007</xref>) and emotion regulation (e.g., <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">Maedgen &amp; Carlson, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr">Walcott &amp; Landau, 2004</xref>). Both emotion regulation and emotion recognition have been shown to be related to social abilities in studies in non-clinical samples (e.g., <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">Eisenberg, Hofer, &amp; Vaughan, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">Mostow, Izard, Fine, &amp; Trentacosta, 2002</xref>), but very few clinical studies of children with ADHD have examined this relation. One exception is the study by <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Anastopoulos and colleagues (2011)</xref>, which demonstrated that emotional liability partially mediated the relation between ADHD status and social skills. In addition, <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Kats-Gold and colleagues (2007)</xref> showed that difficulty with recognizing emotions was related to a general measure of social skills among children with ADHD, but not specifically to peer ratings of social acceptability. No previous study has investigated the effect of multiple mediators simultaneously. Thus, it is not known to what extent different neuropsychological mediators overlap in explaining the link between ADHD and peer problems. In addition, the mediating effects of different types of emotions (i.e., anger, fear, sadness, and happiness) on peer problems have not been investigated.</p>
              <p>Finally, it is important to investigate possible moderators in the relation between ADHD and functional impairments. Few studies exist, although there are some indications that girls with ADHD have more peer problems than do boys with the same disorder (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Henricsson &amp; Rydell, 2006</xref>), and it has been suggested that EF deficits may be more strongly related to peer problems in girls than in boys (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Diamatopoulou et al., 2007</xref>). In addition, some previous studies (e.g., <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">Martel, 2009</xref>, for a review) have suggested that emotion regulation deficits may be particularly evident in the subgroup of children with ADHD and comorbid oppositional defiant disorder (ODD) or conduct disorder (CD).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4">
              <title>AIMS</title>
              <p>The aim of the present study was to investigate to what extent EF deficits, delay aversion, RT variability, and emotional functioning (deficits in emotional regulation and emotion recognition) function as mediators in the relation between ADHD and two of the most important aspects of daily functioning in middle childhood: academic achievement and peer problems. In order to address the limitations of previous research, we conducted full mediation analyses using a statistical method that allowed us to investigate the independent contributions of different neuropsychological deficits. As most previous studies have failed to investigate the moderating effects of gender and ODD/CD, we also explored this issue.</p>
              <p>Based on the previous research presented above, we hypothesized that EF deficits would act as mediators in the relation between ADHD and academic achievement, but not between ADHD and peer problems. Among the EF measures, we expected working memory to be the strongest mediator for academic achievement. The lack of previous studies including RT variability in relation to functional impairments limits any a priori hypothesis. Regarding delay aversion, we hypothesized that this function would not mediate the relation between ADHD and academic achievement. Finally, we expected the emotional variables, but not the other neuropsychological variables, to be significant mediators in the relation between ADHD and peer problems.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s5">
              <title>METHOD</title>
              <sec id="s6">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>The present study included 102 children (56 girls) age 7–13 years (<italic>M</italic> = 10.39, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.79) and diagnosed with ADHD and a control group of 102 children (<italic>M</italic> = 10.37, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.69) individually matched to the clinical group with regard to gender and age (+/−6 months). The ADHD sample included clinically referred children. As one aim was to study gender differences, girls were oversampled. All children had been formally diagnosed with ADHD by a psychiatrist, and the children's diagnostic status was confirmed at the time of the study using both parent and teacher ratings of the ADHD Rating Scale IV (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">DuPaul, Power, Anastopoulos, &amp; Reid, 1998</xref>). The <italic>mean</italic> score for the ADHD Rating Scale IV was 30.20 (<italic>SD</italic> = 7.58) for parent ratings and 36.56 (<italic>SD</italic> = 10.37) for teacher ratings. We asked the parents at what age the child's symptoms had emerged and for how long time the symptoms had been present. In addition, we asked them to rate on a 4-point scale (0 = not at all, 3 = a great deal) how much the child's difficulties interfere with everyday life in the following areas: home life, friendships, classroom learning, and leisure activities. The two last questions were taken from the impact supplement of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ; <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Goodman, 1997</xref>). Based on these three questions and in line with DSM-IV criteria (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">APA, 1994</xref>), we confirmed that the symptoms had been present before age 7, for at least 6 months, and that impairment was found in multiple settings. Based on teacher and parent ratings, 71 children (70%) met the criteria for the combined subtype, 4 children (4%) met the criteria for the hyperactive/impulsive subtype and 27 children (26%) met the criteria for the inattentive subtype. Comorbid diagnoses included ODD/CD (44%), generalized anxiety disorder/anxiety NOS (7%), obsessive compulsive disorder (1%), and Tourette syndrome (4%). Children with an IQ &lt; 70 were not recruited to the study. With regard to pharmacological treatment, 31 children (30%) did not receive any medication, 63 children (62%) were on stimulant medication, and 8 children (8%) were on non-stimulant medication (i.e., Atomoxetine). All children receiving pharmacological treatment for ADHD were asked to withdraw medication 24 hours prior to testing. Despite this, 10 children (4 taking stimulants and 6 taking non-stimulants) were on medication during the neuropsychological testing. However, excluding these 10 children did not result in any significant changes in the results.</p>
                <p>The control group was recruited through local schools. The exclusion criteria for the control group were: 1) severe psychiatric or somatic problems as reported by parents and 2) scores above the 75<sup>th</sup> percentile on either the inattention or the hyperactivity subscale on the ADHD Rating Scale IV (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">DuPaul et al., 1998</xref>) as assessed by both teachers and parents. In the control group, the mean score for the ADHD Rating Scale IV was 4.35 (<italic>SD</italic> = 3.98) for parent ratings and 7.59 (<italic>SD</italic> = 4.42) for teacher ratings. The local ethics committee approved the study.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s7">
                <title>Measures</title>
                <p><italic>Neuropsychological assessment.</italic>  The tests included in this study have all been used in previous publications. The measures were standardized and some measures were reversed so that high values always indicated poor performance. If more than one measure was available within a domain, the mean value of the different measures was used in the analyses.</p>
                <p><bold>Working memory</bold> was measured using three tasks. Spatial working memory was measured by “Find the phone task” (<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">Sjöwall et al., 2013</xref>) using the Psytools software (Delosis, London). This task is very similar in design to the spatial working memory task included in the Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB; <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">Owens, Downes, Sahakian, Polkey, &amp; Robbins, 1990</xref>). In our version of the task, telephones are shown on the computer screen and the task is to remember which telephone that has already rung to avoid selecting that phone several times. The number of times the children returned to a phone that had already rung was used as a measure of working memory deficit. The Children's Size-Ordering Task (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">McInerney, Hrabok, &amp; Kerns, 2005</xref>) measured verbal working memory. In this task, the administrator reads aloud progressively longer lists of common objects (e.g., pencil, train, mountain) and the child is asked to repeat them ordered by size of the object, from smallest to largest. The objects included have been selected so that they are familiar to all children, can be visualized easily, and are unambiguous in their relative size. After at least two practice trials, the test begins with two items per trial, and becomes progressively more difficult to a maximum of seven items per trial. All children are administered all trials, regardless of their performance. The total number of word pairs organized in the correct order was used to measure working memory (maximum = 42). Verbal working memory was also measured using the total score for the backward condition of the digit span subtest (<xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">Wechsler, 1991</xref>). The score used was the total number of correct trials.</p>
                <p><bold>Inhibition</bold> was measured by two tasks using the Psytools software (Delosis, London). The first task was based on the Go/No-Go paradigm. The particular version used here was originally developed by <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Berlin and Bohlin (2002)</xref> and consists of pictures depicting a blue square, a blue triangle, a red square, and a red triangle, which are presented on a computer screen. During the first part of the task, the child is instructed to press a key (“go”) when a frequent stimulus (a blue figure) appears on the screen, but to make no response (“no-go”) when an infrequent stimulus (a red figure) appears. The same stimuli are used for the second part of the task, but the child is instructed to press a key every time a square is presented, and to inhibit his/her response every time a triangle is presented, irrespective of its color. Altogether the task includes 60 stimuli with a “go-rate” of 77%. The score derived from this task was number of commission errors (pressing the key when a “no-go” target was presented). The second task was a Navon-like task previously used by, for example, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">Miyake, Friedman, Emerson, Witzki, and Howerter (2000)</xref>. A circle consisting of small squares, or the opposite, a square consisting of small circles, was displayed on the computer screen and the participants were instructed to either respond to local stimuli (e.g., the small squares making up the circle) or global stimuli (e.g., the circle made up by the squares). In each session, 20 objects (10 squares and 10 circles) were shown. The objects were displayed for 500 milliseconds and the participant had 3,500 milliseconds to give an answer. The score used was the total number of errors for the two sessions (maximum = 40).</p>
                <p><bold>Shifting</bold> was measured using the Navon-like task (see description above). A third session was performed in which participants were asked to shift between responding to local or global stimuli. A total of 40 trials were presented and a square and a circle in the lower corners of the computer screen indicated what stimulus to respond to (local trials = small circle/square, global trials = large circle/square). Number of errors during this last session was used to measure shifting. Two children in the ADHD group had missing data due to failure to understand the instructions.</p>
                <p><bold>Delay aversion</bold> was measured using the Choice Delay Task (<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">Sonuga-Barke, Taylor, Sembi, &amp; Smith, 1992</xref>). In this task, the child is asked to make 25 choices between an immediate small reward (two seconds for one point) and a delayed large reward (30 seconds for 2 points). Delay aversion is measured as the number of times the child chooses the small, immediate reward during the final 10 trials. This task has previously been used in for example the NIMH Multimodal treatment study of ADHD (<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">Solanto et al., 2001</xref>).</p>
                <p><bold>Reaction time variability</bold> was measured as the standard deviation of participants’ RTs for correct answers on the non-shifting trials in the Navon-like task and correct answers on the Go/No-Go task (see descriptions above).</p>
                <p><bold>Emotion regulation</bold> was measured by parental ratings on the Emotion Questionnaire developed by <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">Rydell, Berlin, and Bohlin (2003)</xref>. In the present study, we included the questions measuring how well the child can self-regulate his/her own emotions. This includes a total of 12 questions related to regulation of anger, fear, sadness and happiness/exuberance. For each emotion, one general question is asked (e.g., If sad, my child has trouble calming down by him-/herself) and two questions regarding regulation in specific situations (e.g., if my child has fallen and hurt him-/herself, my child has trouble calming down by him-/herself). Ratings are made on a scale ranging from 1 (do not agree at all) to 5 (fully agree), with higher values indicating greater problems with emotion regulation. The mean score of the items for each emotion was used in the analyses. This instrument has been shown to have high test-retest reliability and it has been validated against both other rating instruments (<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">Rydell et al., 2003</xref>) and self-report measures (<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">Rydell, Thorell, &amp; Bohlin, 2007</xref>). Six ADHD children had missing data because their parents did not consent to completing the rating scale.</p>
                <p><bold>Emotion recognition</bold> was measured using facial images selected from the NimStim Set of Facial Expressions (672 images; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.macbrain.org/resources.htm">http://www.macbrain.org/resources.htm</ext-link>). The NimStim pictures consist of naturally posed photographs (e.g., with hair, make-up) of 43 professional actors (25 male; 21 to 30 years old) and they have been shown to have both high reliability and high validity (<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">Tottenham et al., 2009</xref>). In the present study, we used 36 different faces displaying 6 different emotions: anger, fear, sadness, happiness, surprise, and disgust. For each trial, six different emotions were displayed on the computer screen and the administrator asked the child to identify one emotion (e.g., Who is angry?). A total of 36 trials were used and the score used was number of correct responses for each emotion (maximum score = 6). One ADHD child had missing data. As argued by for example <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Kats-Gold et al. (2007)</xref>, this type of simple emotion recognition task is preferable in studies of individuals with ADHD as it has very low demands on working memory compared to more complex tasks (e.g., matching facial effect to story stems).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s8">
                <title>Functional Impairments</title>
                <p>Functional impairments were measured by peer problems and academic achievement. Peer problems were assessed using the “peer relationship subscale” from the SDQ (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Goodman, 1997</xref>). The SDQ is available in over 30 languages and has been widely used in epidemiological, developmental and clinical research, as well as in routine clinical and educational practice. The peer problems scale in the SDQ includes items such as “generally liked by other children” and “has at least one good friend,” and it has been shown to be highly correlated with the corresponding scale in the Child Behavior Checklist (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Goodman &amp; Scott, 1999</xref>). Ratings were made on a scale from 1 to 5 and the mean scores for parent and teacher ratings (<italic>r</italic> = .69, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) were used. The measure of academic achievement consisted on two separate questions: How do you rate the child's school performance in relation to children in the same age for (a) mathematics (b) language skills. Ratings were made on a scale from 1 to 5 (1 = “much below average”; 2 = “below average”; 3 = “average”; 4 = “above average”; 5 = “much above average”). Concerning the validity of such ratings, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Henricsson and Rydell (2006)</xref> showed that teacher ratings of language skills and mathematics are very highly correlated with results on national tests in these two subjects (<italic>r</italic>s = .82, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). Thus, this measure should be considered a valid measure of children's performance in school.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s9">
                <title>Covariates</title>
                <p>Child age and sex were included as covariates in all analyses. In addition, intelligence (IQ) was measured using the block design subtest from the WISC–III (<xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">Wechsler, 1991</xref>), a test that has been shown to correlate highly with full-scale IQ (r = .93; <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">Groth-Marnat, 1997</xref>). Mean values for the block design subtest were not significantly different when comparing individuals with ADHD (<italic>M</italic> = 9.70, <italic>SD</italic> = 3.67) and controls (<italic>M</italic> = 10.36, <italic>SD</italic> = 2.88) <italic>t</italic> = 1.37, <italic>ns.</italic> The results are reported both with and without controlling for IQ in order to let the reader make his/her own interpretation of the results. This procedure is recommended (e.g., <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Barkley, 1997</xref>) as it has been argued that IQ and executive functioning are not entirely separate constructs.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s10">
                <title>Statistical Analyses</title>
                <p>First, the following three relations were examined: (1) the relations between the independent variable (i.e., ADHD status) and each one of the potential mediators (i.e., neuropsychological deficits), (2) the relation between the independent and the dependent variable (i.e., functional impairments), and (3) the relation between the mediator and the dependent variables when controlling for the independent variable. The first two relations were investigated using independent <italic>t</italic>-tests. The third relation was investigated using partial correlations, with group status, age and sex as covariates. Control for multiple comparisons was carried out using the Holm-Bonferroni method, which is a sequentially rejective version of the simple Bonferroni correction (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Holm, 1979</xref>).</p>
                <p>Next, we tested for simple and multiple mediation using <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">Preacher and Hayes' (2008)</xref> bootstrapping methodology for indirect effects based on 5000 bootstrap resamples. This method describes the confidence intervals (CI) of indirect effects such that no assumptions are made about the indirect effect being normally distributed. Interpretation of the bootstrap data is accomplished by determining whether zero is contained within the 95% CIs. This method has been argued to be superior to the commonly used Sobel test, as it has higher statistical power while maintaining adequate control over the Type I error rate (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">MacKinnon, Lockwood, Hoffman, West, &amp; Sheets, 2002</xref>). Age and sex were included as covariates. In line with previous studies (e.g., <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Anastopoulos et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Huang-Pollock et al., 2009</xref>), the percentage of the total effect explained by each mediator (i.e., the standardized estimate for the indirect effect divided by the standardized estimate for the total effect) was calculated as a measure of effect size in the mediation analyses.</p>
                <p>Finally, possible moderating effects of gender and comorbid ODD/CD were investigated. The main effects of gender and the interaction effects of ADHD status and gender were investigated by computing two-way ANCOVAs with ADHD status and gender as fixed factors, age as the covariate, and the neuropsychological and outcome measures as dependent variables. Next, we conducted a series of regression analyses in which one of the mediators and gender were entered in the first step and the interaction effect of these two variables in the second step. A non-significant interaction effect indicates that gender is not a significant moderator (i.e., the relation between the mediator and the outcome is equally strong for boys and girls). As concerns ODD/CD, ADHD children with or without comorbid ODD/CD were compared with the control group with regard to the measures of emotional functioning. Second, regression analyses were conducted in which the main effects of emotional functioning and group (ADHD with or without ODD/CD) were entered in the first step and the interaction effect of group and emotional functioning in the second step. A non-significant interaction effect indicates that the relation between emotional functioning and peer problems is equally strong for ADHD children with or without ODD/CD.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s11">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>Group differences were seen for all proposed mediators except delay aversion and recognition of disgust (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Significant group differences were also seen for all three outcome variables. Effect sizes were medium to large (d = .45–1.75) for the significant mediators and large (d = 1.02–1.60) for the outcome variables. All significant effects survived control for multiple testing.</p>
              <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
                <label>TABLE 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Means, Standard Deviations, Results of <italic>t</italic>-Tests, and Effect Sizes Comparing ADHD Children With Controls for All Main Variables in the Study (One-Tailed)</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>ADHD</italic>
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>Controls</italic>
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>Effect Size</italic>
                        <hr/>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>M(SD)</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>M(SD)</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>t</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>D</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Neuropsychological functions</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibition</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 (1.05)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.35 (0.71)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working memory</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (0.96)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.29 (0.94)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shifting</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (1.01)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.29 (0.84)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction time variability</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (1.06)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.51 (0.59)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.72<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delay aversion</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 (1.07)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09 (0.93)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Emotion regulation</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of sadness</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29 (1.00)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 (0.93)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.98<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of fear</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05 (1.17)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96 (0.86)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of anger</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43 (1.09)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 (0.72)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of happiness</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36 (1.06)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04 (0.89)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.60<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Emotion recognition</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of anger</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50 (1.37)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45 (0.82)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of fear</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77 (1.32)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64 (1.43)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of happiness</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20 (0.95)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.67 (0.59)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of sadness</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33 (1.01)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.76 (0.83)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of surprise</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70 (1.35)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.28 (1.21)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of disgust</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.20 (1.44)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.36 (1.31)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Functional impairments</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language skills</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34 (0.92)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34 (1.02)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mathematics</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44 (0.98)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47 (1.04)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peer problems</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57 (0.76)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 (0.50)</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1-FN1">***</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p><italic>Note.</italic> ADHD = attention deficit hyperactivity disorder.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1-FN1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Next, we investigated the relation between the mediators and the outcomes when controlling for ADHD status, sex, and age. Delay aversion and recognition of disgust were not included in these analyses, as group differences had not been found for these two variables. The results (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) showed that all three EFs as well as RT variability were significantly related to both areas of academic achievement but not to peer problems. In addition, recognition of anger and surprise were related to language skills, but none of the other emotion variables were related to academic achievement. Regulation of sadness, anger, fear and happiness, as well as recognition of anger, were significantly related to peer problems. When controlling for multiple comparisons (see boldfaced figures in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>), all relations except recognition of surprise remained significant for language skills and all relations except inhibition remained significant for mathematics. However, only regulation of anger remained significantly related to peer problems.</p>
              <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
                <label>TABLE 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Partial Correlations Between Mediators and Functional Impairments, Controlling for Group, Gender, and Age (One-Tailed)</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>Language Skills</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>Mathematics</italic>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>Peer Problems</italic>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Neuropsychological functions</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibition</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−.21</bold>
                        <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">**</xref>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">**</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.01</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working memory</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−.33</bold>
                        <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">***</xref>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−.41</bold>
                        <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">***</xref>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shifting</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−.19</bold>
                        <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">**</xref>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−.20</bold>
                        <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">**</xref>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.05</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction time variability</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−.26</bold>
                        <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">***</xref>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−.33</bold>
                        <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">***</xref>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>
                          <italic>Emotion regulation</italic>
                        </bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of sadness</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>.02</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.04</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of fear</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.05</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">*</xref></italic>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of anger</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.11</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>.20</bold>
                        <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">**</xref>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of happiness</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.11</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>
                          <italic>Emotion recognition</italic>
                        </bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of anger</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">**</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">*</xref></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of fear</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.12</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.02</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of happiness</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.10</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.09</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of sadness</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.10</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <italic>.03</italic>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.01</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of surprise</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2-FN1">*</xref></td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.11</td>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.07</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p><italic>Note.</italic> Bold-faced numbers indicate relations that remained significant when controlling for multiple comparisons. Cursive numbers indicate where a significant interaction effect with gender was found.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T2-FN1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <sec id="s12">
                <title>Simple Mediation</title>
                <p>Mediation was thereafter examined using the bootstrapping procedure presented by <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">Preacher and Hayes (2008)</xref>. Only variables for which the relation between the proposed mediator and the outcome was significant when controlling for ADHD status, and which survived control for multiple testing, were included in these analyses. Regarding language skills, simple mediation effects were found for all three EFs as well as for RT variability and recognition of anger (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Working memory, shifting and RT variability were significant mediators for mathematics, and regulation of anger was a significant mediator for peer problems. As also shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>, the significant mediators varied with regard to how much of the total effect they were able to explain. For example, shifting explained as little as 13% of the total effect of ADHD status on language skills, whereas the corresponding percentage for RT variability was 35%. Finally, all simple mediation analyses were re-run with control for IQ. As shown in a footnote to <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>, most of the mediation effects remained significant for the two measures of academic achievement, whereas regulation of anger remained significant for peer problems.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T3" position="float">
                  <label>TABLE 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Results of Simple Mediation, Including Estimates, Standard Errors (SE), and Confidence Intervals (CI); The Percentage of the Total Effect Is Also Reported</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>Estimate</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>SE</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>Lower CI</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>Upper CI</italic>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <italic>Indirect Effect %</italic>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
                          <bold>Language Skills</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibition</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0743</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0282</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1382</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0277<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN2">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working memory</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1098</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0342</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1862</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0507<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN2">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shifting</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0578</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0254</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1199</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0161<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction time variability</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1581</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0485</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.2594</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0685<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN2">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognition of anger</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0712</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0314</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1404</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0173<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN2">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
                          <bold>Mathematics</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working memory</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1289</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0360</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.2062</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0674<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN2">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shifting</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0600</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0244</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1178</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.0207<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction time variability</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1903</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0439</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.2837</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−.1102<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN2">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
                          <bold>Peer Problems</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of anger</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.1357</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0515</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0377</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.2455<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN1">*</xref><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3-FN2">a</xref></sup></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="T3-FN1">
                      <label>*</label>
                      <p>Significant mediator (i.e., zero is not contained within the confidence intervals).</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="T3-FN2">
                      <label>a</label>
                      <p>Indicate where a mediation is significant when controlling for IQ.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s13">
                <title>Multiple Mediation</title>
                <p>Multiple mediation analyses were conducted to obtain estimates of the total indirect effect, as well as the independent contribution of each mediator (i.e., the effect of each mediator when controlling for the effect of the other significant mediators in the model). Multiple mediation analysis was not performed for peer problems, as only one significant mediator (i.e., regulation of anger) had been identified for this variable. For the relation between ADHD status and language skills (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>), the mediators together explained 53% of the total effect (i.e., multiple β = .24 divided by the total effect β = .45), but only the effect of working memory was significant. For mathematics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>), the mediators together explained 54% of the total effect (i.e., multiple β = .25 divided by the total effect β = .46). Both working memory and RT variability had significant independent effects. As can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>, the direct effect of ADHD status on the dependent variables remained significant for both language skills and mathematics, which means that only partial mediation was demonstrated. Partial mediation was also demonstrated for peer problems (β = .63, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 for the direct path between ADHD and peer problems when the mediator was not included, and β = .49, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 when the effect of regulation of anger was taken into account).</p>
                <fig id="F1" position="float">
                  <label>FIGURE 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Multiple mediation models for the association between attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and academic achievement. Values on paths are standardized path coefficients (β). For the direct relation between ADHD and academic achievement, the value outside parentheses indicates the zero-order correlation, whereas the value inside parentheses indicates the partial correlation (i.e., the size of the direct effect when taking the effect of all mediators into account).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="hdvn39_187_f1"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s14">
                <title>Gender Effects and Effects of Comorbid ODD/CD</title>
                <p>Finally, two possible moderators were examined: gender and comorbid ODD/CD. With regard to gender, no significant main effects of gender and no significant interaction effects of ADHD status and gender were found for any of the neuropsychological variables. For the functional impairments, two significant main effects of gender were found. Girls had significantly lower scores than boys did in mathematics and they were rated as having higher levels of peer problems, but no main effects of gender were found for language skills. No significant interaction effects of ADHD status and gender were found for any of the functional impairments, which indicate that the obtained gender differences were equally large among children with and without ADHD.</p>
                <p>In order to determine whether the relation between the mediators and the outcomes were equally strong for boys and girls, we also examined interaction effects of gender and each one of the mediators (i.e., altogether 45 interaction effects, as the study involved 15 mediators and 3 outcomes). The results showed that only three interaction effects were significant (see boldfaced figures in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). When conducting separate mediation analyses for boys and girls for these three relations, the results for both genders were similar to the results reported above for the whole sample. Thus, gender was not found to be a significant moderator in our mediation models.</p>
                <p>Finally, we investigated ODD/CD as a potential moderator in the relation between emotional functioning and peer problems. The results showed that both ADHD subgroups (ADHD without ODD/CD and ADHD with ODD/CD) differed significantly from the control group with regard to peer problems and all measures of emotional functioning (all <italic>f</italic>s &gt; 4.66, and <italic>p</italic>s &lt; .05), except for recognition of disgust, for which none of the subgroups differed significantly from the controls (both <italic>fs</italic> &lt; .74, <italic>ns</italic>). Second, no interaction effects of ODD/CD and emotional functioning on peer problems were noted (all βs &lt; .14, <italic>ns</italic>). In conclusion, the relations between the different measures of emotional functioning and peer problems were equally strong in the two ADHD subgroups.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s15">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>The overall aim of the present study was to investigate the role of neuropsychological functioning in explaining the link between ADHD and functional impairments associated with the disorder. The main findings were that it was primarily deficits in working memory and RT variability that mediated the relation between ADHD and academic achievement and that regulation of anger mediated the relation between ADHD and peer problems. Neither gender nor symptoms of ODD/CD were shown to moderate these findings.</p>
              <sec id="s16">
                <title>Academic Achievement</title>
                <p>First, and in line with previous research, the present study showed that children with ADHD performed worse than controls on tests of executive functioning (e.g., <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Barkley, 1997</xref>), RT variability (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Castellanos et al., 2005</xref>), and were rated lower on academic achievement (e.g., <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Loe &amp; Feldman, 2007</xref>). Our results are also in line with previous findings showing that EF deficits in general are related to poor academic achievement (e.g., <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Biederman et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Diamantopoulou, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Miller &amp; Hinshaw, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">Thorell, 2007</xref>). By conducting formal mediation analyses, we extend previous findings by showing that all included EF deficits, as well as RT variability, were significant mediators in the relation between ADHD and poor academic achievement. However, only the effect of working memory for language skills, and the effects of RT variability and working memory for mathematics, remained significant when controlling for the overlap between different mediators. Yet another finding of the present study was that the neuropsychological predictors explained about 50% of the group difference in performance for the academic outcomes. This is to be considered a substantial effect given that the difference between ADHD and controls are large for academic achievement (cf. <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">Preacher &amp; Kelley, 2011</xref>). However, it also points out the need to find other possible mediators.</p>
                <p>The present study is, to our knowledge, the first to examine whether RT variability mediates the relation between academic achievement and ADHD. RT variability is believed to arise from an inability to mobilize an appropriate amount of energy in relation to what the task or the situation requires (<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">Sergeant, 2005</xref>). However, the exact nature of high RT variability in ADHD is still uncertain, and there has been some discussion as to whether RT variability should be regarded as inherent in other neuropsychological functions or whether it constitutes a unique entity (cf. <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Castellanos et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">Sonuga-Barke, Wiersema, van der Meere, &amp; Roeyers, 2010</xref>). Most previous findings support the latter interpretation, as RT variability has been shown to have an independent effect on ADHD when analyzed together with other candidate endophenotypes (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">Kuntsi, Oosterlaan, &amp; Stevenson, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">Sjöwall et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Wåhlstedt, Thorell, &amp; Bohlin, 2009</xref>). Here, we demonstrate that RT variability is independent of other neuropsychological deficits, also when examining the relation between ADHD and academic achievement.</p>
                <p>Altogether, the present findings emphasize the advantages of using multiple mediation models to provide a more in-depth understanding of the link between ADHD and poor academic achievement. Most importantly, this analytical approach has allowed us to investigate both the independent contributions and the cumulative effects of several different neuropsychological functions. For a more detailed account of the advantages of this statistical approach, please refer to <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">Preacher and Hayes (2008)</xref>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s17">
                <title>Peer Problems</title>
                <p>In line with previous research (e.g., <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">Hoza, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">McQuade &amp; Hoza, 2008</xref>), the present study showed that the children with ADHD were rated as having much more peer problems compared to the controls. Interestingly, regulation of anger was shown to be a mediator in the relation between ADHD and peer problems. This finding is in line with <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Anastopoulos and colleagues (2011)</xref>, who found that a measure of emotional liability mediated the relation between ADHD and social skills. However, our study also contributes new information. First, we show that the mediating effect of regulation of anger cannot be accounted for by other neuropsychological deficits. Second, we focused on emotion regulation specifically, rather than using a measure that includes both reactivity and regulation of emotions (<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">Mullin &amp; Hinshaw, 2007</xref>). Third, we investigated the effect of different emotions and were able to show that it is specifically regulation of anger, and not other emotions, that is related to peer problems. Fourth, comorbid ODD/CD did not moderate the relation between ADHD and peer problems (i.e., the relation between emotional functioning and peer problems was equally strong for ADHD children with or without ODD/CD).</p>
                <p>Our findings, showing a lack of significant relations between EFs and peer problems, are in line with previous research (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Biederman et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Diamantopoulou et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Huang-Pollock et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">Scholtens et al., 2012</xref>). However, they stand in contrast to results reported by Hinshaw and colleagues (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Miller &amp; Hinshaw, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">Rinsky &amp; Hinshaw, 2011</xref>), showing the involvement of EFs in peer functioning or social abilities more in general. In these two studies, the outcomes were measured in adolescence, and it is possible that well-functioning peer relations are more dependent on executive skills in adolescence than in childhood. In addition, these studies included only girls. However, the present results indicate that although boys and girls with ADHD may differ in the extent to which they develop different peer problems, the underlying neuropsychological deficits mediating the relation between ADHD and peer problems appear to be similar for both genders.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s18">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>Some limitations should be taken into consideration. First, no standardized clinical interview was used. Nonetheless, a licensed child psychiatrist conducted the diagnostic procedure, and all diagnoses were confirmed using teacher and parent ratings on a standardized rating instrument. In addition, the children's symptoms were reported to cause significant impairment in several settings, and both the duration and age-of-onset criteria were met. A second limitation was that peer problems were only assessed by ratings, and it would be of interest to try to replicate our findings using peer nominations. This was not possible in the present study as all children participating in the study were in different classrooms. Thus, with an average of about 25 children in each classroom, this would have resulted in more than 5,000 peer nominations. Third, the effect of comorbid ODD/CD was investigated in the present study, but it would have been interesting to also include other comorbidities such as learning disorder and autism spectrum disorder. Finally, it should be noted as a limitation that IQ was only assessed using one single measure.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s19">
              <title>CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE DIRECTIONS</title>
              <p>The present study provides further support for the importance of EF deficits in explaining poor academic achievement among children with ADHD. Within the EF construct, working memory was shown to be of primary importance. This calls for teaching strategies that better suit the needs of these children (e.g., giving one instruction at a time and repeating the important parts of longer instructions, <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">Raggi &amp; Chronis, 2006</xref>). In addition, computerized training programs have been shown to improve working memory (e.g., <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Klingberg et al., 2005</xref>) and there is also some evidence of enhanced mathematics ability after working memory training (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">Holmes, Gathercole, &amp; Dunning, 2009</xref>).</p>
              <p>Our findings also suggest that it is important to identify children with ADHD who have variable RTs. It has been suggested that variable RTs reflect difficulties maintaining attention while processing information. Specific adjustments in academic settings for children with variable RT have not been postulated but two aspects suggested to be of importance are rewards and the speed/intensity of presentation (cf. <xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">Tamm et al., 2012</xref>).</p>
              <p>With regard to peer problems, the present study added valuable information to this research field by showing that emotion regulation needs to be further acknowledged. Regulation of anger explained 22% of the effect of ADHD on peer problems. As pointed out by <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">Preacher and Kelley (2011)</xref>, it is generally more impressive to explain a smaller percentage of a large total effect compared to explaining a large percentage of a very small total effect. Thus, 22% should be considered important given that ADHD was so strongly related to peer problems. In addition, it has been shown that poor emotional functioning in children with ADHD has many other negative consequences besides the aspects investigated here (e.g., <xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">Wehmeier, Schacht, &amp; Barkley, 2010</xref>), indicating that future research on interventions aimed at improving emotional functioning is of great importance. However, it is also important to remember that a substantial part of the relation between ADHD and peer problems could not be explained by the neuropsychological variables included in the present study. Thus, future research needs to examine other possible mediators. In addition, it would be of interest to investigate neuropsychological functioning in relation to other aspects of peer relations (e.g., peer-rated social status), as well as different aspects of social functioning, in children diagnosed with ADHD.</p>
              <p>Building on our findings, future research needs to look beyond the executive function deficits that have been in focus in much of the ADHD research during the past decade and also include deficits in emotional functioning. In this line of research, it will be important to investigate what specific aspects of emotional functioning that are of greatest importance to ADHD and the functional impairments associated with this disorder. In research on executive functioning deficits, it has been fruitful to study independent effects of different functions such as working memory and inhibition rather than using composite measures that include many different functions. Similar attempts should be made in the area of emotional functioning in order to better differentiate between constructs such as emotional lability, emotional intensity, and emotion regulation. Finally, it will be important to use more person-oriented analyses to determine what specific cutoffs should be used to obtain the highest sensitivity and specificity when trying to predict different functional impairments in children with ADHD.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
              <p>Potential conflict of interests: Dr. Thorell has served as a consultant for Shire and is on the advisory board for Prima. Mr. Sjöwall has no potential conflict of interest to report.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>
                  <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</source>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <edition>4th ed.</edition>
                  <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anastopoulos</surname>
                      <given-names>A. D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>T. F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garrett</surname>
                      <given-names>M. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morrissey-Kane</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schatz</surname>
                      <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sommer</surname>
                      <given-names>J. L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ashley-Koch</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-regulation of emotion, functional impairment, and comorbidity among children with AD/HD</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Attention Disorder</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>583</fpage>
                  <lpage>92</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barkley</surname>
                      <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>ADHD and the nature of self-control</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barry</surname>
                      <given-names>T. D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lyman</surname>
                      <given-names>R. D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klinger</surname>
                      <given-names>L. G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Academic underachievement and attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: The negative impact of symptom severity on school performance</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of School Psychology</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <lpage>283</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berlin</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bohlin</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Response inhibition, hyperactivity, and conduct problems among preschool children</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Clinical Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <lpage>251</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Biederman</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Monuteaux</surname>
                      <given-names>M. C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Doyle</surname>
                      <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seidman</surname>
                      <given-names>L. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilens</surname>
                      <given-names>T. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferrero</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Faraone</surname>
                      <given-names>S. V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of executive function deficits and attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) on academic outcomes in children</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <fpage>757</fpage>
                  <lpage>766</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15482034</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brock</surname>
                      <given-names>L. L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rimm-Kaufman</surname>
                      <given-names>S. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nathanson</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grimm</surname>
                      <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The contributions of “hot” and “cool” executive function to children's academic achievement, learning-related behaviors, and engagement in kindergarten</article-title>
                  <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <lpage>349</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castellanos</surname>
                      <given-names>F. X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sonuga-Barke</surname>
                      <given-names>E. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Milham</surname>
                      <given-names>M. P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tannock</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Characterizing cognition in ADHD: Beyond executive dysfunction</article-title>
                  <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <lpage>123</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16460990</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castellanos</surname>
                      <given-names>F. X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sonuga-Barke</surname>
                      <given-names>E. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scheres</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Di Martino</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hyde</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walters</surname>
                      <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Varieties of attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder-related intra-individual variability</article-title>
                  <source>Biological Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>57</volume>
                  <fpage>1416</fpage>
                  <lpage>1423</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15950016</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daley</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Birchwood</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>ADHD and academic performance: Why does ADHD impact on academic performance and what can be done to support ADHD children in the classroom?</article-title>
                  <source>Child: Care, Health and Development</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
                  <lpage>464</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diamantopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rydell</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thorell</surname>
                      <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bohlin</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of executive functioning and symptoms of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder on children's peer relations and school performance</article-title>
                  <source>Developmental Neuropsychology</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>521</fpage>
                  <lpage>542</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17650992</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>DuPaul</surname>
                      <given-names>G. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Power</surname>
                      <given-names>T. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anastopoulos</surname>
                      <given-names>A. D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reid</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>ADHD rating scale- IV. Checklists, norms, and clinical interpretation</source>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eisenberg</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hofer</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vaughan</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gross</surname>
                      <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effortful control and its socioemotional consequences</article-title>
                  <source>Handbook of emotion regulation</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
                  <lpage>306</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodman</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Strength and difficulties questionnaire: A research note</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Child Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>581</fpage>
                  <lpage>586</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodman</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scott</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparing the strength and difficulties questionnaire and the child behavioral checklist: Is small beautiful?</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of abnormal child psychology</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <lpage>24</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10197403</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Groth-Marnat</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Handbook of psychological assessment</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <edition>3rd ed</edition>
                  <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Henricsson</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rydell</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Children with behaviour problems: The influence of social competence and social relations on problem stability, school achievement and peer acceptance across the first six years of school</article-title>
                  <source>Infant and Child Development</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
                  <lpage>66</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holm</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A simple sequentially rejective multiple test procedure</article-title>
                  <source>Scandinavian Journal of Statistics</source>
                  <year>1979</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <lpage>70</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holmes</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gathercole</surname>
                      <given-names>S. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dunning</surname>
                      <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Adaptive training leads to sustained enhancement of poor working memory in children. Developmental Science</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>F9</fpage>
                  <lpage>15</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoza</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Peer functioning in children with ADHD</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Pediatric Psychology</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>665</fpage>
                  <lpage>663</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang-Pollock</surname>
                      <given-names>C. L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mikami</surname>
                      <given-names>A. Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pfiffner</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McBurnett</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Can executive functions explain the relationship between attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and social adjustment?</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>679</fpage>
                  <lpage>91</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19184400</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kats-Gold</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Besser</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Priel</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of simple emotion recognition skills among school aged boys at risk of ADHD</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
                  <lpage>379</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17243015</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klingberg</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernell</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Olesen</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnson</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gustafsson</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dahlström</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Westerberg</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Computerized training of working memory in children with ADHD – A randomized, controlled trial</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <lpage>186</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15689731</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuntsi</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oosterlaan</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stevenson</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychological mechanisms in hyperactivity: Is response inhibition deficit, working memory impairment, delay aversion, or something else?</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, and Allied Disciplines</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <lpage>210</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lambek</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tannock</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dalsgaard</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trillingsgaard</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Damm</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thomsen</surname>
                      <given-names>P. H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validating neuropsychological subtypes of ADHD: How do children with and without an executive function deficit differ?</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <fpage>895</fpage>
                  <lpage>904</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20406332</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lan</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Legare</surname>
                      <given-names>C. H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pontiz</surname>
                      <given-names>C. C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morrison</surname>
                      <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Investigating the link between the subcomponents of executive function and academic achievement: A cross-cultural analysis of Chinese and American preschoolers</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Experimental Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>108</volume>
                  <fpage>677</fpage>
                  <lpage>692</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21238977</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Loe</surname>
                      <given-names>I. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feldman</surname>
                      <given-names>H. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Academic and educational outcomes of children with ADHD</article-title>
                  <source>Ambulatory Pediatrics</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <lpage>90</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17261487</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>MacKinnon</surname>
                      <given-names>D. P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lockwood</surname>
                      <given-names>C. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoffman</surname>
                      <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>West</surname>
                      <given-names>S. G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheets</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison of methods to test mediation and other intervening variable effects</article-title>
                  <source>Psychological Methods</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <lpage>104</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11928892</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maedgen</surname>
                      <given-names>J. W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carlson</surname>
                      <given-names>C. L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Social functioning and emotional regulation in the attention deficit hyperactivity disorder subtypes</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Clinical Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <lpage>42</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10693030</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martel</surname>
                      <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Research review: A new perspective on attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: Emotion dysregulation and trait models</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <fpage>1042</fpage>
                  <lpage>1051</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19508495</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McInerney</surname>
                      <given-names>R. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hrabok</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kerns</surname>
                      <given-names>K. A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The children's size-ordering task: A new measure of nonverbal working memory</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Clinical and Experimental Neuropsychology</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>735</fpage>
                  <lpage>745</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16019649</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McQuade</surname>
                      <given-names>J. D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoza</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Peer problems in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder: current status and future directions</article-title>
                  <source>Developmental Disabilities and Research Reviews</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>320</fpage>
                  <lpage>324</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miller</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hinshaw</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Does childhood executive function predict adolescent functional outcomes in girls with ADHD?</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <lpage>326</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19960365</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miller</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nevado-Montenegro</surname>
                      <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hinshaw</surname>
                      <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Childhood executive function continues to predict outcomes in young adult females with and without childhood diagnosed ADHD</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>657</fpage>
                  <lpage>668</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22124540</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miyake</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Friedman</surname>
                      <given-names>N. P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Emerson</surname>
                      <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Witzki</surname>
                      <given-names>A. H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Howerter</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The unity and diversity of executive functions and their contributions to complex “frontal lobe” tasks: A latent variable analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Cognitive Psychology</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <lpage>100</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10945922</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mostow</surname>
                      <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Izard</surname>
                      <given-names>C. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fine</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trentacosta</surname>
                      <given-names>C. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling emotional, cognitive, and behavioral predictors of peer acceptance</article-title>
                  <source>Child Development</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <fpage>1775</fpage>
                  <lpage>1787</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12487493</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mullin</surname>
                      <given-names>B. C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hinshaw</surname>
                      <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gross</surname>
                      <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Emotion regulation and externalizing disorders in children and adolescents</article-title>
                  <source>Handbook of emotion regulation</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>523</fpage>
                  <lpage>541</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R38">
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nigg</surname>
                      <given-names>J. T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>What causes ADHD? Understanding what goes wrong and why</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R39">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nigg</surname>
                      <given-names>J. T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Willcutt</surname>
                      <given-names>E. G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Doyle</surname>
                      <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sonuga-Barke</surname>
                      <given-names>E. J. S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Causal heterogeneity in attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: Do we need neuropsychologically impaired subtypes?</article-title>
                  <source>Biological Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>57</volume>
                  <fpage>1224</fpage>
                  <lpage>1230</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15949992</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R40">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Owens</surname>
                      <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Downes</surname>
                      <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sahakian</surname>
                      <given-names>B. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Polkey</surname>
                      <given-names>C. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Robbins</surname>
                      <given-names>T. W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Planning and spatial working memory following frontal lobe lesions in man</article-title>
                  <source>Neuropsychologica</source>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>1021</fpage>
                  <lpage>1034</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R41">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Preacher</surname>
                      <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayes</surname>
                      <given-names>A. F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Asymptotic and resampling strategies for assessing and comparing indirect effects in multiple mediator models</article-title>
                  <source>Behavior Research Methods</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>879</fpage>
                  <lpage>891</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18697684</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R42">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Preacher</surname>
                      <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kelley</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect size measures for mediation models: Quantitative strategies for communicating indirect effects</article-title>
                  <source>Psychological Methods</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <lpage>115</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21500915</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R43">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Raggi</surname>
                      <given-names>V. R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chronis</surname>
                      <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Interventions to address the academic impairment of children and adolescents with ADHD</article-title>
                  <source>Clinical Child and Family Psychology Review</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <lpage>111</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16972189</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R44">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rinsky</surname>
                      <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hinshaw</surname>
                      <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Linkages between childhood executive functioning and adolescent social functioning and psychopathology in girls with ADHD</article-title>
                  <source>Child Neuropsychology</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>368</fpage>
                  <lpage>390</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21390921</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R45">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rogers</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hwang</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Toplak</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weiss</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tannock</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Inattention, working memory, and academic achievement in adolescents referred for Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</article-title>
                  <source>Child Neuropsychology</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>444</fpage>
                  <lpage>458</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21390917</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R46">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rydell</surname>
                      <given-names>A-M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berlin</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bohlin</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Emotionality, emotion regulation, and adaption among five-to-eight-year old children</article-title>
                  <source>Emotion</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <lpage>47</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12899315</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R47">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rydell</surname>
                      <given-names>A-M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thorell</surname>
                      <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bohlin</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Emotion regulation in relation to social functioning: An investigation of child self-reports</article-title>
                  <source>European Journal of Developmental Psychology</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <lpage>313</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R48">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scholtens</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diamantopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tillman</surname>
                      <given-names>C. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rydell</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of symptoms of ADHD, ODD, and cognitive functioning on social acceptance and positive illusory bias in children</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Attention Disorders</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>685</fpage>
                  <lpage>696</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21868588</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R49">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sergeant</surname>
                      <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: A critical appraisal of the cognitive-energetic model</article-title>
                  <source>Biological Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>57</volume>
                  <fpage>1248</fpage>
                  <lpage>1255</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15949995</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R50">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sinzig</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Morsch</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lehmkuhl</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Do hyperactivity, impulsivity and inattention have an impact on the ability of facial affect recognition in children with autism and ADHD?</article-title>
                  <source>European Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <lpage>72</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17896119</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R51">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sjöwall</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roth</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lindqvist</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thorell</surname>
                      <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Multiple deficits in ADHD: Executive dysfunction, delay aversion, reaction time variability and emotional deficits</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <fpage>619</fpage>
                  <lpage>627</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23061803</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R52">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Solanto</surname>
                      <given-names>M. V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abikoff</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sonuga-Barke</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schachar</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Logan</surname>
                      <given-names>G. D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wigal</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Turkel</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The ecological validity of delay aversion and response inhibition as measures of impulsivity in AD/HD: A supplement to the NIMH multimodal treatment study of AD/HD</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <lpage>228</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11411784</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R53">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sonuga-Barke</surname>
                      <given-names>E. J. S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychological heterogeneity in AD/HD – A dual pathway model of behaviour and cognition</article-title>
                  <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>130</volume>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <lpage>36</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11864715</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R54">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sonuga-Barke</surname>
                      <given-names>E. J. S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taylor</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sembi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Hyperactivity and delay aversion I: The effect of delay on choice</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <lpage>398</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1564081</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R55">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sonuga-Barke</surname>
                      <given-names>E. J. S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wiersema</surname>
                      <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van der Meere</surname>
                      <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roeyers</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Context-dependent dynamic processes in attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder: Differentiating common and unique effects of state regulation deficits and delay aversion</article-title>
                  <source>Neuropsychological Review</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <lpage>102</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R56">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tamm</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Narad</surname>
                      <given-names>E. M. E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Antonini</surname>
                      <given-names>T. N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                      <given-names>K. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hawk</surname>
                      <given-names>L. W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Epstein</surname>
                      <given-names>J. N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reaction time variability in ADHD: A review</article-title>
                  <source>Neurotherapeutics</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>500</fpage>
                  <lpage>508</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930417</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R57">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thorell</surname>
                      <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Do delay aversion and executive function deficits make distinct contributions to the functional impact of ADHD symptoms? A study of early academic skill deficits</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <fpage>1061</fpage>
                  <lpage>1070</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17995481</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R58">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thorell</surname>
                      <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Veleiro</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siu</surname>
                      <given-names>A. F. Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mohammadi</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Examining the relation between ratings of executive functioning and academic achievement: Findings from a cross-cultural study</article-title>
                  <source>Child Neuropsychology</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>630</fpage>
                  <lpage>638</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23075095</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R59">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tottenham</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tanaka</surname>
                      <given-names>J. W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leon</surname>
                      <given-names>A. C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McCarry</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nurse</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hare</surname>
                      <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nelson</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The NimStim set of facial expressions: Judgments from untrained research participants</article-title>
                  <source>Psychiatry Research</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>168</volume>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <lpage>249</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564050</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R60">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wåhlstedt</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thorell</surname>
                      <given-names>L. B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bohlin</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Heterogeneity in ADHD: Neuropsychological pathways, comorbidity and symptom domains</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>551</fpage>
                  <lpage>564</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19016322</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R61">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walcott</surname>
                      <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Landau</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The relation between disinhibition and emotion regulation in boys with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Clinical Child and Adolescent Psychology</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <fpage>772</fpage>
                  <lpage>782</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15498744</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R62">
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wechsler</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Wechsler intelligence scale for children</source>
                  <year>1991</year>
                  <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R63">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wehmeier</surname>
                      <given-names>P. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schacht</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barkley</surname>
                      <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Social and emotional impairment in children and adolescents with ADHD and the impact on quality of life</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Adolescent Health</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>46</volume>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <lpage>17</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20159496</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R64">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuill</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lyon</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Selective difficulty in recognizing facial expressions of emotion in boys with ADHD. General performance impairments or specific problems in social cognition</article-title>
                  <source>European Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>398</fpage>
                  <lpage>404</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17401608</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
