<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-07T13:06:46Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4697303" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4697303</identifier>
        <datestamp>2016-01-31</datestamp>
        <setSpec>cambridgeopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Psychol Med</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Psychol Med</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PSM</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Psychological Medicine</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0033-2917</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1469-8978</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4697303</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4697303</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4697303</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26647849</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291715002007</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0033291715002007</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00200</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Intrusive memories to traumatic footage: the neural basis of their encoding
and involuntary recall</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">I. A. Clark et al.</alt-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Intrusive memories to traumatic
footage</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Clark</surname>
                    <given-names>I. A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fns01">†</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Holmes</surname>
                    <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Woolrich</surname>
                    <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mackay</surname>
                    <given-names>C. E.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Psychiatry</addr-line>,
<institution>University of Oxford</institution>, <addr-line>Warneford
Hospital</addr-line>, <addr-line>Oxford OX3 7NG</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Medical Research Council Cognition and Brain
Sciences Unit</addr-line>, <addr-line>15 Chaucer Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Cambridge
CB2 7EF</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Division of Psychology</addr-line>,
<addr-line>Department of Clinical Neuroscience</addr-line>, <institution>Karolinska
Institutet</institution>, <addr-line>Stockholm</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Psychiatry</addr-line>,
<institution>Oxford Centre for Human Brain Activity (OHBA)</institution>,
<addr-line>Warneford Hospital</addr-line>, <addr-line>Oxford OX3 7NG</addr-line>,
<country>UK</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><addr-line>Address for correspondence: C. E.
Mackay</addr-line>, <addr-line>Department of Psychiatry</addr-line>,
<institution>University of Oxford</institution>, <addr-line>Warneford
Hospital</addr-line>, <addr-line>Warneford Lane</addr-line>,
<addr-line>Oxford</addr-line>, <addr-line>OX3 7NG</addr-line>. (Email: <email>clare.mackay@psych.ox.ac.uk</email>)</corresp>
                <fn fn-type="present-address" id="fns01">
                  <label>†</label>
                  <p>Present address: Wellcome Trust Centre for Neuroimaging, Institute of Neurology,
University College London, 12 Queen Square, London WC1N 3BG, UK.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2016</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>46</volume>
              <issue>3</issue>
              <fpage>505</fpage>
              <lpage>518</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2014</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2015</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>11</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2015</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Cambridge University Press 2015</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Cambridge University Press</copyright-holder>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits
unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original
work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0033291715002007a.pdf"/>
              <abstract abstract-type="normal">
                <sec id="sec_a1">
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p>A hallmark symptom after psychological trauma is the presence of intrusive memories. It
is unclear why only some moments of trauma become intrusive, and how these memories
involuntarily return to mind. Understanding the neural mechanisms involved in the
encoding and involuntary recall of intrusive memories may elucidate these questions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec_a2" sec-type="methods">
                  <title>Method</title>
                  <p>Participants (<italic>n</italic> = 35) underwent functional magnetic resonance imaging
(fMRI) while being exposed to traumatic film footage. After film viewing, participants
indicated within the scanner, while undergoing fMRI, if they experienced an intrusive
memory of the film. Further intrusive memories in daily life were recorded for 7 days.
After 7 days, participants completed a recognition memory test. Intrusive memory
encoding was captured by comparing activity at the time of viewing ‘Intrusive scenes’
(scenes recalled involuntarily), ‘Control scenes’ (scenes never recalled involuntarily)
and ‘Potential scenes’ (scenes recalled involuntarily by others but not that
individual). Signal change associated with intrusive memory involuntary recall was
modelled using finite impulse response basis functions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec_a3" sec-type="results">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>We found a widespread pattern of increased activation for Intrusive <italic>v</italic>.
both Potential and Control scenes at encoding. The left inferior frontal gyrus and
middle temporal gyrus showed increased activity in Intrusive scenes compared with
Potential scenes, but not in Intrusive scenes compared with Control scenes. This pattern
of activation persisted when taking recognition memory performance into account.
Intrusive memory involuntary recall was characterized by activity in frontal regions,
notably the left inferior frontal gyrus.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec_a4" sec-type="conclusion">
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>The left inferior frontal gyrus may be implicated in both the encoding and involuntary
recall of intrusive memories.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Key words</title>
                <kwd>Dorsolateral prefrontal cortex</kwd>
                <kwd>flashbacks</kwd>
                <kwd>functional magnetic resonance imaging</kwd>
                <kwd>intrusive memories</kwd>
                <kwd>left inferior frontal gyrus</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="3"/>
                <table-count count="2"/>
                <ref-count count="72"/>
                <page-count count="14"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>The majority of people will experience or witness a traumatic event during their lifetime
and a significant minority will develop post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) (Breslau
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; American Psychiatric Association, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). A hallmark symptom of PTSD is the occurrence of
intrusive memories – involuntary images of the trauma intruding into consciousness (Brewin,
<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). We lack understanding of why only some
moments within a trauma are (re)experienced as intrusive memories and how these moments
involuntarily return to mind. Processing at the time of trauma (peritraumatic processing) –
i.e. during memory encoding – has been implicated in both later PTSD and intrusive memory
development (Ehlers &amp; Clark, <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Ozer
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; American Psychiatric Association, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Brewin, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Investigating the neural mechanisms during encoding may add to our
understanding of intrusive memories. The current study investigated a hypothesized neural
‘signature’ during the encoding of an experimental analogue of trauma (Bourne <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and the involvement of this signature in
later intrusive memory involuntary recall.</p>
              <p>Due to the nature of PTSD, the wealth of neuroimaging work has been conducted in PTSD
patients with established symptoms (Lanius <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Hughes &amp; Shin, <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Such research has often used symptom provocation paradigms,
which involve exposing PTSD patients to reminders of their trauma while undergoing
neuroimaging (Rauch <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Shin <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>, <xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, <xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Lanius <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Hughes &amp; Shin, <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Neurocircuitry models from this work suggest that PTSD is
characterized by increased amygdala (and other limbic) activation and reduced ventromedial
prefrontal cortex activation (Rauch <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>, <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). A recent model by Admon <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) suggested that abnormalities in the amygdala and dorsal anterior
cingulate cortex are predisposing, while abnormal interactions between the hippocampus and
ventromedial prefrontal cortex arise after developing PTSD (Admon <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). However, patient studies can tell us little
about how intrusive memories are formed since they cannot examine the original encoding of
the trauma.</p>
              <p>Studying the neural correlates of real-life trauma is unfeasible, but intrusive memories
can be experimentally induced using an experimental analogue – the trauma film paradigm
(Lazarus, <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">1964</xref>; Holmes &amp; Bourne, <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Participants view footage of real-life scenes of
death and serious injury, in line with the fifth edition of the Diagnostic and Statistical
Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5; American Psychiatric Association, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) definition for psychological trauma. Combining the trauma film
with neuroimaging allows a prospective design to study intrusive memory encoding and
involuntary recall.</p>
              <p>We recently conducted, to our knowledge, the only study to date investigating the neural
basis of intrusive memory encoding (Bourne <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Results suggested a widespread neural
signature at the time of viewing scenes that later became intrusive memories, including
increases in activation in the amygdala, striatum, rostral anterior cingulate cortex,
thalamus and ventral occipital cortex.</p>
              <p>In particular, two regions (and only these) seemed to distinguish between scenes that
became intrusive memories for an individual and scenes that had the ‘potential’ to become
intrusive memories (i.e. scenes of emotional content recalled involuntarily by some
participants, but not that individual); the left inferior frontal gyrus (IFG) and middle
temporal gyrus (MTG) (Bourne <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). These results at encoding partially mirror
the ‘subsequent memory effect’ found in non-traumatic memory (Paller &amp; Wagner, <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Kensinger &amp; Corkin, <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). The subsequent memory effect suggests predictive differences at
encoding for items that are later deliberately recalled relative to items that are not
recalled in left prefrontal regions and bilateral middle temporal regions – areas that
include the left IFG and MTG. We therefore sought to ask whether these two regions would
also predict moments of the film that would be recalled involuntarily. Another possible
explanation for our previous results is that intrusive memory scenes were simply better
recognized than potential scenes. These encoding results require replication, and
additionally for recognition memory to be taken into account.</p>
              <p>Our second question concerns the neural basis of intrusive memory involuntary recall. To
our knowledge, no study has captured the neural activation at the moment of intrusive memory
involuntary recall – that is, the moment when a participant experiences an intrusive memory
while undergoing functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). Symptom provocation studies
indicate increased activity in limbic and paralimbic areas, suggesting that these regions
may be involved in intrusive memory involuntary recall (Rauch <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Liberzon <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Shin <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Osuch <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). However, while patients may (or may not)
experience intrusive memories during scanning, the neural mechanisms of their involuntary
recall remain unknown as an intrusive memory could have occurred at any point during symptom
provocation. Further, other symptoms with different underpinning may be implicated during
symptom provocation (Bryant <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Pietrzak <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In a separate vein, one study using healthy
participants has shown that the involuntary recall of picture stimuli, compared with their
voluntary recall, has been associated with the middle and superior frontal gyri (Hall
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Whether these results can be extrapolated to
intrusive memories of traumatic stimuli is unknown.</p>
              <p>We note that part of the data acquired and presented here (the fMRI data concerning
encoding) is also used elsewhere (Clark <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) in combination with our previous work (Bourne
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Using different analysis techniques we
attempted to investigate a second separate question – one of prediction instead of
association. That is, could we ‘learn’ the brain activity associated with later intrusive
memories in order to predict, from new unseen brain activity, ‘future’ intrusive memories?
On the other hand, here, we report the differences in brain activity during scenes that were
later recalled involuntarily by that participant (intrusive scenes), compared with scenes
recalled involuntarily by previous participants, but not that individual (potential scenes).
The work presented in the present paper therefore attempts to identify regions that may
differentiate between intrusive and potential scenes. Our parallel work (Clark <italic>et
al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) attempts to quantify the extent that solely
the peritraumatic brain activity can predict intrusive memories. Thus, although we recognize
that we use the same component of the dataset in two different papers, we use it to address
two distinctly different questions.</p>
              <p>The current experiment investigated the encoding and involuntary recall of intrusive
memories of experimental trauma. We first sought to replicate our previous findings of
widespread increases in neural activation at the time of viewing scenes that caused
intrusive memories relative to scenes that did not. Specifically, we predicted that
activation in the left IFG and MTG would distinguish intrusive memory scenes from
‘Potential’ scenes (scenes of emotional content recalled involuntarily by previous
participants, but not that individual). Further, to take into account possible signal
changes due to better recognition memory for intrusive compared with potential scenes, we
reconfigured the fMRI time series into film ‘stills’ to repeat our encoding analysis using
only correctly recognized film picture stills. Finally, we sought to investigate the neural
mechanisms of intrusive memory involuntary recall, modelling brain activity while
participants experienced an intrusive memory during fMRI. To adaptively capture the moment
of involuntary recall we modelled the fMRI time series data using finite impulse response
basis functions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2">
              <title>Method</title>
              <sec id="sec2-1" sec-type="subjects">
                <title>Participants</title>
                <p>A total of 41 participants were recruited from the local community. Data could not be
analysed for six participants (online Supplementary material). This left 35 participants
(mean age = 22.43 years, <sc>s.d.</sc> = 7.52; 29 female, six male) with no reported
current or previous psychiatric history. The study was approved by the University of
Oxford Central University Research Ethics Committee. All participants provided written
informed consent and were reimbursed £25 (US $40).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-2">
                <title>Behavioural measures</title>
                <sec id="sec2-2-1">
                  <title>Trauma film viewing</title>
                  <p>The experimental procedure is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>.
After completing baseline and mood measures (online Supplementary material) participants
viewed traumatic film footage, including scenes of actual and threatened death and
serious injury, while undergoing fMRI. The film comprised 15 short clips which included
20 Possible intrusive scenes and 16 Control scenes. Scene type was determined using data
from approximately 200 participants who had taken part in previous behavioural
experiments. ‘Possible’ scenes were scenes that had induced intrusive memories in
previous participants (e.g. emergency personnel at an accident with an injured victim),
‘Control’ scenes were those that had never induced intrusive memories (e.g. emergency
personnel around the accident but no visible death or injury). Possible scenes were
later classified as either ‘Intrusive’ scenes (recalled involuntarily by that
participant) or ‘Potential’ scenes (not recalled involuntarily by that participant, but
recalled involuntarily by previous participants) depending on the diary data (see
Intrusive memory diary below). All scenes had unique topic content to facilitate
intrusive memory identification. Scene length was matched as closely as possible between
Possible (length, 5–37 s; mean 22.5 s) and Control scenes (length, 5–36 s; mean 16.4 s)
(<italic>t</italic><sub>34</sub> = 1.94, <sc>n.s</sc>.); see the online Supplementary
material (online Supplementary Tables S1 and S2) for the exact duration of each scene.
Scenes were distributed evenly throughout the whole film. These constraints were
included to take into account the relative slowness of the haemodynamic response (Buxton
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). <fig id="fig01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Experimental procedure. Participants completed baseline questionnaires and
measures of their current mood. They then viewed film footage with traumatic
content, including scenes of death and serious injury, while undergoing functional
magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). On film completion participants were removed
from the scanner and mood measurements were administered. Participants were then
trained to identify intrusive memories. They were then returned to the scanner
indicating with a button press if they experienced an intrusive memory of the film
while undergoing fMRI. For the following week participants kept a diary of any
further intrusive memories, returning at 1 week to perform a recognition memory
test of the film contents. BDI-II, Beck Depression Inventory-II; STAI-T,
State–Trait Anxiety Inventory, trait scale; VAS, visual analogue scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715002007_fig1"/></fig></p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec2-2-2">
                  <title>Intrusive memory involuntary recall during fMRI</title>
                  <p>On film completion, participants were briefly removed from the scanner to complete mood
ratings. As per previous trauma film paradigm experiments (Holmes <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>), participants were instructed as how to
identify intrusive memories – defined as: (1) moments of the film spontaneously popping
into mind unexpectedly (rather than the participant purposefully recalling the film);
and (2) mental images, e.g. taking the form of pictures or sounds.</p>
                  <p>Participants then returned into the scanner. Participants were asked to lie in the
scanner for 6 min and respond with a button press if they experienced an intrusive
memory of the film (i.e. if the film spontaneously popped into their mind). To minimize
experimental demands, it was made clear to the participants that they may – or may not –
experience any intrusive memories during the scan. This allowed us to capture the moment
of intrusive memory involuntary recall while participants were in the scanner undergoing
fMRI.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec2-2-3">
                  <title>Intrusive memory diary</title>
                  <p>Participants kept a daily intrusive memory diary for the following week (Holmes
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Participants were asked to write the
content of any intrusive memory (e.g. the car hitting the boy) and their emotional
rating of the intrusive memory, from 1 ‘very negative’ to 5 ‘very positive’. All content
descriptions were checked to confirm they matched a specific film scene. Intrusive
memories experienced during the intrusive memory involuntary recall scan were included
in the diary. From the diary Intrusive and Potential scenes we derived from the Possible
scenes retrospectively for each participant. That is, ‘Intrusive’ scenes were those
matched with the involuntary memories reported in the diary, and ‘Potential’ scenes were
the remaining Possible scenes that did not return as intrusive memories for that
participant.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec2-2-4">
                  <title>Film still recognition memory test</title>
                  <p>At 1 week post-film viewing participants performed a yes/no recognition memory test
containing 201 picture stills; 103 from the film (51 from Control scenes, 52 from
Potential and Intrusive scenes) and 98 foils – see the online Supplementary
material.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-3">
                <title>fMRI data acquisition</title>
                <p>All fMRI imaging data (trauma film viewing and intrusive memory involuntary recall) were
acquired on a 3-T Siemens TIM Trio System with a 12-channel head coil (voxel
resolution = 3 × 3 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup>; repetition time = 3 s; echo time = 30 ms).
T1-weighted structural images were acquired for subject registration using a magnetization
prepared rapid gradient echo (MPRAGE) sequence (voxel
resolution = 1 × 1 × 1 mm<sup>3</sup>; repetition time = 2040 ms; echo time = 4.7 ms).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-4">
                <title>fMRI data analysis</title>
                <p>Analyses were performed using FEAT (fMRI Expert Analysis Tool) version 6.0 (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl">http://www.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl</uri>). Data were pre-processed using FEAT's default
options: motion correction applied using MCFLIRT and fieldmaps with an echo planar imaging
(EPI) spacing of 0.49 ms and echo time of 22 ms; Gaussian spatial smoothing applied with a
full width half maximum of 5 mm; brain matter separated from non-brain using a mesh
deformation approach; high-pass temporal filtering applied with a cut-off of 100 s.</p>
                <sec id="sec2-4-1">
                  <title>Intrusive memory encoding</title>
                  <p>Analysis was performed at a whole-brain level. The three event types (Intrusive,
Potential, Control) were specified for each participant in the general linear model with
a fourth variable of no interest to model text slides (which provided information
concerning each film clip). The model was applied voxel-wise to the pre-processed
imaging data. First-level within-subject analysis was performed using FILM (FMRIB's
Improved Linear Model). Voxel-wise group analysis was performed in Montreal Neurological
Institute (MNI) 152 standard space using FLAME (FMRIB's Local Analysis of Mixed Effects)
stage 1 (Beckmann <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Woolrich <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref72" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Woolrich, <xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). <italic>z-</italic>Statistic images were thresholded at
<italic>z</italic> &gt; 2.3 and a family-wise error corrected cluster significance
threshold of <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (Forman <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>).</p>
                  <p>Following whole-brain analysis, percentage blood oxygen level-dependent (BOLD) signal
change was extracted from the left IFG and MTG using predefined regions of interest
(ROIs). The left IFG and MTG were defined as regions that were significantly activated
in the Bourne <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>)
results on a whole-brain basis in the Intrusive (referred to as Flashback)
<italic>v</italic>. Potential contrast, but not for the Intrusive <italic>v</italic>.
Control contrast.</p>
                  <p>To control for any effect of Intrusive scenes being better recognized than Potential
scenes we performed an additional analysis (as above) using only Intrusive recognized
picture stills and Potential recognized picture stills (identified by the recognition
memory test) with each still modelled for 0.5 s.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec2-4-2">
                  <title>Intrusive memory involuntary recall</title>
                  <p>We recruited nine additional participants to act as a control group (online
Supplementary material). Participants underwent a 6 min scan randomly pressing a button
approximately 5–10 times.</p>
                  <p>Analysis was performed at the whole-brain level. For both groups (intrusive memory
involuntary recall and control button press) 3-s wide (the repetition time) finite
impulse response (FIR) basis functions modelled consecutive ‘time bins’ surrounding the
button press (Diederen <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). To take into account the approximate 6 s
delay in haemodynamic response, the time bins were placed from −3 to +12 s in relation
to the button press – resulting in five time bins for each button press. The five time
bins were entered into a single general linear model and applied to the pre-processed
data in FILM for each participant. The FIR basis function was modelled as a single basis
function with a 0 s phase shift and 3 s time window. Exploratory group-wise analysis was
performed at the whole-brain level in MNI standard space using FLAME with
<italic>z</italic> statistic images thresholded at <italic>z</italic> &gt; 1.7 and a
family-wise error-corrected cluster significance threshold of
<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
                  <p>Following whole-brain analysis, percentage BOLD signal change was extracted from ROIs
showing significant activation in the intrusive memory involuntary recall
<italic>v</italic>. control button press contrast and the reverse contrast in any of the
time bins. Additional signal change was extracted from the precentral gyrus to compare
motor activity. The precentral gyrus was created from the Oxford–Harvard cortical and
subcortical probabilistic anatomical atlas thresholded at a minimum probability of
20%.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2-5">
                <title>Ethical standards</title>
                <p>All procedures contributing to this work comply with the ethical standards of the
relevant national and institutional committees on human experimentation and with the
Helsinki Declaration of 1975, as revised in 2008.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="sec3-1">
                <title>Behavioural results</title>
                <p>Baseline measures and mood change are reported in the online Supplementary material.</p>
                <p>In terms of the main outcome of interest, participants reported a total of 303 intrusive
memories that could be matched in content to the film from the 1-week diary and in the
scanner soon after film viewing (mean per participant = 8.66, <sc>s.d.</sc> = 7.15). A
further 13 intrusive memories could not be matched to the film (95.9% did match) and were
not included in analyses. The mean emotion rating of the intrusive memories was 2.15
(<sc>s.d.</sc> = 0.45), suggesting that participants found their intrusive memories
negative.</p>
                <p>The number of different scene types per person was the variable of interest for the fMRI
analysis. The mean number of Intrusive scenes per participant was 3.09
(<sc>s.d.</sc> = 1.46), leaving a mean number of Potential scenes (from the 20 possible
scenes) of 16.91 (<sc>s.d.</sc> = 1.46). The number of Control scenes was pre-determined
at 16 per participant.</p>
                <p>On the recognition memory test at 1 week, in our set, Intrusive picture stills were
better recognized than Potential picture stills (83.04%, <sc>s.d.</sc> = 13.89; 64.07%,
<sc>s.d.</sc> = 14.97, respectively; <italic>t</italic><sub>34</sub> = 6.76,
<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). For further information, see the online Supplementary
material.</p>
                <p>In the scanner soon after film viewing, 25 participants reported intrusive memories of
the film, totalling 148 intrusive memories (mean frequency = 5.92, <sc>s.d.</sc> = 4.08;
mean number different intrusive memory scenes = 2.36, <sc>s.d.</sc> = 1.37). The nine
control participants had a mean number of button presses of 7.89
(<sc>s.d.</sc> = 2.15).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3-2">
                <title>fMRI results</title>
                <sec id="sec3-2-1">
                  <title>Intrusive memory encoding</title>
                  <p>Whole-brain analysis comparing Intrusive with Potential (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>a</italic></xref>, top row) and Control scenes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>a</italic></xref>, middle row) revealed
widespread increases in activation, including the putamen, rostral anterior cingulate
cortex, insula, thalamus and ventral occipital cortex. Signal change extracted from
predefined ROIs showed, as predicted, differences in activation in the MTG and left IFG
between Intrusive and Potential scenes but not between Intrusive and Control scenes
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>b</italic></xref>). Comparison of
Potential scenes with Control scenes at the whole-brain level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>a</italic></xref> bottom row) revealed increased activation
in the thalamus and ventral occipital cortex. <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab01">Table
1</xref> shows peak voxel coordinates. <fig id="fig02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Neural basis of intrusive memory encoding. (<italic>a</italic>) Whole-brain
analysis of the encoding of Intrusive <italic>v</italic>. Potential
<italic>v</italic>. Control scenes, increased blood oxygen level-dependent (BOLD)
responses in colour for each contrast. (<italic>b</italic>) Region-of-interest
(ROI) analysis for the left inferior frontal gyrus (IFG) and middle temporal gyrus
(MTG) showing the BOLD percentage signal change for Intrusive and Potential scenes
relative to Control scenes. (<italic>c</italic>) Whole-brain analysis of the
encoding of Intrusive recognized <italic>v</italic>. Potential recognized,
increased BOLD response shown in colour. (<italic>d</italic>) ROI analysis for the
left IFG and MTG showing the BOLD percentage signal change for Intrusive
recognized and Potential recognized picture stills. Values are means, with
standard deviations represented by vertical bars. R, Right; L, left.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715002007_fig2"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="tab01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Peak voxel coordinates identified in the whole-brain intrusive memory encoding
analysis<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn1_1"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715002007_tab1"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster size</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>x</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>y</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic>-Statistic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intrusive &gt; potential</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left putamen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left precuneus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left insular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left middle temporal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left caudate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intrusive &gt; control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior temporal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 347</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.37</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left supramarginal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left caudate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right thalamus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potential &gt; control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left occipital fusiform gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 148</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right supramarginal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left lingual gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left temporal occipital fusiform cortex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior parietal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right thalamus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">939</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left thalamus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right caudate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior frontal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">769</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right middle frontal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left superior frontal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">625</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left precentral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right frontal pole</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">572</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right frontal orbital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain stem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">528</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left thalamus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior cingulate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hippocampus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" colspan="1">Intrusive
recognized &gt; potential recognized</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left putamen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left frontal orbital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right putamen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1_1"><label>a</label><p>Brain regions identified using the Oxford–Harvard cortical and subcortical
anatomical atlas.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                  <p>Behavioural results on the recognition memory test highlighted that Intrusive picture
stills were better recognized than Potential picture stills. Further comparison of the
neuroimaging data was therefore made using only those Intrusive and Potential picture
stills correctly recognized as from the film to control for any neural effects that
could be explained by this better recognition memory. Results show a similar pattern of
activation as to the original Intrusive <italic>v</italic>. Potential analysis at both
whole-brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>c</italic></xref>) and ROI
level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2<italic>d</italic></xref>). <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab01">Table 1</xref> shows peak voxel coordinates. See also
online Supplementary material and Fig. S1.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec3-2-2">
                  <title>Intrusive memory involuntary recall</title>
                  <p>Whole-brain analyses using the five time bins compared activation during intrusive
memory involuntary recall (i.e. involuntary recall in the scanner soon after film
viewing) and the control button press (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig.
3<italic>a</italic></xref>; peak voxel coordinates in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab02">Table 2</xref>). Increased activation for the intrusive memory involuntary
recall group compared with the control button press group was seen in middle and
superior frontal regions between 0 and 3 s and in the left IFG and bilateral operculum
between 3 and 6 s. Increased activation for the reverse contrast was seen between 6 and
9 s. No suprathreshold activation was found for either contrast between −3 and 0, and
9–12 s. <fig id="fig03" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Intrusive memory involuntary recall. (<italic>a</italic>) Whole-brain analysis
showing the increased blood oxygen level-dependent (BOLD) response for intrusive
memory involuntary recall <italic>v</italic>. control button press group at the
two time bins (0–3 s and 3–6 s in relation to the button press) showing
significant differences in activation, and the one time bin (6–9 s) showing
increased BOLD response for the control button press group <italic>v</italic>.
intrusive memory involuntary recall. (<italic>b</italic>) Region-of-interest
profile plots of the signal change observed across each time bin from −3 to +12 s
in relation to the button press. Intrusive memory involuntary recall signal change
activation is shown in pink, control button press signal change activation in
light blue. Values are means, with standard deviations represented by vertical
bars. IFG, Inferior frontal gyrus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715002007_fig3"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="tab02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Peak voxel coordinates identified in the whole-brain intrusive memory involuntary
recall analysis<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn2_1"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715002007_tab2"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster size</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>x</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>y</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Z</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic>-Statistic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Intrusion &gt; control; 0–3 s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left middle frontal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4312</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right postcentral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superior frontal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right precentral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" valign="top" colspan="1">Intrusion &gt; control; 3–6 s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior frontal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right postcentral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right middle frontal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right central opercular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left frontal operculum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior frontal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left central opercular</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left frontal orbital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior frontal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8" valign="top" colspan="1">Control &gt; intrusion; 6–9 s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right middle frontal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right frontal pole</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right postcentral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left lingual gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2324</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right supracalcarine cortex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior parietal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right lateral occipital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right intracalcarine cortex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn2_1"><label>a</label><p>Brain regions identified using the Oxford–Harvard cortical and subcortical
anatomical atlas.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                  <p>Signal change was extracted from ROIs showing significant activation at the whole-brain
level and the precentral gyrus. BOLD signal activation profile plots are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3<italic>b</italic></xref>. The BOLD signal response
in the precentral gyrus followed the same pattern in both groups; peaking during the
time bin modelling 3–6 s after the button press. This peak (expected due to the delay in
BOLD signal response) suggests successful modelling of changes in activation by the
finite impulse response basis functions.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The current study investigated the neural basis of the encoding and involuntary recall of
intrusive memories to film footage of traumatic events. We found a widespread pattern of
increased activation at the encoding of Intrusive scenes (emotional scenes that were
involuntarily recalled) compared with both Potential scenes (emotional scenes that were not
involuntarily recalled by that participant but were previously by other participants) and
Control scenes (scenes that were never involuntarily recalled). As predicted, the left IFG
and MTG showed increased activity between Intrusive <italic>v</italic>. Potential scenes,
but not Intrusive <italic>v</italic>. Control scenes. These areas may potentially
distinguish whether a scene which is traumatic in content will intrude or not.</p>
              <p>The encoding findings provide a strong replication of our previous work (Bourne <italic>et
al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) in a new sample. In addition to the previous
work and importantly, we were able to show that while Intrusive picture stills were better
recognized than Potential picture stills, analysis using only recognized picture stills
revealed the same pattern of brain activation.</p>
              <p>The fMRI involuntary recall findings captured the neural activation at the moment of
intrusive memory involuntary recall (that is, experiencing an intrusive memory in the
scanner) indicating involvement of the middle and superior frontal cortices, operculum and
left IFG. The left IFG was the only region to be involved in both intrusive memory encoding
and involuntary recall.</p>
              <sec id="sec4-1">
                <title>Intrusive memory encoding</title>
                <p>Results provide support for a neural signature at the time of viewing those scenes from
footage of traumatic events that later return as an intrusive memory. By comparing
activation during Intrusive and Potential picture stills that were recognized at 1 week,
we are able to suggest that the differential activation between Intrusive and Potential
scenes was not merely due to participants having better recognition memory for Intrusive
scenes. That is, we know that all the picture stills used in the analysis were recognized
by participants. Neural activation found from comparing intrusive and potential events can
therefore not simply be explained as an indication of better recognition memory
performance for intrusive events. Indeed, the similarity in brain regions identified by
both contrasts supports the notion that neural signature is associated with the later
involuntary recall of that event <italic>per se</italic>.</p>
                <p>Multiple regions were associated with the encoding of Intrusive scenes, and included, but
were not limited to, regions associated with threat detection, in particular surprise to
threat (e.g. rostral anterior cingulate cortex) (Bishop <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Browning &amp; Harmer, <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), emotional processing, pain and empathy of pain
(e.g. insula, anterior cingulate, thalamus) (Leknes &amp; Tracey, <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and visual processing and mental imagery (e.g.
ventral occipital cortex) (Kosslyn <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). These are regions consistent with
intrusive memories being emotional, vivid images of traumatic events and regions that are
partially in line with models of PTSD (Rauch <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Admon <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p>
                <p>What might be the theory underlying our neural activation results in the creation of an
intrusive memory in comparison with a traumatic moment that does not later return
involuntarily? While our experimental design restricts conclusions, we speculate on the
following as a starting point for future theoretical development. Neurocircuitry models of
PTSD draw on animal fear-conditioning models and implicate emotional regions such as the
limbic system (e.g. Rauch <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Wegerer <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) have argued that fear conditioning also
underlies intrusive memories, albeit in behavioural studies. While our results do
highlight emotion regions, in line with fear-conditioning models, a number of additional
regions were also identified in our study (e.g. MTG and IFG). This indicates that
additional processing beyond that of fear conditioning may be involved (see Beckers
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p>
                <p>Several other literatures also provide theoretical insights. Models of intrusive memories
in PTSD treatment stemming from clinical and cognitive psychology implicate emotional
regions, and additionally point to heightened activity in sensory/imagery-related regions
(suggested to be mediated by the precuneus) alongside decreased activity in memory regions
(Brewin <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Brewin, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). This is proposed to lead to ineffective coupling of emotional and
contextual information and thus the later occurrence of intrusive memories. Our results
are partially consistent with this model (e.g. occipital areas), supporting the emphasis
on mental imagery. Notably, imagery is not mentioned in the above neurocircuitry models of
PTSD (Rauch <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). However, we argue that the emphasis on
imagery should not be restricted to PTSD memory recall, but rather is part of a continuum
with non-clinical autobiographical recall. Episodic memory involves imagery (Tulving,
<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Vivid image-based autobiographical
memories have been associated with activity in occipital regions and the precuneus (Cabeza
&amp; St. Jacques, <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), and the underlying
neural processes associated with mental imagery substantially overlap with those for
autobiographical memory (Hassabis &amp; Maguire, <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Schacter &amp; Addis, <xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).
This link between autobiographical memory and intrusive memories is also underscored by
autobiographical memory theorists who span clinical and non-clinical literatures (Conway,
<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Berntsen &amp; Hall, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Rubin <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).</p>
                <p>Where our results notably differ from previous models of intrusive memories and PTSD is
the activity pattern found in the left IFG and MTG. The left IFG and MTG showed increased
activity between Intrusive and Potential scenes, but not Intrusive and Control scenes. We
suggest that these brain regions may be involved in distinguishing why particular
traumatic scenes become an intrusive memory while other traumatic scenes in the same
sequence do not. As noted in the introduction, both regions have previously been
associated with subsequent memory for deliberate recall (Paller &amp; Wagner, <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Kensinger &amp; Corkin, <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). We suggest that enhanced encoding occurs at
these ‘hotspot’ moments which later become intrusive memories, with heightened involvement
of these memory-related areas in combination with increases in sensory and emotional
processing. In contrast, PTSD models proposed elsewhere suggest ‘disrupted’ encoding and
memory fragmentation (e.g. Brewin, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec4-2">
                <title>Intrusive memory involuntary recall during fMRI</title>
                <p>Our final aim of the study was to model brain activity when participants experienced an
intrusive memory in the scanner while undergoing fMRI. Using finite impulse response basis
functions to model the BOLD signal change we identified neural activity at the moment of
intrusive memory involuntary recall. Initial activity was observed in the middle and
superior frontal cortices, followed by activation in the operculum and left IFG. These
findings of middle and superior frontal cortex activity are convergent with previous
results of involuntary recall for picture stimuli (Hall <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), extending this previous finding to the
involuntary recall of more naturalistic complex film stimuli. In PTSD patients, decreases
in activity following treatment in the middle frontal cortex during trauma imagery have
also been identified (Lindauer <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Additionally, the frontal operculum has
been associated with the attentional control of cognitive processes and task selection
(Higo <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and the left IFG with the selection of
competing memory representations (Nelson <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Levens &amp; Phelps, <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec4-3">
                <title>The left IFG and intrusive memories</title>
                <p>The left IFG was the only region identified here involved in both intrusive memory
encoding and involuntary recall. Interestingly, studies of PTSD patients have indicated
neural networks involving the left IFG (James <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and the left IFG has shown increases in
activity when PTSD patients process traumatic compared with neutral material (Landré
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Current neurocircuitry models do not
implicate the left IFG in PTSD (Rauch <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Admon <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), though we note that this study involves
encoding, which by definition has not been examined in PTSD patients.</p>
                <p>What might be the role of the left IFG in intrusive memory encoding and recall, at least
for experimental trauma? As previously mentioned, the left IFG has been associated with
predicting later subsequent memory recall (Kensinger &amp; Corkin, <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). It has also been associated with the selection
of information (Moss <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), competing memory representations (Nelson
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Levens &amp; Phelps, <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) and evaluations of emotional information (Lee
&amp; Siegle, <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). A meta-analysis of
cognitive control suggests that the left IFG may be involved in the ‘flexibility’ to
switch from one task to another (Niendam <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Further, greater putamen–left IFG
functional connectivity activity has been associated with unwanted thoughts in healthy
participants (Kühn <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). We do note, however, that these
associations, while interesting, are made with reverse inference and thus should be done
so with caution (Poldrack, <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>).</p>
                <p>From our current results, we tentatively hypothesize that left IFG activation while
viewing traumatic material (during encoding) may ‘flag’ the event that will subsequently
return as an intrusive memory, comprising an analogue trauma ‘hotspot’ (Grey &amp;
Holmes, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). During intrusive memory
involuntary recall, left IFG activation may represent the orientation of attention towards
the ‘flagged’ memory, contributing to the overriding of other psychological functioning
and capture of attention.</p>
                <p>Overall, our view is that trauma intrusions are not simply bits of ‘fragmented or
incoherent’ memory, rather that intrusions comprise highly selective hotspots meaningful
to that individual (Ehlers <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Grey &amp; Holmes, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Krans <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Further we see intrusive memory in PTSD on
a continuum with other emotional intrusive memories, and on a continuum between clinical
and non-clinical populations (see also Kvavilashvili, <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec4-4">
                <title>Limitations</title>
                <p>The number of events modelled in the current experiment is low compared with more
traditional fMRI designs, though similar to the number of different intrusive memories
seen in PTSD patients – a mean of 3.74 (Grey &amp; Holmes, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). This may be inevitable in paradigms attempting to capture
‘rare’ clinically relevant symptoms. Conventional ideas may suggest that three events
provide insufficient power for a reliable contrast. On the other hand, the statistics used
do account for the low number of events, and a small number of events is more likely to
cause a type II error (false negative) than a type I error (false positive), because low
event frequency increases noise, making it difficult to find meaningful results (see also
empirical demonstration in Bourne <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; online Supplementary material).</p>
                <p>Due to the nature of the traumatic content, scene length varied between 5 and 37 s. This
is greater variance than is typically seen in fMRI study designs. Given the slowness of
the haemodynamic response (between 5 and 7 s), this adds further noise to the data.
Further, the total time modelled as specific scenes of interest is relatively low (indeed,
the total scan time of the whole film is under 25 min). Conventional wisdom suggests
scanning for as long as possible and collecting the most data over events of interest as
possible, resulting in longer scan times and greater amounts of data (see, for example,
Henson, <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p>
                <p>However, if our results were detrimentally unreliable due to low event frequency,
variance in scene length, limited scanning time or other factors typically enhanced to
optimize the fMRI design, we would expect to have been unable to replicate our previous
findings. The results presented here on the other hand show a near-identical pattern of
activation as our previous results. Further, using multivariate pattern analysis
techniques reported elsewhere we have been able to predict intrusive memories solely from
the brain activity during encoding of film footage with traumatic content (Clark
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Overall, this suggests that these fMRI
results underlying intrusive memory encoding, while not ideal in all respects, are
reliable in terms of replicability.</p>
                <p>The prospective design and use of a scanner at encoding rely upon an analogue of trauma,
and this is not the same as experiencing real trauma. However, repeated exposure to media
film images of traumatic events have been associated with higher scores on the PTSD
Checklist – Civilian Version (a measure of PTSD symptoms) (Silver <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and higher acute stress symptoms (Holman
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The inclusion of trauma exposure through
electronic media, television and movies in the line of work in the new DSM-5 (American
Psychiatric Association, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) also prompts the
need for greater understanding of these forms of exposure.</p>
                <p>Our intrusive memory involuntary recall task in the scanner has only been tested here at
a time soon after the analogue trauma. Recent evidence suggests that immediate (1 h) and
delayed (1 week) intrusive memories may result from different types of retrieval
mechanisms (Staugaard &amp; Berntsen, <xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).
Immediate intrusive memories may relate more to salient aspects of the memorability at
encoding (e.g. vividness, emotionality, recency), whereas delayed intrusive memories may
reflect the influence of retrieval cues in the environment that elicit such involuntary
recall. Our current results are on immediate intrusive memories. Future research should
test a larger time interval by returning participants to the scanner at 1 week.</p>
                <p>This study aimed to provide the first capture of the neural processes involved at the
moment of intrusive memory involuntary recall. However, our intrusive memory involuntary
recall analysis presents only the first steps in what will need to be a longer line of
enquiry. Our control condition (button press alone) was used to subtract brain activity
associated with the button press itself in the absence of an intrusion (for related
methodology to capture neural activity associated with the occurrence of a hallucination
in schizophrenia via balloon press, see Diederen <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Hoffman <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Future investigations should develop
improved and appropriately powered control conditions to develop methods to capture
intrusiveness, as this is key to many psychiatric phenomena. Additionally, further studies
which specifically contrast voluntarily and involuntary recall, in particular following
movie stimuli, are clearly required.</p>
                <p>Finally, it is not possible to ascertain whether the intrusions are ‘truly’ spontaneous,
or merely reported as spontaneous. Interestingly, this issue applies equally to the
clinical form of this experimental analogue, since patients with PTSD are asked to report
or monitor their spontaneously occurring intrusive memories during assessment/treatment.
Future studies might seek to examine this issue further.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec5">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>Our analyses suggest that whilst experiencing trauma the brain behaves differently during
moments that later become intrusive memories, consistent with clinical suggestions that the
peritraumatic phase is important in predicting PTSD (Ozer <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; American Psychiatric Association, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Whereas a strikingly widespread pattern of
activation was involved at encoding, the left IFG was the only region involved in both the
encoding and involuntary recall of intrusive memories. What are the clinical implications?
Tentatively we suggest that if left IFG activation can be modulated during the encoding of
trauma memory and its consolidation (Walker <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>), then we may be able to modulate intrusive
memory occurrence by reducing left IFG activation. Further, due to the association between
the left IFG and language processing (Vigneau <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), results may provide a clue as to why certain
talking-based interventions (e.g. critical incident stress debriefing) soon after trauma
have been found to be detrimental (Roberts <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Talking-based interventions increasing left
IFG activity may serve to increase intrusive memory (re)encoding at this early time point.
We note that at later time points (e.g. 1 month and later) trauma-focused
cognitive–behavioural therapy is effective (e.g. Bisson <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p>
              <p>In summary, after witnessing a traumatic event, it is only certain moments from the trauma
that reappear as intrusive memories. Why it is that some moments rather than others become
intrusive memories has long been a puzzle. We suggest that alterations in brain activation
at the time of viewing trauma determine which moments will later become intrusive memories.
In particular, activity in the left IFG seems to be key for both the encoding and the
involuntary recall of intrusive memories. Further, we speculate that rather than disrupted
encoding resulting in memory fragments and intrusive memories, a theoretical alternative is
that intrusive memories result from better encoded memories at specific points in time.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack id="ack">
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>This work was supported by the UK Medical Research Council (MRC) (I.A.C., MRC Centenary
Early Career Award; E.A.H., MRC Intramural Programme MC-A060-5PR50), the Wellcome Trust
(E.A.H., Wellcome Trust Clinical Fellowship WT088217; M.W.W.), the MRC/Engineering and
Physical Sciences Research Council UK MEG Partnership (M.W.W.) and the National Institute
for Health Research (NIHR) Oxford Biomedical Research Programme (E.A.H., M.W.W., C.E.M.).
The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the National
Health Service, the NIHR or the Department of Health. Funding to pay the Open Access
publication charges for this article was provided by the UK Medical Research Council.</p>
            </ack>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec6">
              <title>Supplementary material</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S0033291715002007sup001">
                <p>For supplementary material accompanying this paper visit http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0033291715002007.</p>
                <media xlink:href="S0033291715002007sup001.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" orientation="portrait" id="d36e1977" position="anchor">
                  <caption>
                    <p>click here to view supplementary material</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
            <notes notes-type="other" id="nts2">
              <title>Declaration of Interest</title>
              <p>None.</p>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="reflist1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="ref1">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Admon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hendler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A causal model of post-traumatic stress
disorder: disentangling predisposed from acquired neural abnormalities</article-title>.
<source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23768722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref2">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>
(<year>2013</year>). <source>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental
Disorders</source>, <edition>5th edn</edition>
<publisher-name>American Psychiatric
Association</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Washington,
DC</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref3">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beckers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krypotos</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boddez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Effting</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kindt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>What's wrong with fear conditioning?</article-title>
<source>Biological Psychology</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22223096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref4">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>General multi-level linear modelling for group
analysis in fMRI</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1052</fpage>–<lpage>1063</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14568475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref5">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berntsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The episodic nature of involuntary
autobiographical memories</article-title>. <source>Memory and Cognition</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>789</fpage>–<lpage>803</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15552356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref6">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Prefrontal cortical function and anxiety:
controlling attention to threat-related stimuli</article-title>. <source>Nature
Neuroscience</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14703573</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref7">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bisson</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Psychological therapies for chronic
post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in adults</article-title>. <source>Cochrane
Database of Systematic Reviews</source>, Issue 12. Art. No.: CD003388. DOI:
10.1002/14651858.CD003388.pub4.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref8">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The neural basis of flashback formation: the
impact of viewing trauma</article-title>. <source>Psychological Medicine</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1521</fpage>–<lpage>1533</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23171530</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref9">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Breslau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chilcoat</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andreski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Trauma and posttraumatic stress disorder in
the community</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>626</fpage>–<lpage>632</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9672053</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref10">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brewin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>“I Wouldn't Start From Here” – an alternative
perspective on PTSD from the ICD-11: comment on Friedman (2013)</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Traumatic Stress</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24151002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref11">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brewin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Episodic memory, perceptual memory, and their
interaction: foundations for a theory of posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>.
<source>Psychological Bulletin</source>
<volume>140</volume>, <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23914721</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref12">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brewin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Intrusive images in psychological disorders:
characteristics, neural mechanisms, and treatment implications</article-title>.
<source>Psychological Review</source>
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20063969</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref13">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Expectancy and surprise predict neural and
behavioral measures of attention to threatening stimuli</article-title>.
<source>NeuroImage</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>1942</fpage>–<lpage>1948</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21945791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref14">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The roles of noradrenergic and glucocorticoid
activation in the development of intrusive memories</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <elocation-id/>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref15">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uludağ</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubowitz</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Modeling the hemodynamic response to brain
activation</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source>
<volume>23</volume> (<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>),
<fpage>S220</fpage>–<lpage>S233</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501093</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref16">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cabeza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>St. Jacques</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Functional neuroimaging of autobiographical
memory</article-title>. <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17188554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref17">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niehaus</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Di Simplicio</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>First steps in using machine learning on fMRI
data to predict intrusive memories of traumatic film footage</article-title>.
<source>Behaviour Research and Therapy</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25151915</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref18">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Sensory-perceptual episodic memory and its
context: autobiographical memory</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of
the Royal Society of London Series B – Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>356</volume>, <fpage>1375</fpage>–<lpage>1384</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11571029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref19">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diederen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neggers</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daalman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goekoop</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Deactivation of the parahippocampal gyrus
preceding auditory hallucinations in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>American
Journal of Psychiatry</source>
<volume>167</volume>, <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref20">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>A cognitive model of posttraumatic stress
disorder</article-title>. <source>Behaviour Research and Therapy</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10761279</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref21">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hackmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clohessy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wenninger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The nature of intrusive memories after trauma:
the warning signal hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Behaviour Research and Therapy</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>995</fpage>–<lpage>1002</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12296496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref22">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mintun</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noll</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Improved assessment of significant activation
in functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI): use of a cluster-size
threshold</article-title>. <source>Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>636</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7596267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref23">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>“Hotspots” in trauma memories in the treatment
of post-traumatic stress disorder: a replication</article-title>. <source>Memory</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>788</fpage>–<lpage>796</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18720224</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref24">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gjedde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kupers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Neural mechanisms of voluntary and involuntary
recall: a PET study</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source>
<volume>186</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17913256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref25">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hassabis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Deconstructing episodic memory with
construction</article-title>. <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17548229</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref26">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Efficient experimental design for
fMRI</article-title>. In <source>Statistical Parametric Mapping. The Analysis of
Functional Brain Images</source> (ed. <string-name><given-names>K. J.</given-names><surname>Friston</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Ashburner</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Kiebel</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T. E.</given-names><surname>Nichols</surname></string-name> and <string-name><given-names>W. D.</given-names><surname>Penny</surname></string-name>), pp. <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>210.</lpage>
<publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>:
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref27">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Higo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boorman</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buch</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rushworth</surname><given-names>MFS</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Distributed and causal influence of frontal
operculum in task control</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy
of Sciences USA</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>4230</fpage>–<lpage>4235</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref28">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pittman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Constable</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhagwagar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Time course of regional brain activity
accompanying auditory verbal hallucinations in schizophrenia</article-title>.
<source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source>
<volume>198</volume>, <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21972276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref29">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garfin</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Media's role in broadcasting acute stress
following the Boston marathon bombings</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the
National Academy of Sciences USA</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref30">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Inducing and modulating intrusive emotional
memories: a review of the trauma film paradigm</article-title>. <source>Acta
Psychologica</source>
<volume>127</volume>, <fpage>553</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18234153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref31">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brewin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hennessy</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Trauma films, information processing, and
intrusive memory development</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental
Psychology: General</source>
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14979748</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref32">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Functional neuroimaging studies of
post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Expert Review of
Neurotherapeutics</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21306214</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref33">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engdahl</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leuthold</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Kampen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Georgopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Neural network modulation by trauma as a
marker of resilience: differences between veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder
and resilient controls</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>410</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23426853</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref34">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kensinger</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Two routes to emotional memory: distinct
neural processes for valence and arousal</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the
National Academy of Sciences USA</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>3310</fpage>–<lpage>3315</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref35">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kosslyn</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ganis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Neural foundations of imagery</article-title>.
<source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>642</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11533731</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref36">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naring</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Intrusive trauma memory: a review and
functional analysis</article-title>. <source>Applied Cognitive Psychology</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1076</fpage>–<lpage>1088</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref37">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kühn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vanderhasselt</surname><given-names>M-A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Raedt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gallinat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The neural basis of unwanted thoughts during
resting state</article-title>. <source>Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1320</fpage>–<lpage>1324</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23929943</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref38">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kvavilashvili</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Solving the mystery of intrusive flashbacks in
posttraumatic stress disorder: comment on Brewin</article-title>. <source>Psychological
Bulletin</source>
<volume>140</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24364748</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref39">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Landré</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Destrieux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barantin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quidé</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tapia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jaafari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clarys</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isingrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>El-Hage</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Working memory processing of traumatic
material in women with posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Psychiatry and Neuroscience</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21971161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref40">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lanius</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bluhm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lanius</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A review of neuroimaging studies in PTSD:
heterogeneity of response to symptom provocation</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Psychiatric Research</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>729</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16214172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref41">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>). <article-title>A laboratory approach to the dynamics of
psychological stress</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>400</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref42">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siegle</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Common and distinct brain networks underlying
explicit emotional evaluation: a meta-analytic study</article-title>. <source>Social
Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>534</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19270039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref43">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leknes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A common neurobiology for pain and
pleasure</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18354400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref44">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levens</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Insula and orbital frontal cortex activity
underlying emotion interference resolution in working memory</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2790</fpage>–<lpage>2803</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044897</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref45">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liberzon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fig</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koeppe</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Alterations of corticothalamic perfusion
ratios during a PTSD flashback</article-title>. <source>Depression and Anxiety</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9166645</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref46">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lindauer</surname><given-names>RJL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Booij</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Habraken</surname><given-names>JBA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Meijel</surname><given-names>EPM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uylings</surname><given-names>HBM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlier</surname><given-names>IVE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>den Heeten</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Eck-Smit</surname><given-names>BLF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gersons</surname><given-names>BPR</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Effects of psychotherapy on regional cerebral
blood flow during trauma imagery in patients with post-traumatic stress disorder: a
randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Psychological Medicine</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17803835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref47">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pilgrim</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Acres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Selecting among competing alternatives:
selection and retrieval in the left inferior frontal gyrus</article-title>.
<source>Cerebral Cortex</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1723</fpage>–<lpage>1735</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref48">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reuter-Lorenz</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sylvester</surname><given-names>C-YC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jonides</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Mapping interference resolution across task
domains: a shared control process in left inferior frontal gyrus</article-title>.
<source>Brain Research</source>
<volume>1256</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19111526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref49">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Niendam</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glahn</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Meta-analytic evidence for a superordinate
cognitive control network subserving diverse executive functions</article-title>.
<source>Cognitive, Affective and Behavioral Neuroscience</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref50">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Osuch</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geraci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Podell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herscovitch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Post</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Regional cerebral blood flow correlated with
flashback intensity in patients with posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>.
<source>Biological Psychiatry</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11522258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref51">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ozer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lipsey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Predictors of posttraumatic stress disorder
and symptoms in adults: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12555794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref52">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paller</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Observing the transformation of experience
into memory</article-title>. <source>Trends in Cognitive Science</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref53">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pietrzak</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krystal</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neumeister</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Linking <italic>in vivo</italic> brain
serotonin type 1B receptor density to phenotypic heterogeneity of posttraumatic stress
symptomatology</article-title>. <source>Molecular Psychiatry</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22584868</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref54">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poldrack</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Can cognitive processes be inferred from
neuroimaging data?</article-title>
<source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16406760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref55">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Neurocircuitry models of posttraumatic stress
disorder and extinction: human neuroimaging research – past, present, and
future</article-title>. <source>Biological Psychiatry</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16919525</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref56">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whalen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Neuroimaging and the neuroanatomy of
PTSD</article-title>. <source>CNS Spectrums</source>
<volume>3</volume> (<issue>Suppl. 2</issue>),
<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref57">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Kolk</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fisler</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenike</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A symptom provocation study of posttraumatic
stress disorder using positron emission tomography and script-driven
imagery</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8624181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref58">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kitchiner</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kenardy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bisson</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Multiple session early psychological
interventions for the prevention of post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>.
<source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source>, Issue 3. Art. No.: CD006869.
DOI: 10.1002/14651858.CD006869.pub2.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref59">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boals</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bernsten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Memory in posttraumatic stress disorder:
properties of voluntary and involuntary, traumatic and non-traumatic autobiographical
memories in people with and without PTSD symptoms</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Experimental Psychology: General</source>
<volume>137</volume>, <fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>614</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18999355</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref60">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schacter</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Addis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The cognitive neuroscience of constructive
memory: remembering the past and imagining the future</article-title>.
<source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>362</volume>, <fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>786</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref61">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kosslyn</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Macklin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Visual imagery and perception in posttraumatic
stress disorder. A positron emission tomographic investigation</article-title>.
<source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9075464</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref62">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kosslyn</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lasko</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Regional cerebral blood flow during
script-driven imagery in childhood sexual abuse-related PTSD: a PET
investigation</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Psychiatry</source>
<volume>156</volume>, <fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10200737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref63">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Macklin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lasko</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cannistraro</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Regional cerebral blood flow in the amygdala
and medial prefrontal cortex during traumatic imagery in male and female Vietnam
veterans with PTSD</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14757593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref64">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Amygdala, medial prefrontal cortex, and
hippocampal function in PTSD</article-title>. <source>Annals of the New York Academy of
Sciences</source>
<volume>1071</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16891563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref65">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gil-Rivas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Mental- and physical-health effects of acute
exposure to media images of the September 11, 2001, attacks and the Iraq
war</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1623</fpage>–<lpage>1634</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23907546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref66">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Staugaard</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berntsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Involuntary memories of emotional scenes: the
effects of cue discriminability and emotion over time</article-title>. <source>Journal
of Experimental Psychology: General</source>
<volume>143</volume>, <fpage>1939</fpage>–<lpage>1957</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24933516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref67">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tulving</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Episodic memory: from mind to
brain</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Psychology</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref68">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vigneau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beaucousin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hervé</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duffau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crivello</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Houdé</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mazoyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tzourio-Mazoyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Meta-analyzing left hemisphere language areas:
phonology, semantics, and sentence processing</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1414</fpage>–<lpage>1432</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16413796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref69">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brakefield</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hobson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stickgold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Dissociable stages of human memory
consolidation and reconsolidation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>425</volume>, <fpage>616</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14534587</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref70">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wegerer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blechert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kerschbaum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Relationship between fear conditionability and
aversive memories: evidence from a novel conditioned-intrusion paradigm</article-title>.
<source>PLOS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <elocation-id/>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref71">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Robust group analysis using outlier
inference</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18407525</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="ref72">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Multi-level linear modelling for fMRI group
analysis using Bayesian inference</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1732</fpage>–<lpage>1747</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15050594</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
