<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-07T13:04:47Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6373308" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6373308</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-03-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>springeropen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Child Psychiatry Hum Dev</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Child Psychiatry Hum Dev</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Child Psychiatry and Human Development</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0009-398X</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1573-3327</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6373308</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6373308</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6373308</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29959588</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29959588</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">826</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10578-018-0826-4</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>SDQ in the Hands of Fathers and Preschool Teachers—Psychometric Properties in a Non-clinical Sample of 3–5-Year-Olds</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0136-8862</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dahlberg</surname>
                    <given-names>Anton</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <phone>+46 18 4716576</phone>
                    <email>anton.dahlberg@pubcare.uu.se</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8483-7964</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ghaderi</surname>
                    <given-names>Ata</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6594-2291</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sarkadi</surname>
                    <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6363-4030</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Salari</surname>
                    <given-names>Raziye</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9457</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8993.b</institution-id><institution>Child Health and Parenting (CHAP), Department of Public Health and Caring Sciences, </institution><institution>Uppsala University, </institution></institution-wrap>Box 564, Uppsala, 751 22 Sweden </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0626</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4714.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Division of Psychology, </institution><institution>Karolinska Institutet, </institution></institution-wrap>Stockholm, Sweden </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2018</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2018</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>50</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>132</fpage>
              <lpage>141</lpage>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="OpenAccess">
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <p id="Par1">The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) is a well-established instrument for measuring social and behavioural problems among children, with good psychometric properties for older children, but less validity reports on pre-schoolers. In addition, there is a knowledge gap concerning fathers as informants. The present work is one of the few validity studies to include preschool teachers and the first on preschool children where fathers are included as separate informants. In this study, SDQs were collected from a large community sample (<italic>n</italic> = 17,752) of children aged 3–5, rated by mothers, fathers, and preschool teachers and analysed using confirmatory factor analysis. Our results revealed acceptable fit for all informant groups and measurement invariance across child gender, child age, and parental education level. Our findings suggest good construct validity of the SDQ for a non-clinical preschool population and imply that it may be used for assessing child behaviour problems from different informant perspectives.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ)</kwd>
                <kwd>Fathers</kwd>
                <kwd>Confirmatory factor analysis (CFA)</kwd>
                <kwd>Preschool children</kwd>
                <kwd>Construct validity</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001862</institution-id>
                      <institution>Svenska Forskningsrådet Formas</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>259-2012-68</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarkadi</surname>
                      <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001725</institution-id>
                      <institution>Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>259-2012-68</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarkadi</surname>
                      <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001858</institution-id>
                      <institution>VINNOVA</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>259-2012-68</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarkadi</surname>
                      <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2019</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="Par2">In research involving children, there is general agreement on the importance of early discovery of and early interventions towards mental health problems. For this to be possible, we need instruments with proper psychometric qualities. One of the most commonly used instruments for assessing behaviour and mental health problems among younger children is the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ), which is being used both clinically and in research on children aged 2–17 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sdqinfo.com">http://www.sdqinfo.com</ext-link>). Consisting of 25 items, the SDQ is a relatively short questionnaire while still being comparable to the similar but lengthier Child Behavior Checklist (CBCL), displaying moderate to high correlations on total and equivalent subgroup scores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The SDQ, in general, displays good construct and concurrent validity, as well as some evidence on predictive validity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Construct validity has mainly been assessed using confirmatory factor analysis (CFA). Although displaying promising psychometric properties, few studies have investigated the SDQs validity and reliability for use among preschool-aged children specifically (see Croft et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] for one example); on the contrary, it has mostly been used with teenagers or a broad range of ages spanning through preschool and the early school years. A study by Croft et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] concluded satisfactory construct validity for preschool children when rated by parents.</p>
              <p id="Par3">Factor analytic studies of the SDQ have supported the original five-factor structure in many [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] but not all cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In a large sample study, Goodman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] concluded that the five-factor model should be used in clinical samples, while a model with two broader externalising and internalising subscales should be used in epidemiological studies or low-risk samples. Stone et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] found support for the original factor solution, when analysing data from several previous studies. To the best of our knowledge, the major part of the CFA studies published concern school children. Thus, we identified a need for more studies on the construct validity of the SDQ for preschool children. Ezpeleta et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] have provided some evidence suggesting that the original five-factor model is feasible for preschool children, although not entirely convincing mainly due to low values on indices of comparative fit. Investigating factor structure of the SDQ for pre-schoolers in a Nordic context, support for a two-factor model consisting of hyperactivity and conduct problems was found for children aged 1–3, while a model including the original subscales, except for the prosocial subscale, was proposed for 4–5-year-olds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par4">The multi-informant approach of the SDQ provides opportunity to assess the validity of the questionnaire when filled in by different informant groups. Data from teachers’ ratings generally show better model fit than parents, especially on subscale level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Although there is evidence for good validity of teachers’ SDQ ratings of children in primary school [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], no CFA studies have included preschool teachers.</p>
              <p id="Par5">Some studies of the SDQ have indicated that fathers tend to report more externalising behaviour problems than mothers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Interestingly, fathers are rarely treated as a unique informant group in validity studies of the SDQ. In the published CFA studies that we found, separate analyses of mothers and fathers are conspicuous by their absence, with very few exceptions (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]). Looking at how parent data are constituted, mothers are greatly overrepresented, with fathers mostly present as either co-respondents or marginally represented together with the mothers (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]). It is also common to report parents as one group, not specifying the proportions of mothers and fathers (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]). Although it can be argued that the factor structure of the SDQ rated by fathers and mothers should be similar—a statement somewhat supported by Björnsdotter et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]—this is something that needs to be empirically investigated further in order to answer questions regarding the validity of SDQ across different informants and age groups.</p>
              <p id="Par6">For preschool children, measurement invariance has been established between mothers and fathers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Still, to the best of our knowledge, the only studies assessing invariance across different age groups, child gender, or parental (maternal) education level within each informant group are on school-aged children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par7">The aim of the present study is to test the original five-factor structure of the SDQ for preschool children and to assess whether the suggested model has an acceptable fit for fathers as well as mothers and preschool teachers. This study also seeks to assess measurement invariance across child gender, child age, and parental education for all three informant groups.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Data Collection</title>
                <p id="Par8">For this study, data were extracted from the <italic>Children and Parents in Focus</italic> project [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]: an ongoing population-based intervention trial in Uppsala, Sweden, aiming at investigating the mental health of preschool children and their parents, and evaluating the effects of a parenting programme. Parents and preschool teachers filled in a set of questionnaires in connection with the children’s annual check-up at Child Health Centres, including the SDQ. Since more than 90% of all children aged 3–5 in Sweden attend preschool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] and 95% visit the child health centres regularly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], a major part of the population was targeted.</p>
                <p id="Par9">For detailed background, measures, study design, and field procedures, see Salari et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The extracted data were collected between August 2013 and August 2016. Since data were collected during a 3-year period for all children aged 3–5 in the same geographical area, some children were represented in the data set at two or three different ages. The study was approved by the Regional Ethical Review Board in Uppsala (Dnr 2012/437). Informed consent was obtained from all participants included in the study.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Sample</title>
                <p id="Par10">A total of 23,554 questionnaires were collected from parents and teachers of pre-schoolers aged 3–5. For the study at hand, we excluded data where informants were not the mother, father or preschool teacher of the focal child; when the questionnaires were completed in languages other than Swedish; and when more than one child was rated on the same questionnaire. For children who were represented at two or three time points during the study, one questionnaire was selected at random. Finally, to assess subscale scores on the SDQ, at least three items per subscale need to be filled in (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sdqinfo.com">http://www.sdqinfo.com</ext-link>). Therefore, questionnaires with insufficient amount of data based on these restrictions were also excluded from statistical analyses. After data exclusion, questionnaires from 6636 mothers, 5749 fathers, and 5367 preschool teachers, representing 7113 children, remained for statistical analyses. The order of exclusion and number of excluded cases are displayed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. All three informant groups had an equal proportion of children from each age group present: the percentages of 3-, 4-, and 5-year-olds were 34, 32, and 32%, respectively. Girls and boys were equally represented across all three informant groups. Information on child gender was missing from three questionnaires from fathers, eight questionnaires from mothers, and from one questionnaire from preschool teachers. The proportions of the 7113 children rated by different combinations of informants are displayed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p>
                <p id="Par11">
                  <fig id="Fig1">
                    <label>Fig. 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Flowchart of exclusion</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="10578_2018_826_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e398"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
                <p id="Par12">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab1">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Proportions of children rated by different combinations of informants</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left">One parent</th>
                          <th align="left">Preschool teacher</th>
                          <th align="left">Both parents</th>
                          <th align="left">One parent and teacher</th>
                          <th align="left">All three informants</th>
                          <th align="left">Total</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">
                            <italic>n</italic>
                          </td>
                          <td align="left">741</td>
                          <td align="left">80</td>
                          <td align="left">1005</td>
                          <td align="left">940</td>
                          <td align="left">4347</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">7113</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">%</td>
                          <td align="left">10.4</td>
                          <td align="left">1.1</td>
                          <td align="left">14.1</td>
                          <td align="left">13.2</td>
                          <td align="left">61.1</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">100</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p id="Par13">The age of the parents ranged between 19 and 58 for mothers (<italic>M</italic> = 35.8, SD = 4.9) and between 19 and 68 for fathers (<italic>M</italic> = 38.3, SD = 5.9). To assess education level, parents were divided into two categories: less than 3 years of college or university education, and more than 3 years of college or university education. The number of parents with college or university education of at least 3 years was compared with municipality data retrieved from Statistics Sweden (scb.se). Comparisons revealed a skewness of the data towards higher education level: 52% of the fathers and 63% of the mothers in our sample compared with 49% within the municipality. Non-native parents comprised 14% of the fathers and 14% of the mothers, which was representative of the municipality population.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Instruments</title>
                <p id="Par14">The SDQ consists of 25 items, each rated as being <italic>not true</italic> (0), <italic>somewhat true</italic> (1), or <italic>certainly true</italic> (2). Items are divided into five subscales covering conduct problems, hyperactivity, emotional symptoms, peer problems, and prosocial behaviour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Summing up the scores on the first four subscales generates the SDQ total difficulties score, ranging from 0 to 40.</p>
                <p id="Par15">The Swedish version of the SDQ was used to collect data from children 3–5 years old. Some items were slightly changed in wording after discussions with health, research, and pedagogy professionals involved in the Children and Parents in Focus study (see Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> for the SDQ items and modifications). The reason for this was that the preschool professionals considered the original wording of some SDQ items to be disharmonious with their philosophical and pedagogical beliefs and thus refused to respond if they were not altered. Thus, we agreed on a clearer focus on behaviours rather than specific traits of individual children. The altered wording of the three items in question were considered to be in line with both pedagogical praxis in Sweden, and with the original intention of creating a questionnaire focusing on displayed behaviour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Demographic information about the child (e.g. birthdate and gender) and the parent (gender, education level) were collected together with the SDQ.</p>
                <p id="Par16">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab2">
                    <label>Table 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>The original five-factor structure of the SDQ</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">Subscale</th>
                          <th align="left">Items</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="5">Conduct problems</td>
                          <td align="left">Often has temper tantrums or hot tempers</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Generally obedient, usually does what adults request<sup>a</sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Often fights with other children or bullies them</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Often argumentative with adults</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Can be spiteful to others<sup>b</sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="5">Hyperactivity</td>
                          <td align="left">Restless, overactive, cannot stay still for long</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Constantly fidgeting or squirming</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Easily distracted, concentration wanders</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Can stop and think things out before acting</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Sees tasks through to the end, good attention span</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="5">Emotional symptoms</td>
                          <td align="left">Often complains of headaches, stomach-aches or sickness</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Many worries, often seems worried</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Often unhappy, down-hearted or tearful</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Nervous or clingy in new situations, easily loses confidence</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Many fears, easily scared</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="5">Peer problems</td>
                          <td align="left">Rather solitary, tends to play alone</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Has at least one good friend</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Generally liked by other children</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Picked on or bullied by other children</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Gets on better with adults than with other children</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" rowspan="5">Prosocial behaviour</td>
                          <td align="left">Considerate of other people’s feelings</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Shares readily with other children (treats, toys, pencils, etc.)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Helpful if someone is hurt, upset or feeling ill</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Kind to younger children<sup>c</sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Often volunteers to help others (parents, teachers, other children)</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p>Modified items are presented in the footnotes</p>
                      <p><sup>a</sup>Usually does what adults request</p>
                      <p><sup>b</sup>Can behave spitefully towards others</p>
                      <p><sup>c</sup>Considerate of younger children</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Procedure</title>
                <p id="Par17">All parents of children aged 3–5 were invited to fill in the questionnaires as part of their annual check-up at child health centres. Along with the invitation letter to the annual check-up, three sets of questionnaires were sent home to each child. Parents/guardians were asked to fill in one questionnaire each and bring the completed forms to the visit. In addition, parents were instructed to take the third questionnaire to the child’s preschool and ask the preschool teacher to complete the form, put it in the prepaid envelope provided and send it directly to the child health centre. The preschool teachers in Sweden have a three-and-a-half-year academic education and have professional knowledge in child development and pedagogical interventions aimed at children aged 1–6.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p id="Par18">All statistical analyses were conducted using R, version 3.4.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The items of the SDQ were rated on a 3-point Likert scale and thus treated as ordinal data. Therefore, internal consistency was assessed based on polychoric ordinal alpha calculations as proposed by Gadermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], using the psych package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The fit of the original theoretical five factor model of the SDQ was assessed through CFA, using the lavaan package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Due to the ordinal nature of the data, analyses were based on polychoric correlation matrices, using Diagonally Weighted Least Squares (DWLS) for estimation of model parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Chi square (with alpha set to <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05), Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA), Comparative Fit Index (CFI), and Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI) were used to test model fit. The criteria for acceptable model fit were set to RMSEA less than 0.06, in combination with CFI or TLI above 0.90 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Although the Chi square statistics were calculated, they are of little importance as a measure of model fit in our analyses, since the large sample sizes make it very likely to find significant differences between models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Because the majority of the children were rated by more than one informant, three separate analyses were conducted for fathers, mothers, and preschool teachers.</p>
                <p id="Par19">The questionnaire used was designed for children aged 2–4, and the children in our study were aged 3–5. In order to determine whether the questionnaire was still psychometrically valid, measurement invariance (MI) analysis was applied to assess potential differences across age groups. This was also applied for child gender and parental education level. These analyses were carried out within the CFA framework, imposing equality constraints to the factor loadings and thresholds in a hierarchal manner. First, a free model with no equality constraints was analysed to assess fitness for each subgroup. Secondly, a model with constrained factor loadings was specified and compared to the free model. If the models were not significantly different in fit, a third model with constrained loadings and intercepts was specified and compared to the second model. Comparing the restricted and unrestricted models, changes in <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> are often used as a measure. However, given the large sample sizes, even very small changes are likely to be significant, making this measure unsuitable for our analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Instead, change in CFI was used as a subgroup invariance measure, as proposed by Cheung and Rensvold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] and Chen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], and applied by He et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Changes in CFI less than 0.01 were considered not significant.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>Internal Consistency</title>
                <p id="Par20">The calculated alpha values indicated good internal consistency for fathers (conduct problems: 0.78, hyperactivity: 0.84, emotional symptoms: 0.72, peer problems: 0.72, prosocial behaviour: 0.82, and total difficulties: 0.87), mothers (conduct problems: 0.79, hyperactivity: 0.87, emotional symptoms: 0.73, peer problems: 0.77, prosocial behaviour: 0.84, and total difficulties: 0.88), and preschool teachers (conduct problems: 0.88, hyperactivity: 0.92, emotional symptoms: 0.81, peer problems: 0.84, prosocial behaviour: 0.92, and total difficulties: 0.92).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec10">
                <title>Factor Structure</title>
                <p id="Par21">Model fit indices from the CFAs of mothers, fathers, and preschool teachers are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. All fit indices for the five-factor model were satisfactory, suggesting acceptable fit for all groups (CFI and TLI &gt; 0.90 and RMSEA &lt; 0.06). This suggested that the original factor structure was feasible for use on younger children, rated by fathers, mothers or preschool teachers.</p>
                <p id="Par22">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab3">
                    <label>Table 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Model fit for confirmatory factor analyses for different informants</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left">
                            <italic>n</italic>
                          </th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="4">Model Fit Indices</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left"/>
                          <th align="left"><italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> (df)</th>
                          <th align="left">CFI</th>
                          <th align="left">TLI</th>
                          <th align="left">RMSEA (90% CI)</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Fathers</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">5749</td>
                          <td align="left">3510.038 (265)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.914</td>
                          <td align="left">0.902</td>
                          <td align="left">0.049 (0.048–0.050)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Mothers</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">6636</td>
                          <td align="left">3487.356 (265)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.926</td>
                          <td align="left">0.916</td>
                          <td align="left">0.046 (0.045–0.048)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Preschool teachers</td>
                          <td char="." align="char">5367</td>
                          <td align="left">3146.890 (265)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.953</td>
                          <td align="left">0.947</td>
                          <td align="left">0.050 (0.048–0.051)</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p><italic>CFI</italic> Comparative Fit Index, <italic>TLI</italic> Tucker-Lewis Index, <italic>RMSEA</italic> root mean square error of approximation, <italic>CI</italic> confidence interval</p>
                      <p>CFI or TLI &gt; 0.90 and RMSEA &lt; 0.06 indicate acceptable fit</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>Measurement Invariance</title>
                <p id="Par23">Assuming adequate fit for all three informant groups, subgroup CFAs were conducted to assess model fit based on child gender, child age, and parental education level. Results (Tables <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>) indicated acceptable fit for all subgroups. Following these analyses, multiple-group CFAs were conducted across all sub-populations to assess MI. When imposing equality constraints to factor loadings within child gender subgroups, no significant change in model fit was detected for fathers, mothers, or preschool teachers (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). This implied metric invariance, meaning that the items on the SDQ measure the latent factors comparably for girls and boys. Next, when imposing equality constraints to the thresholds, no significant change in model fit was detected for fathers, mothers, or preschool teachers (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), implying scalar invariance, or that the meaning of the subscales and the levels of the underlying items are equal across the child gender subgroups.</p>
                <p id="Par24">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab4">
                    <label>Table 4</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Model fit and nested model comparisons for multiple-group CFAs: child gender and child age</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">Multiple group CFA</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="3">Model Fit Indices</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">Nested model comparisons</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">CFI</th>
                          <th align="left">TLI</th>
                          <th align="left">RMSEA (90% CI)</th>
                          <th align="left">Comparison</th>
                          <th align="left">CFI change</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6">Fathers</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6"> Child gender<sup>†</sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Girls (<italic>n</italic> = 2791)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.905</td>
                          <td align="left">0.893</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.046–0.050)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Boys (<italic>n</italic> = 2955)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.921</td>
                          <td align="left">0.910</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.046–0.050)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 1<sup>a</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.914</td>
                          <td align="left">0.902</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.046–0.049)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 2<sup>b</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.921</td>
                          <td align="left">0.914</td>
                          <td align="left">0.045 (0.044–0.046)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 2 vs 1</td>
                          <td align="left">0.007</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 3<sup>c</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.916</td>
                          <td align="left">0.912</td>
                          <td align="left">0.046 (0.044–0.047)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 3 vs 2</td>
                          <td align="left">0.005</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6"> Child age</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  3-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 1955)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.910</td>
                          <td align="left">0.899</td>
                          <td align="left">0.047 (0.045–0.050)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  4-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 1828)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.909</td>
                          <td align="left">0.897</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.045–0.051)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  5-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 1966)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.926</td>
                          <td align="left">0.917</td>
                          <td align="left">0.045 (0.042–0.048)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 1<sup>a</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.916</td>
                          <td align="left">0.905</td>
                          <td align="left">0.047 (0.045–0.048)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 2<sup>b</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.925</td>
                          <td align="left">0.919</td>
                          <td align="left">0.043 (0.042–0.045)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 2 vs 1</td>
                          <td align="left">0.009</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 3<sup>c</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.918</td>
                          <td align="left">0.916</td>
                          <td align="left">0.044 (0.043–0.045)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 3 vs 2</td>
                          <td align="left">0.007</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6">Mothers</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6"> Child gender<sup>‡</sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Girls (<italic>n</italic> = 3224)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.917</td>
                          <td align="left">0.906</td>
                          <td align="left">0.044 (0.042–0.046)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Boys (<italic>n</italic> = 2955)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.921</td>
                          <td align="left">0.910</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.046–0.050)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 1<sup>a</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.927</td>
                          <td align="left">0.917</td>
                          <td align="left">0.045 (0.044–0.047)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 2<sup>b</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.933</td>
                          <td align="left">0.927</td>
                          <td align="left">0.043 (0.041–0.044)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 2 vs 1</td>
                          <td align="left">0.006</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 3<sup>c</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.928</td>
                          <td align="left">0.925</td>
                          <td align="left">0.043 (0.042–0.045)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 3 vs 2</td>
                          <td align="left">0.005</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6"> Child age</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  3-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 2257)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.929</td>
                          <td align="left">0.919</td>
                          <td align="left">0.044 (0.041–0.046)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  4-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 2100)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.916</td>
                          <td align="left">0.905</td>
                          <td align="left">0.047 (0.045–0.050)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  5-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 2279)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.939</td>
                          <td align="left">0.930</td>
                          <td align="left">0.042 (0.040–0.045)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 1<sup>a</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.928</td>
                          <td align="left">0.919</td>
                          <td align="left">0.044 (0.043–0.046)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 2<sup>b</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.937</td>
                          <td align="left">0.932</td>
                          <td align="left">0.040 (0.039–0.042)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 2 vs 1</td>
                          <td align="left">0.009</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 3<sup>c</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.928</td>
                          <td align="left">0.926</td>
                          <td align="left">0.042 (0.041–0.044)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 3 vs 2</td>
                          <td align="left">0.009</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6">Preschool teachers</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6"> Child gender<sup>§</sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Girls (<italic>n</italic> = 2596)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.944</td>
                          <td align="left">0.936</td>
                          <td align="left">0.045 (0.043–0.048)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Boys (<italic>n</italic> = 2770)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.957</td>
                          <td align="left">0.951</td>
                          <td align="left">0.052 (0.050–0.054)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 1<sup>a</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.952</td>
                          <td align="left">0.946</td>
                          <td align="left">0.049 (0.047–0.050)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">   Model 2<sup>b</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.960</td>
                          <td align="left">0.957</td>
                          <td align="left">0.044 (0.042–0.045)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 2 vs 1</td>
                          <td align="left">0.008</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 3<sup>c</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.957</td>
                          <td align="left">0.955</td>
                          <td align="left">0.044 (0.043–0.046)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 3 vs 2</td>
                          <td align="left">0.003</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6"> Child age</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  3-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 1828)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.955</td>
                          <td align="left">0.949</td>
                          <td align="left">0.049 (0.046–0.052)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  4-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 1710)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.950</td>
                          <td align="left">0.944</td>
                          <td align="left">0.051 (0.048–0.054)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  5-year-olds (<italic>n</italic> = 1829)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.967</td>
                          <td align="left">0.962</td>
                          <td align="left">0.040 (0.037–0.043)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 1<sup>a</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.957</td>
                          <td align="left">0.951</td>
                          <td align="left">0.047 (0.045–0.048)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 2<sup>b</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.965</td>
                          <td align="left">0.962</td>
                          <td align="left">0.041 (0.040–0.043)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 2 vs 1</td>
                          <td align="left">0.008</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">  Model 3<sup>c</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.960</td>
                          <td align="left">0.959</td>
                          <td align="left">0.043 (0.041–0.045)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 3 vs 2</td>
                          <td align="left">0.005</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p><italic>CFI</italic> Comparative Fit Index, <italic>TLI</italic> Tucker-Lewis Index, <italic>RMSEA</italic> root mean square error of approximation</p>
                      <p>CFI or TLI &gt; 0.90 and RMSEA &lt; 0.06 indicate acceptable fit; Change in CFI (∆ CFI) used as criteria test differences between two nested models—∆ CFI less than 0.01 indicates <italic>p</italic> &gt; .05 (not significant)</p>
                      <p><sup>a</sup>All parameters free</p>
                      <p><sup>b</sup>Constrained factor loadings</p>
                      <p><sup>c</sup>Constrained factor loadings and intercepts</p>
                      <p><sup>†</sup>3 cases with missing gender information</p>
                      <p><sup>‡</sup>8 cases with missing gender information</p>
                      <p><sup>§</sup>1 case with missing gender information</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p id="Par25">
                  <table-wrap id="Tab5">
                    <label>Table 5</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Model fit and nested model comparisons for multiple-group CFA: parental education level</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="2">Multiple group CFA</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="3">Model Fit Indices</th>
                          <th align="left" colspan="2">Nested model comparisons</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left">CFI</th>
                          <th align="left">TLI</th>
                          <th align="left">RMSEA</th>
                          <th align="left">Comparison</th>
                          <th align="left">Change in CFI</th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6">Fathers</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Lower education (<italic>n</italic> = 2630)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.917</td>
                          <td align="left">0.907</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.046–0.050)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Higher education (<italic>n</italic> = 2827)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.914</td>
                          <td align="left">0.903</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.046–0.050)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Model 1<sup>a</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.916</td>
                          <td align="left">0.905</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.046–0.049)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Model 2<sup>b</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.923</td>
                          <td align="left">0.916</td>
                          <td align="left">0.045 (0.043–0.046)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 2 vs 1</td>
                          <td align="left">0.008</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Model 3<sup>c</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.919</td>
                          <td align="left">0.915</td>
                          <td align="left">0.045 (0.044–0.047)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 3 vs 2</td>
                          <td align="left">0.004</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" colspan="6">Mothers</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Lower education (<italic>n</italic> = 2331)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.924</td>
                          <td align="left">0.914</td>
                          <td align="left">0.048 (0.046–0.051)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Higher education (<italic>n</italic> = 3991)</td>
                          <td align="left">0.930</td>
                          <td align="left">0.921</td>
                          <td align="left">0.043 (0.042–0.045)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Model 1<sup>a</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.926</td>
                          <td align="left">0.917</td>
                          <td align="left">0.045 (0.044–0.047)</td>
                          <td align="left"/>
                          <td align="left"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Model 2<sup>b</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.932</td>
                          <td align="left">0.926</td>
                          <td align="left">0.043 (0.041–0.044)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 2 vs 1</td>
                          <td align="left">0.006</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"> Model 3<sup>c</sup></td>
                          <td align="left">0.928</td>
                          <td align="left">0.924</td>
                          <td align="left">0.043 (0.042–0.045)</td>
                          <td align="left">Model 3 vs 2</td>
                          <td align="left">0.004</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <table-wrap-foot>
                      <p><italic>CFI</italic> Comparative Fit Index, <italic>TLI</italic> Tucker-Lewis Index, <italic>RMSEA</italic> root mean square error of approximation</p>
                      <p>CFI or TLI &gt; 0.90 and RMSEA &lt; 0.06 indicate acceptable fit; Change in CFI (∆ CFI) used as criteria test differences between two nested models—∆ CFI less than 0.01 indicates <italic>p</italic> &gt; .05 (not significant)</p>
                      <p><sup>a</sup>All parameters free</p>
                      <p><sup>b</sup>Constrained factor loadings</p>
                      <p><sup>c</sup>Constrained factor loadings and intercepts</p>
                    </table-wrap-foot>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
                <p id="Par26">To assess MI across 3-, 4-, and 5-year-olds, similar procedures were undertaken, with separate analyses for fathers, mothers and preschool teachers. No significant changes in CFI were found when testing for metric invariance (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Likewise, with additional restrictions on intercepts, scalar invariance was considered to be present. The results implied MI across child age groups for fathers, mothers, and preschool teachers.</p>
                <p id="Par27">Next, MI across education level groups of mothers and fathers was assessed, using the same procedures as above. Both metric and scalar invariance were established, based on non-significant changes in CFI. See Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> for fit measures and model comparisons.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec12" sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par28">The purpose of this study was to investigate the factor structure of the SDQ for fathers, mothers and preschool teachers in a community sample, as well as to assess measurement invariance across child gender, child age, and parental education level. Our study adds to the psychometric literature on the SDQ and specifically increases knowledge about the construct validity of the SDQ when rating pre-schoolers. Previous research has mainly focused on school-aged children and adolescents and rarely on preschool children only, making our study a new and valuable contribution to knowledge on the SDQ for this age group by thoroughly assessing the factor structure across different informants and confirming MI. Our findings show that the original five-factor model of the SDQ can indeed be used on younger children in a general child population, also indicating its reliability in the hands of different informants.</p>
              <p id="Par29">This is the first time that data from fathers have been analysed separately through CFA when assessing the construct validity of the SDQ for pre-schoolers, and the second time for all ages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Fathers are increasingly involved in and important for the child’s development and can provide very useful information about the child [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Still, psychometric properties of questionnaires like the SDQ that measure children’s behaviour and emotional problems have seldom been investigated for fathers. To secure gender equality at child health services concerning involvement of both parents, it is essential to use instruments that are validated for fathers as well as mothers.</p>
              <p id="Par30">In addition, preschool teachers as informants have not been thoroughly assessed before, making this study an important contribution to aggregated knowledge on the SDQ. It is also an important step towards gathering reliable information from multiple sources when assessing children’s mental health, as recommended by Goodman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In a study by Fält et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], the child health nurses reported that the quality of health check-ups for 3–5-year-olds improved when they had SDQ ratings from the preschool teacher as well as from the parents. The present study adds to the knowledge on the SDQ as a valuable tool for screening for mental illness in children by assessing its construct validity when used on preschool children. Since 95% of all preschool children in Sweden visit child health centres regularly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and attend preschool, using the SDQ as the standard procedure in this setting could be one way of reaching children at risk at an early stage.</p>
              <p id="Par31">The invariance analyses suggest that both metric and scalar invariances are present for all informants, across child gender, child age, and education levels of the parents. MI has only been established across different countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] and informant groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Although Stone et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] provide some evidence for metric invariance across child gender and maternal education level for mothers rating school children, the cut-offs that they used for acceptable fit were more liberal than generally recommended. Our study shows metric invariance according to more conservative standards.</p>
              <p id="Par32">The results from our study confirm the five-factor structure for the Swedish version of the SDQ, thus being in line with previous studies suggesting that the SDQ is comparable across cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The results also indicate that cultural modification of the SDQ, in terms of an altered wording of three items, based on preschool organisational preferences, did not jeopardise the model fit.</p>
              <p id="Par33">Although the factor structure was acceptable for mothers, fathers and preschool teachers alike, we were not able to test for MI across informants. This was due to the fact that many children in the current sample were rated by more than one informant. Thus, clustering effects were likely to occur in a random fashion, for which we were not able to control. Therefore, we decided to analyse the data from the three informants separately, resulting in as much data as possible and not introducing possible confounders by removing children not rated by all informants. Comparison of fitness between informants was therefore not possible, which can be seen as a limitation.</p>
              <p id="Par34">The sample in our study included a larger proportion of people with higher education compared to the distribution within the municipality. Although we cannot completely eliminate the possibility that the slightly lopsided sample in terms of parental education level could affect the factor structure, MI across the education variable suggests that the SDQ is a valid instrument across different parental education levels.</p>
              <p id="Par35">As the SDQ shows satisfactory construct validity, it would be desirable to present norms for this age group and for all three informants in a future study. In fact, to facilitate the application of the SDQ in clinical settings, it is necessary to provide norms from a large community sample, covering children aged 3–5 and all three informants. Finally, although we found the construct validity to be good in the present study, we did not analyse any competing theoretical models of the factor structure of the SDQ. It is possible that another theoretical model would provide even better fit, such as the four-factor multi-trait-multi-method structure suggested by Bull et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. However, since the original model is the one being used in clinical practice and the only model provided with norms, we chose to analyse this model only.</p>
              <p id="Par36">Notwithstanding the above-mentioned limitations, the results from our study imply that the SDQ is a feasible instrument for assessing emotional and behavioural problems among preschool children. Moreover, our study is an important step in investigating whether the original five-factor structure of the SDQ can be used in large community samples. Findings based on fathers’ ratings suggest acceptable fit, implying that the SDQ rated by fathers can be used to the same extent as mothers’ ratings to assess behaviour problems among preschool children.</p>
              <p id="Par37">Lastly, the sample in this study was a non-clinical sample, which allowed for assessment of the construct validity of the instrument when used on the general population. Factor analytic studies from the lengthier but comparable CBCL for preschool children indicate good fit when rated by parents or preschool teachers in clinical and non-clinical samples in most but not all studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. However, CFAs assessing fathers’ ratings have not examined the questionnaire on subscale-level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Our findings suggest that the SDQ might be a suitable instrument for epidemiological studies of preschool children’s mental health and can be used in its originally proposed five-factor solution in non-clinical populations. This enables thorough investigation of subscale differences in epidemiological studies, thus resulting in more detailed studies of populations.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec13">
              <title>Summary</title>
              <p id="Par38">The SDQ is a well-established instrument for measuring social and behavioural problems among children, with good psychometric properties for older children, but less validity reports on pre-schoolers. In addition, there is a knowledge gap concerning fathers as informants. The present work is one of the few validity studies to include preschool teachers and the first on preschool children, where fathers are included as separate informants. In this study, the SDQ was collected from a large community sample (<italic>n</italic> = 17,752) of children aged 3–5, rated by mothers, fathers, and preschool teachers and analysed using alpha calculations and confirmatory factor analysis. Measurement invariance analyses were also conducted to assess invariance across child gender, child age, and parental education level. Our results revealed high internal consistency, acceptable fit for all informant groups and measurement invariance across child gender, child age, and parental education level. Our findings suggest good construct validity of the SDQ for a non-clinical preschool population and imply that it may be used for assessing behaviour problems in pre-schoolers from different informant perspectives.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>This research was supported by a joint grant from major Swedish research funders FORMAS, Vetenskapsrådet, FAS and VINNOVA (Grant No. 259-2012-68). We thank our colleagues at CHAP for their help with data collection, particularly Helena Fabian, Elisabet Fält and Antónia Tökes.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
              <sec id="FPar1">
                <title>Conflict of interest</title>
                <p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="FPar2">
                <title>Ethical Approval</title>
                <p>All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national research committee and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards. The study was approved by the Regional Ethical Review Board in Uppsala (Dnr 2012/437).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="FPar3">
                <title>Informed Consent</title>
                <p>Informed consent was obtained from the parents of all children included in the study.</p>
              </sec>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klasen</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparing the German versions of the strengths and difficulties questionnaire (SDQ-Deu) and the child behavior checklist</article-title>
                  <source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <lpage>276</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s007870070030</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11202102</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scott</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparing the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire and the child behavior checklist: is small beautiful?</article-title>
                  <source>J Abnorm Child Psychol</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <lpage>24</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1022658222914</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10197403</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stone</surname>
                      <given-names>LL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Otten</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Engels</surname>
                      <given-names>RC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vermulst</surname>
                      <given-names>AA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Janssens</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychometric properties of the parent and teacher versions of the strengths and difficulties questionnaire for 4-to 12-year-olds: a review</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Child Fam Psychol Rev</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <lpage>274</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10567-010-0071-2</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20589428</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ford</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Simmons</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gatward</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meltzer</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Using the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) to screen for child psychiatric disorders in a community sample</article-title>
                  <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>177</volume>
                  <fpage>534</fpage>
                  <lpage>539</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.177.6.534</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11102329</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>He</surname>
                      <given-names>J-P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burstein</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schmitz</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Merikangas</surname>
                      <given-names>KR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ): the factor structure and scale validation in US adolescents</article-title>
                  <source>J Abnorm Child Psychol</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <fpage>583</fpage>
                  <lpage>595</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10802-012-9696-6</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23183936</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Croft</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stride</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maughan</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rowe</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validity of the strengths and difficulties questionnaire in preschool-aged children</article-title>
                  <source>Pediatrics</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>135</volume>
                  <fpage>e1210</fpage>
                  <lpage>e1219</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2014-2920</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25847804</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van Roy</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Veenstra</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clench-Aas</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Construct validity of the five-factor Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) in pre-, early, and late adolescence</article-title>
                  <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <fpage>1304</fpage>
                  <lpage>1312</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.2008.01942.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19120709</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Becker</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychopathological screening of children with ADHD: Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire in a pan-European study</article-title>
                  <source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <fpage>i56</fpage>
                  <lpage>i62</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00787-006-1008-7</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17177017</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klein</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Otto</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fuchs</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zenger</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>von Klitzing</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychometric properties of the parent-rated SDQ in preschoolers</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Psychol Assess</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>96104</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1027/1015-5759/a000129</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hawes</surname>
                      <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dadds</surname>
                      <given-names>MR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Australian data and psychometric properties of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</article-title>
                  <source>Aust N Z J Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>644</fpage>
                  <lpage>651</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/j.1440-1614.2004.01427.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15298588</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mellor</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stokes</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The factor structure of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Psychol Assess</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1027/1015-5759.23.2.105</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ruchkin</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koposov</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schwab-Stone</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Strength and Difficulties Questionnaire: scale validation with Russian adolescents</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Psychol</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>63</volume>
                  <fpage>861</fpage>
                  <lpage>869</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.20401</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17674399</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodman</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lamping</surname>
                      <given-names>DL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ploubidis</surname>
                      <given-names>GB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>When to use broader internalising and externalising subscales instead of the hypothesised five subscales on the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ): data from British parents, teachers and children</article-title>
                  <source>J Abnorm Child Psychol</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>1179</fpage>
                  <lpage>1191</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10802-010-9434-x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20623175</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ezpeleta</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Granero</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de la Osa</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Penelo</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Domènech</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire 3–4 in 3-year-old preschoolers</article-title>
                  <source>Compr Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <lpage>291</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.comppsych.2012.07.009</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22999518</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gustafsson</surname>
                      <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gustafsson</surname>
                      <given-names>PA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Proczkowska-Björklund</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) for preschool children—a Swedish validation</article-title>
                  <source>Nord J Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>70</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08039488.2016.1184309</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25971862</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van den Heuvel</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>How reliable and valid is the teacher version of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire in primary school children?</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>e0176605</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0176605</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28453573</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davé</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nazareth</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Senior</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sherr</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison of father and mother report of child behaviour on the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</article-title>
                  <source>Child Psychiatry Hum Dev</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
                  <lpage>413</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10578-008-0097-6</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18266104</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bruce</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rodgers</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Firth</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freeston</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mum knows best? Psychological status in an oncology sample</article-title>
                  <source>Child Care Health Dev</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <fpage>643</fpage>
                  <lpage>648</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2214.2005.00553.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16207221</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Björnsdotter</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Enebrink</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghaderi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychometric properties of online administered parental strengths and difficulties questionnaire (SDQ), and normative data based on combined online and paper-and-pencil administration</article-title>
                  <source>Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1753-2000-7-40</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23331706</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mieloo</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validity and reliability of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire in 5–6 year olds: differences by gender or by parental education?</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>e36805</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036805</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22629332</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Becker</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Woerner</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hasselhorn</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banaschewski</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rothenberger</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Validation of the parent and teacher SDQ in a clinical sample</article-title>
                  <source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>ii11</fpage>
                  <lpage>ii16</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15243781</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiorri</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hall</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Casely-Hayford</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malmberg</surname>
                      <given-names>L-E</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluating measurement invariance between parents using the strengths and difficulties questionnaire (SDQ)</article-title>
                  <source>Assessment</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <lpage>74</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073191114568301</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25604631</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stone</surname>
                      <given-names>LL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The parent version of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</article-title>
                  <source>Eur J Psychol Assess</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <lpage>50</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1027/1015-5759/a000119</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salari</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Children and Parents in Focus project: a population-based cluster-randomised controlled trial to prevent behavioural and emotional problems in children</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Public Health</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>961</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-13-961</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24131587</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Swedish National Agency for Education (2013) Children and staff in preschool autumn 2012 (Barn och personal i förskolan hösten 2012). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.skolverket.se">http://www.skolverket.se</ext-link> (<bold>In Swedish</bold>). Accessed 5 May 2018</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wallby</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Modin</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hjern</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Child health care utilisation in families with young or single mothers in a Swedish county</article-title>
                  <source>J Child Health Care</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <lpage>29</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1367493512450624</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23197384</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire: a research note</article-title>
                  <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <fpage>581</fpage>
                  <lpage>586</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.1997.tb01545.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9255702</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>R Core Team</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>
                  <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gadermann</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guhn</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zumbo</surname>
                      <given-names>BD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating ordinal reliability for Likert-type and ordinal item response data: a conceptual, empirical, and practical guide</article-title>
                  <source>Pract Assess Res Eval</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Revelle W (2014) psych: Procedures for personality and psychological research. Northwestern University, Evanston. R package version 1</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rosseel</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>lavaan: an R package for structural equation modeling</article-title>
                  <source>J Stat Softw</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>36</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v048.i02</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bowen</surname>
                      <given-names>NK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Masa</surname>
                      <given-names>RD</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Conducting measurement invariance tests with ordinal data: a guide for social work researchers</article-title>
                  <source>J Soc Social Work</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <lpage>249</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/681607</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lt</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bentler</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: conventional criteria versus new alternatives</article-title>
                  <source>Struct Equ Model</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>55</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10705519909540118</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barrett</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Structural equation modelling: adjudging model fit</article-title>
                  <source>Pers Individ Differ</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>815</fpage>
                  <lpage>824</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.paid.2006.09.018</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fan</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of sample size, estimation methods, and model specification on structural equation modeling fit indexes</article-title>
                  <source>Struct Equ Model</source>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <lpage>83</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10705519909540119</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheung</surname>
                      <given-names>GW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rensvold</surname>
                      <given-names>RB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluating goodness-of-fit indexes for testing measurement invariance</article-title>
                  <source>Struct Equ Model</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <lpage>255</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15328007SEM0902_5</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>FF</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Sensitivity of goodness of fit indexes to lack of measurement invariance</article-title>
                  <source>Struct Equ Model</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <fpage>464</fpage>
                  <lpage>504</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10705510701301834</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarkadi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kristiansson</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oberklaid</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bremberg</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fathers’ involvement and children’s developmental outcomes: a systematic review of longitudinal studies</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Paedr</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>97</volume>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>158</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1651-2227.2007.00572.x</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goodman</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Psychometric properties of the strengths and difficulties questionnaire</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Acad Child Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>1337</fpage>
                  <lpage>1345</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-200111000-00015</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fält</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarkadi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fabian</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Exploring nurses’, preschool teachers’ and parents’ perspectives on information sharing using SDQ in a Swedish setting—a qualitative study using grounded theory</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>e0168388</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0168388</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28076401</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ortuño-Sierra</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>New evidence of factor structure and measurement invariance of the SDQ across five European nations</article-title>
                  <source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <fpage>1523</fpage>
                  <lpage>1534</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00787-015-0729-x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26036862</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matsuishi</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Scale properties of the Japanese version of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ): a study of infant and school children in community samples</article-title>
                  <source>Brain Dev</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>30</volume>
                  <fpage>410</fpage>
                  <lpage>415</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.braindev.2007.12.003</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18226867</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bull</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koh</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Poon</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Confirmatory factor analysis of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire in Singaporean kindergartners</article-title>
                  <source>Child Care Health Dev</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <lpage>116</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cch.12288</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26470606</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lengua</surname>
                      <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sadowski</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Friedrich</surname>
                      <given-names>WN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fisher</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Rationally and empirically derived dimensions of children’s symptomatology: expert ratings and confirmatory factor analyses of the CBCL</article-title>
                  <source>J Consult Clin Psychol</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <fpage>683</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-006X.69.4.683</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11550734</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ivanova</surname>
                      <given-names>MY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Preschool psychopathology reported by parents in 23 societies: testing the seven-syndrome model of the child behavior checklist for ages 1.5–5</article-title>
                  <source>J Am Acad Child Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <fpage>1215</fpage>
                  <lpage>1224</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ivanova</surname>
                      <given-names>MY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Syndromes of preschool psychopathology reported by teachers and caregivers in 14 societies using the caregiver-teacher report form (C-TRF)</article-title>
                  <source>J Early Child Infant Psychol</source>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <lpage>116</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pandolfi</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magyar</surname>
                      <given-names>CI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dill</surname>
                      <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Confirmatory factor analysis of the Child Behavior Checklist 1.5–5 in a sample of children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>
                  <source>J Autism Dev Disord</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <fpage>986</fpage>
                  <lpage>995</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-009-0716-5</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19263208</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR48">
                <label>48.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kerr</surname>
                      <given-names>DC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lunkenheimer</surname>
                      <given-names>ES</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Olson</surname>
                      <given-names>SL</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Assessment of child problem behaviors by multiple informants: a longitudinal study from preschool to school entry</article-title>
                  <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <fpage>967</fpage>
                  <lpage>975</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01776.x</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17914997</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
