<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-07T13:04:24Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6476491" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6476491</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-05-07</datestamp>
        <setSpec>plosone</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6476491</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6476491</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6476491</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31009465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0214945</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-18-31209</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>The magnitude of sex differences in verbal episodic memory increases with social progress: Data from 54 countries across 40 years</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Sex differences in episodic memory across countries</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6340-3638</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Asperholm</surname>
                    <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nagar</surname>
                    <given-names>Sanket</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dekhtyar</surname>
                    <given-names>Serhiy</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Herlitz</surname>
                    <given-names>Agneta</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
                  <role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff001">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Division of Psychology, Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <aff id="aff002">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Monash Institute of Cognitive and Clinical Neuroscience, School of Psychological Science, Monash University, Melbourne, Australia</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <aff id="aff003">
                <label>3</label>
                <addr-line>Aging Research Center, Department of Neurobiology, Care Sciences and Society, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ginsberg</surname>
                    <given-names>Stephen D.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role>Editor</role>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="edit1">
                <addr-line>Nathan S Kline Institute, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
              </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001">
                  <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
                </fn>
                <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>martin.asperholm@ki.se</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>14</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <elocation-id>e0214945</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>29</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2019 Asperholm et al</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Asperholm et al</copyright-holder>
                <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0214945.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <p>Sex differences in episodic memory have been reported. We investigate (1) the existence of sex differences in verbal and other episodic memory tasks in 54 countries, and (2) the association between the time- and country-specific social progress indicators (a) female to male ratio in education and labor force participation, (b) population education and employment, and (c) GDP per capita, and magnitude of sex differences in verbal episodic memory tasks. Data were retrieved from 612 studies, published 1973–2013. Results showed that females outperformed (Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> &gt; 0) males in verbal (42 out of 45 countries) and other (28 out of 45 countries) episodic memory tasks. Although all three social progress indicators were, separately, positively associated with the female advantage in verbal episodic memory performance, only population education and employment remained significant when considering the social indicators together. Results suggest that women’s verbal episodic memory performance benefits more than men’s from education and employment.</p>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group id="award001">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution>Swedish Research Council</institution>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>721-2014-2241</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herlitz</surname>
                      <given-names>Agneta</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
                <award-group id="award002">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution>Swedish Council for Working Life and Social Research (FORTE)</institution>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>2010-0705</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herlitz</surname>
                      <given-names>Agneta</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
                <funding-statement>This research was supported by grants awarded to Agneta Herlitz by the Swedish Research Council (grant no. 521-2007-3020, 421-2009-2255, and 721-2014-2241) and the Swedish Research Council for Health, Working Life and Welfare (FORTE) (grant no. 2010-0705).</funding-statement>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="2"/>
                <table-count count="1"/>
                <page-count count="11"/>
              </counts>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta id="data-availability">
                  <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>All relevant data are within the manuscript and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
            <notes>
              <title>Data Availability</title>
              <p>All relevant data are within the manuscript and its Supporting Information files.</p>
            </notes>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>The presence of sex differences in some but not all cognitive functions is well documented [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. For example, women are often reported to have an advantage in verbal production [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], reading comprehension [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and episodic memory (recollection of past experiences in terms of their content, location, and temporal occurrence; [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]), while men often perform at a higher level on visuospatial [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and some numerical tasks [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. These sex differences are typically modest in size and the underlying mechanisms are not yet sufficiently understood. Despite this, they have consistently been reported from early childhood into old age, and in most examined regions of the world, although their magnitude seems to vary across countries [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Here, factors contributing to the variation in magnitude of sex differences in episodic memory will be examined.</p>
              <p>Along with the constant progression in economic, political, environmental, and social landscapes across the globe [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], there is evidence suggesting that cognitive performance is improving. The <italic>Flynn effect</italic>, describing intergenerational gains in IQ scores, has been documented in almost every region where it has been examined [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Some of the factors contributing to these cognitive gains across generations are increased education, shifts in family size, and strengthened health care [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The <italic>Flynn effect</italic> is typically larger in regions that have experienced the most rapid pace of development over the examined time period [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and women are reported to exhibit a larger <italic>Flynn effect</italic> than men [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p>
              <p>The gender equality of a country often refers to the degree to which women, relative to men, have access to education, economic opportunity, and political resources and may thereby be an indicator of the living conditions of women. Several composite and domain-specific nation-level indicators of gender equality exist, focusing to a varying degree on political resources, economic opportunities, education, and health [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Based on findings of the origin of the <italic>Flynn effect</italic>, the association between indicators of gender equality and sex differences in cognitive performance is of interest.</p>
              <p>The associations between gender equality indicators and cognitive sex differences have been investigated using the PISA database, where data on mathematics performance and reading comprehension in 15-16-year-olds is available between the years 2000 and 2009 (OECD-PISA). For example, Guiso and colleagues [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] examined the 2003 PISA wave and reported associations between the Gender Gap Index (GGI; [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]) on the one hand, and mathematical performance on the other, with boys´ overall advantage disappearing in the most gender equal countries. Else-Quest and colleagues [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] examined other indicators of gender equality and mathematics performance in the same 2003 PISA wave and for Trends in International Mathematics and Science Study (IEA-TIMSS). Associations were found between gender equality in girls´ school enrollment and TIMSS, and between other indicators of gender equality and sex differences in mathematic performance in PISA data. In contrast, Stoet and Geary [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] reported that no consistent pattern could be found when analyzing all four PISA waves in relation to GGI and other gender equality indicators from United Nations Development Project (UNDP). Also, Lippa and colleagues [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] investigated mental rotation and line angle judgment performance in the BBC internet survey of human sex differences [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and found a relationship between these measures and gender equality going in the opposite direction, with larger sex differences favoring men in more gender equal societies.</p>
              <p>Relatively few studies have been conducted on sex differences in those cognitive areas in which there is a general female advantage. However, a larger female advantage in the PISA reading comprehension test has been found in more gender equal societies [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], although not systematically [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Using data from Survey of Health, Ageing and Retirement in Europe (SHARE), Weber [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] reported that having experienced better living conditions in younger adulthood is associated with larger sex differences favoring women in a verbal episodic memory task across 13 European countries in individuals 50 years and older. Similarly, Bonsang and colleagues [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], also using data from SHARE and databases from other international studies, found that educational attainment, labor-market participation and societal gender norms favoring women’s participation in the work force were positively related to a female advantage in the same verbal episodic memory task assessed in 27 countries.</p>
              <p>Taken together, findings on the association between social progress indicators and sex differences in cognitive tasks are mixed. Furthermore, most research has been conducted on the same databases, thereby limiting the generalizability of the research to sex differences in mathematics, reading comprehension, and a specific verbal episodic memory task. In contrast, we used 612 individual studies published 1973–2013, originating from 54 countries to, first, examine the existence of sex differences across countries in both verbal and other episodic memory tasks. Because recent research [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] has demonstrated that similar patterns of cognitive sex differences exist across nations, we expected to find sex differences favoring females in most countries. Our second goal was to explain potential cross-national variability in these sex differences, exploring whether time-specific national indicators of gender equality, education level and labor force participation, and economic development are associated with cross-national variations of sex differences in episodic memory. We hypothesized that these national and time-specific indicators would be positively correlated with a relative female advantage in episodic memory and that the indicator of gender equality would be the strongest predictor.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="sec003">
                <title>Dataset</title>
                <p>A database of effect sizes—standardized differences in episodic memory performance between men and women—was obtained from a meta-analysis investigating sex differences in episodic memory [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In total, the database consisted of 612 studies originating from 54 different countries, published between 1973 and 2013, involving a total of 587,691 participants. Most of the articles included had several samples (e.g., age groups), participating in more than one episodic memory task (e.g., list of word and list of faces), some with more than one dependent measure (e.g., free and cued recall of a word list, and immediate and delayed recognition of faces).</p>
                <p>All studies included in the database fulfilled the following criteria: (1) the study contained original, empirical data and was published in a peer-reviewed journal available in English; (2) the sample consisted of males and females who were not selected based on based on any diagnosis, disease, or disorder and not influenced in any way that may have affected their episodic memory performance; (3) episodic memory was tested using controlled and uniform tasks for all participants within the sample; and (4) the dependent measure assessed episodic memory performance (Asperholm et al., 2018). For more information about the dataset, see Asperholm and colleagues [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec004">
                <title>Episodic memory tasks</title>
                <p>The episodic memory tasks were originally sorted into eight categories based on the material to be remembered [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Here, we analyzed the dataset <italic>Verbal</italic>, in which the episodic memory tasks consisted of words, sentences, facts, conversations, or nameable objects to be remembered. This category contained 495 studies originating from 45 countries. The other seven categories, <italic>Images</italic>, <italic>Faces</italic>, <italic>Movies</italic>, <italic>Locations</italic>, <italic>Routes</italic>, <italic>Sensory</italic>, <italic>and Remaining</italic> were not analyzed separately because they originated from a limited number of countries (<italic>Movies</italic> k = 7; <italic>Routes</italic> k = 9; <italic>Faces</italic> k = 12; <italic>Sensory</italic> k = 4), had social indicator distributions which negated useful analyses (<italic>Images</italic>; <italic>Locations</italic>), or had material which was unknown or could not be categorized into any of the categories (<italic>Remaining</italic>). Instead, these categories were combined into the dataset <italic>Other</italic> episodic memory tasks, thus, containing all effect sizes but those included in <italic>Verbal</italic>. The <italic>Other</italic> category contained 373 studies originating from 45 countries.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec005">
                <title>Country and year</title>
                <p>For both datasets, <italic>Verbal</italic> and <italic>Other</italic>, if information regarding the country where the study was conducted was not explicitly stated in the article, it was derived from the affiliation(s) of the (first) author(s). Studies originating from countries from which predictors could not be retrieved were excluded, resulting in 54 countries being represented in the final data set. Since exact dates for data collection were not available for most studies, dates were estimated by subtracting 1 from year of publication. Thus, the data collections forming the basis of the included studies were assumed to have taken place between 1972 and 2013.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec006">
                <title>Social progress indicators</title>
                <p>Three indicators of a country’s living conditions were assessed for their association with the magnitude of sex differences in episodic memory performance. As the studies used in the analyses had been conducted at different time-points, spanning from 1972 to 2013, the indicators needed to be time-specific as well as country-specific. The indicators, described below, were retrieved from the World Bank (WB; [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]) and UNDP [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p>
                <sec id="sec007">
                  <title>Gender equality</title>
                  <p>This is a composite measure that comprises (1) the UNDP indicator Average Years of Schooling Attained (Female population, 25 years and over) subtracted by Average Years of Schooling Attained (Male population, 25 years and over) and (2) the WB indicator Female to male ratio in labor force participation (for ages between 15 and 64). All data points were z-transformed using the mean and standard deviation for all possible year/country combinations of the included countries throughout the relevant years 1972–2013. This composite measure was assumed to be indicative of national gender equality in educational and occupational opportunities from 1972 to 2013.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec008">
                  <title>Population education and employment</title>
                  <p>This is a composite measure that comprises (1) the UNDP indicator <italic>Average Years of Schooling Attained (Total population</italic>, <italic>25 years and over)</italic> and (2) the WB indicator <italic>Labor force participation rate</italic> (% of total population ages 15–64). All data points were z-transformed using the mean and standard deviation for all possible year/country combinations for the included countries throughout the relevant years 1972–2013. This composite measure was assumed to be indicative of the national education level and labor force participation from 1972 to 2013.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec009">
                  <title>GDP per capita</title>
                  <p>Gross domestic product (GDP) per capita is a measure of economic activity in relation to the size of the population. This measure, given in current US dollars, was extracted from the WB database and subsequently transformed using the natural logarithm to achieve a normal distribution of the variable. All data points were z-transformed using the mean and standard deviation for all possible year/country combinations of the included countries throughout the relevant years 1972–2013.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec010">
                  <title>Data extrapolation</title>
                  <p>The indicators of <italic>Average Years of Schooling Attained</italic> (UNDP) were available in 5-year intervals. Indicators of <italic>Labor force participation</italic> (WB) had a more consistent coverage but were only available from 1990 and onwards, while <italic>GDP per Capita</italic> was available for the complete time-range. If an indicator value was missing for a certain year and country combination, linear extrapolation was undertaken using the closest available data points before and after the year in question. If only a later or prior data point was available, the value of that data point was used. For the full dataset, this resulted in estimations of 43% of the values for <italic>Gender Equality</italic>, 43% for <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic>, and 0% for <italic>GDP per Capita</italic>.</p>
                  <p>A table of the studies, effect sizes, and social progress indicators included in the analyses, can be found in Supporting information (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0214945.s001">S1 Table</xref>), together with a list of references for those studies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0214945.s003">S1 References</xref>).</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec011">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Sex differences were specified using Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> ((<italic>m</italic><sub>women</sub>−<italic>m</italic><sub>men</sub>)/ <italic>sd</italic><sub>total</sub>), with a positive effect size indicating an advantage for females in episodic memory and a negative effect size indicating an advantage for males. Analyses of publication bias has previously been reported, which showed that the sex differences in episodic memory did not result from a bias to study or report sex differences, or from using selective samples [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p>
                <p>In order to determine the presence as well as the extent of sex differences in <italic>Verbal</italic> and <italic>Other</italic> across countries, two five-level random-effects meta-analytic linear models with country as a discrete moderator were performed (accounting for the hierarchical structure of the data with studies, samples and tasks described under <italic>Dataset</italic>).</p>
                <p>The next step involved examining the association between living conditions (<italic>Gender Equality</italic>, <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic>, and <italic>GDP per Capita</italic>) and sex differences in episodic memory for <italic>Verbal</italic> and <italic>Other</italic> across countries over the period 1972–2013. First, we computed the correlations (Pearson’s <italic>r</italic>) between the social progress indicators alone, followed by separate six-level meta-regression models (adding country as a hierarchical level) assessing the direct effects of each measure on sex differences in <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory tasks. The final part of the analysis involved fitting a meta-regression that included all three indicators, allowing us to assess the independent contributions of <italic>Gender Equality</italic>, <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic>, and <italic>GDP per Capita</italic> to the variation in sex differences in <italic>Verbal</italic>. A power analysis to calculate sample size was not computed beforehand as sample size was determined by available studies [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p>
                <p>All analyses above were performed using version 1.9–9 of the R package <italic>metafor</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec012">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Two separate five-level random effects meta-analyses with country as moderator were computed for both the datasets <italic>Verbal</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214945.g001">Fig 1A</xref>) and <italic>Other</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214945.g001">Fig 1B</xref>) to assess the overall pattern of sex differences and variation in magnitude of sex differences across countries. For <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory tasks, there was an overall female advantage (<italic>d</italic> = .27; CI = [.24, .30]; p &lt; .001) that was seen in most countries (i.e., Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> &gt; 0 in 42 out of 45 countries), although the sex difference was not statistically significant in all of them. The moderator analysis showed a statistical significant impact of country (QM (df = 44) = 185; p &lt; .001), justifying subsequent analyses trying to explain this variation.</p>
              <fig id="pone.0214945.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0214945.g001</object-id>
                <label>Fig 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Effect size estimates for each country for both task categories.</title>
                  <p>Forest plot describing the variation in sex differences in (a) Verbal and (b) Other episodic memory tasks across the (a) 45 and (b) 45 countries used in the analyses, with k = number of studies available for each country. Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> (unfilled circles) is presented on the x-axis, with error bars describing the 95% confidence intervals (notice that some error bars have been truncated). Filled circles indicate the year each study was carried out.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="pone.0214945.g001"/>
              </fig>
              <p>For <italic>Other</italic> episodic memory tasks, there was an overall small female advantage (<italic>d</italic> = .07; CI = [.03, .10]; p &lt; .001), seen in approximately four-fifths of the countries (i.e., Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> &gt; 0 in 28 out of 45 countries), but again not statistically significant in all of them. The moderator analysis showed no statistical significant impact of country (QM (df = 44) = 52; p = .18), thereby not justifying analyses of variation across countries.</p>
              <p>Correlation analyses for the full dataset revealed positive associations between the three indicators (<italic>Gender Equality</italic> vs. <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic>: <italic>r</italic> = .70, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; <italic>Gender Equality</italic> vs. <italic>GDP per Capita</italic>: <italic>r</italic> = .50, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001<italic>; Population Education and Employment</italic> vs. <italic>GDP per Capita</italic>: <italic>r</italic> = .56, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
              <p>Simple and combined models estimating direct unadjusted effects of the indicator variables <italic>Gender Equality</italic>, <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic>, and <italic>GDP per Capita</italic> were computed for <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory tasks (for summary statistics, see <xref rid="pone.0214945.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; for scatterplots of the simple effects, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214945.g002">Fig 2</xref>). For <italic>Verbal</italic>, the estimated B-values in all simple models were positive and statistically significant, whereas for the combined model, only <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic> remained significant. Because the indicator variables were transformed to z-values before they were analyzed, the estimated B-values for these indicators specify how much the magnitude of the sex difference in <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory changes per change in z-point for the indicator. Thus, in the combined model, one z-point change in <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic> is associated with an increase of 0.08 in Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> in <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory performance.</p>
              <fig id="pone.0214945.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0214945.g002</object-id>
                <label>Fig 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Scatterplots for the three simple effects analyses.</title>
                  <p>Indicator of (a) Gender equality, (b) Population Education and Employment, (c) GDP per Capita (x-axis) plotted against sex differences in Verbal episodic memory performance (y-axis). The diameter of each data point is equal to the inverse of its squared variance. The lines indicate the best-fitting regressions.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="pone.0214945.g002"/>
              </fig>
              <table-wrap id="pone.0214945.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0214945.t001</object-id>
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Summary statistics of regression analyses for <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory task.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>
                  <graphic id="pone.0214945.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0214945.t001"/>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple model 1</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple model 2</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple model 3</th>
                        <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Combined model</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Intercept</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>    Estimate</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">***</xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>    Standard error</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Gender Equality</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>    B estimate</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>    B standard error</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Population Education and Employment</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>    B estimate</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">*</xref></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>    B standard error</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>GDP per Capita</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>    B estimate</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">***</xref></td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>    B standard error</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>Observations</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2681</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2681</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2681</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2681</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>R</bold>
                          <sup>
                            <bold>2</bold>
                          </sup>
                        </td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
                        <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </alternatives>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="t001fn001">
                    <p>* p &lt; .05</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="t001fn002">
                    <p>** p &lt; .01</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="t001fn003">
                    <p>*** p &lt; .001</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Meta-regressions were also computed for <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory tasks excluding the large databases used by Weber et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and Bonsang et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], leaving the 419 studies collected by Asperholm and colleagues [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Excluding these databases did not change the overall pattern of results except that Population Education and Employment went from significant to marginally significant in the combined model (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0214945.s002">S2 Table</xref>). Similarly, analyzing only the databases used by Weber et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and Bonsang et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] yielded a similar pattern of results, the only difference between this analysis and the original for <italic>Verbal</italic> being that the estimated B-value for <italic>GDP per capita</italic> in the combined model became significant (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0214945.s002">S2 Table</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec013">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The aims of this study were (1) to determine the existence and magnitude of sex differences in episodic memory tasks across countries, and (2) to investigate if and how societal changes—in terms of time-specific national indicators of gender equality, educational level and labor force participation, and economic development—were associated with the magnitude of sex differences in episodic memory. These questions were addressed in a large dataset, including 612 studies originating from 54 countries, spanning over 40 years. In line with our hypothesis, results showed that there was an overall female advantage for <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory, found in 42 of 45 countries although not reliably so in all. <italic>Other</italic> episodic memory tasks also yielded an advantage for women, although smaller, found in 28 of 45 countries. Furthermore, results indicated that all three social progress indicators were, independently, positively associated with the female advantage in <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory performance. <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic> was the most important predictor among the three indicators for <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory, contrary to our hypothesis that gender equality would be the strongest predictor.</p>
              <p>Although the female advantage in Verbal episodic memory tasks was seen in most countries, the advantage was not reliable in all of them (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214945.g001">Fig 1A</xref>). One reason for the lack of significance may be that too few studies were conducted in some countries providing a less reliable estimate of the sex difference. The finding of a general female advantage in <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory is in line with other studies reporting an advantage for women in most countries [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. It is also in line with other research, reporting remarkably similar patterns of sex differences in reading comprehension, mathematics, mental rotation, and line angle judgment across a large number of countries (e.g., [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]). Our results extend previous findings of similarities across nations in regard to episodic memory, not only in that more countries and studies were included, but also in that the female advantage in episodic memory can be generalized to a multitude of verbal episodic memory tasks, and does not only hold for the specific word list analyzed in previous studies [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p>
              <p>By linking country- and time specific social indicators to each of the studies included in our analysis, we found that the indicators <italic>Gender equality</italic>, <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic>, and <italic>GDP per Capita</italic> were reliable predictors of the female advantage when analyzed separately. However, the only predictor of a female <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory advantage when taking all indicators into account was <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic>, an indicator of education level and labor force participation in the population. There is substantial literature showing that educational attainment is positively associated with cognitive performance, with recent evidence from quasi-experimental studies demonstrating that prolonging compulsory education by one or two years may increase cognitive performance [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. We should therefore expect an indicator of a country’s education level to be predictive of the country’s cognitive performance level in general. Our results suggest, however, that women gain cognitively more than men from higher educational and occupational participation, as the female advantage is larger in countries with higher population education and occupation. This result both confirms and extends previous findings [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] by showing that societal improvements in education and labor force participation are associated with a larger female advantage in a multitude of verbal episodic memory tasks.</p>
              <p>The indicator aimed to capture <italic>Gender Equality</italic>, namely the difference between women’s and men’s educational level and labor force participation, and <italic>GDP per Capita</italic> were both highly correlated with <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic>. It is therefore likely that <italic>Population Education and Employment</italic> captures some of the positive effects estimated in the two other indicators, thereby explaining why these indicators were relatively less predictive of the sex difference in <italic>Verbal</italic> episodic memory.</p>
              <p>The sex difference in <italic>Other</italic> episodic memory tasks was small. This is not surprising as the categories constituting <italic>Other</italic> episodic memory tasks to a varying degree yield sex differences, with a female (<italic>Movies</italic>, <italic>Locations</italic>, <italic>Faces</italic>, <italic>Sensory</italic>, <italic>Remaining</italic>), male (<italic>Routes</italic>) or no (<italic>Images</italic>) advantage [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. As the analysis of cross-national variability in the sex differences in <italic>Other</italic> episodic memory tasks came out insignificant, analyses attempting to explain variation across countries were redundant.</p>
              <sec id="sec014">
                <title>Strengths and limitations</title>
                <p>Although the current study has a number of strengths, such as assessing sex differences in a large number of countries sampled over a 40-year period, it also has some limitations. The most obvious limitation is that cause and effect inferences cannot be made; the results only suggest an association between the social indicators and the magnitude of the difference. Second, the majority of research on episodic memory is conducted in North America, Europe, and Australia, whereas few studies have been conducted in African, Asian, and South American countries. The estimates of the magnitude of the sex differences are therefore less reliable in the latter. Lastly, the current analyses comprised studies that used a variety of verbal episodic memory tasks. While this heterogeneity may act as a limitation, it also forms the basis of a very conservative test of the hypotheses.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>The results of the current study indicate that the female advantage in episodic memory is present in most countries. The results also suggest that the advantage in verbal episodic memory tasks is further heightened in countries with higher population education and labor force participation, likely serving as proxies for increased education, heightened cognitive stimulation, and a more enriching environment. Although it is still an open question why women seem to be more positively affected by these societal improvements than men, it can be hypothesized that women benefit disproportionately because they may start from a more disadvantaged level. More research into these questions is warranted.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec016">
              <title>Supporting information</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0214945.s001">
                <label>S1 Table</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Details of all studies used in the analyses.</title>
                  <p>Studies included in the database with country of study, effect size <italic>d</italic> (variance) of <italic>Verbal</italic> and <italic>Other</italic> episodic memory tasks, total number of males/females participating in the study, together with country- and time-specific measures indicative of gender equality in educational and occupational opportunities, population education level and labor force participation, and GDP per capita. Effect sizes were derived by using the formulas recommended by Borenstein et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] to combine intersample and intrasample data points. For more information about this procedure, see Asperholm et al. (5). Explanation of headings: Country = Country of study; <italic>d</italic> (variance) = Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> and variance of categories <italic>Verbal</italic> and <italic>Other</italic> episodic memory tasks (when combining all effect sizes within a study using verbal material or other, non-verbal, material); N Males/Females = The total number of males/females participating in the study; Gender equality = A country- and time-specific measure indicative of gender equality in educational and occupational opportunities; Population Education Employment = A country- and time-specific measure indicative of education level and labor force participation; GDP per Capita = A country- and time-specific measure of economic activity in relation to the size of the population.</p>
                  <p>(PDF)</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="pone.0214945.s001.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0214945.s002">
                <label>S2 Table</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Summary table of additional sensitivity regression analyses.</title>
                  <p>Summary table of regression analyses for <italic>Verbal</italic> excluding data from databases used by Weber et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and Bonsang et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and for <italic>Verbal</italic> only containing data used by Weber et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and Bonsang et al. [<xref rid="pone.0214945.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. (*) p &lt; .10; * <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05; ** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; *** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
                  <p>(PDF)</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="pone.0214945.s002.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0214945.s003">
                <label>S1 References</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>References of studies included in the analyses.</title>
                  <p>(PDF)</p>
                </caption>
                <media xlink:href="pone.0214945.s003.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>This research was supported by grants awarded to AH by the Swedish Research Council and the Swedish Council for Working Life and Social Research (FORTE). The large amount of data in this study was made available through work by Emelie von Vogelsang Antonsson, Hannes Bäckman, Erik Grimsby, Nadja Högman, Linnea Jesinkey, Maria Larsson, Catharina Lewin, Hillevi Johansson Lignell, Severin Lindskog, Tone Nordling, Christian Plahn, Jonas Rafi, Jenny Rehnman, Markus Söderqvist, and Marielouice Wänseth.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref001">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>. <article-title>The new science of cognitive sex differences</article-title>. <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2013.10.011</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24246136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24246136</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref002">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gender differences in verbal ability</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref003">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guiso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sapienza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zingales</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Diversity. Culture, gender, and math</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>320</volume>(<issue>5880</issue>):<fpage>1164</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. Epub 2008/05/31. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1154094</pub-id> .<?supplied-pmid 18511674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18511674</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref004">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Herlitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rehnman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sex differences in episodic memory</article-title>. <source>Current Directions in Psychological Science</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref005">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Asperholm</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nadja</surname></name>; <name><surname>Rafi</surname><given-names>Jonas</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Herlitz</surname><given-names>Agneta</given-names></name>. <article-title>What did you do yesterday?</article-title><source>A meta-analysis of sex differences in episodic memory</source>. <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref006">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Voyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryden</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Magnitude of sex differences in spatial abilities: a meta-analysis and consideration of critical variables</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7724690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7724690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref007">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Voyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Time limits and gender differences on paper-and-pencil tests of mental rotation: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref008">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Else-Quest</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cross-national patterns of gender differences in mathematics: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0018053</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20063928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20063928</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref009">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guiso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sapienza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zingales</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Diversity. Culture, gender, and math</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>320</volume>(<issue>5880</issue>):<fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref010">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skirbekk</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freund</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herlitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The changing face of cognitive gender differences in Europe</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>32</issue>):<fpage>11673</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref011">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stoet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geary</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Gender-Equality Paradox in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics Education</article-title>. <source>Psychol Sci</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. Epub 2018/02/15. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0956797617741719</pub-id> .<?supplied-pmid 29442575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29442575</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref012">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lippa</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collaer</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sex differences in mental rotation and line angle judgments are positively associated with gender equality and economic development across 53 nations</article-title>. <source>Arch Sex Behav</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>990</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. Epub 2009/01/09. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10508-008-9460-8</pub-id> .<?supplied-pmid 19130205?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19130205</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref013">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Herlitz</surname><given-names>A, Z K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gender differences and similarities in cognitive functions in Bangladesh and Sweden</article-title>. <source>International Psychogeriatrics</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>–.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref014">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hogervorst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rahardjo</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jolles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brayne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gender differences in verbal learning in older participants</article-title>. <source>Aging Health</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref015">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Furlong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cartmel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <source>Young People and Social Change</source>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref016">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Inglehart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modernization, Cultural Change, and the Persistence of Traditional Values</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref017">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overview of the Flynn effect</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>753</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref018">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pietschnig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voracek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>One Century of Global IQ Gains: A Formal Meta-Analysis of the Flynn Effect</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on Psychological Sciences</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref019">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dekhtyar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herlitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Flynn effect in Europe–Effects of sex and region</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref020">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Else-Quest</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Political Is Personal: Measurement and Application of Nation-Level Indicators of Gender Equity in Psychological Research</article-title>. <source>Psychology of Women Quarterly</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref021">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Economic Forum. The Global Gender Gap Report. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.weforum.org/reports/the-global-gender-gap-report-2017">https://www.weforum.org/reports/the-global-gender-gap-report-2017</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref022">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stoet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geary</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sex differences in mathematics and reading achievement are inversely related: within- and across-nation assessment of 10 years of PISA data</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e57988</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0057988</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23516422?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23516422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref023">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reimers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The BBC internet study: general methodology</article-title>. <source>Arch Sex Behav</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. Epub 2007/03/24. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10508-006-9143-2</pub-id> .<?supplied-pmid 17380377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17380377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref024">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gender, culture, and sex-typed cognitive abilities</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e39904</fpage> Epub 2012/07/19. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0039904</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22808072?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22808072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref025">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonsang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skirbekk</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Staudinger</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name>. <article-title>As You Sow, So Shall You Reap: Gender-Role Attitudes and Late-Life Cognition</article-title>. <source>Psychol Sci</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1201</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. Epub 2017/07/25. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0956797617708634</pub-id> .<?supplied-pmid 28737096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28737096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref026">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The World Bank. DataBank. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://databank.worldbank.org/data/home.aspx">http://databank.worldbank.org/data/home.aspx</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref027">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations Development Programme. Human Development Reports. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdr.undp.org/en/data">http://hdr.undp.org/en/data</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref028">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Viechtbauer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Conducting meta-analyses in R with the metafor package</article-title>. <source>Journal of Statistical Software</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref029">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lager</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seblova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Falkstedt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lovden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cognitive and emotional outcomes after prolonged education: a quasi-experiment on 320 182 Swedish boys</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. Epub 2016/06/04. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyw093</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27255438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27255438</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref030">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brinch</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Schooling in adolescence raises IQ scores</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. Epub 2011/12/29. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1106077109</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22203952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22203952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="pone.0214945.ref031">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Borenstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JPT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>. <source>Introduction to meta-analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Chichester, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sonds Ltd.</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
