<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-07T13:02:47Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7797247" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7797247</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-21</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rmdopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">RMD Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">RMD Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">rmdopen</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rmdopen</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>RMD Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2056-5933</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7797247</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7797247</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7797247</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33414179</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33414179</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">rmdopen-2020-001379</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rmdopen-2020-001379</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Rheumatoid Arthritis</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
                  <subject>1506</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <series-title>Original research</series-title>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Effects of alcohol consumption and smoking on risk for RA: results from a Swedish prospective cohort study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib id="author-80087877" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8225-3794</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hedenstierna</surname>
                    <given-names>Louise</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-80089751" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bellocco</surname>
                    <given-names>Rino</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-80089785" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ye</surname>
                    <given-names>Weimin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-80089866" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Adami</surname>
                    <given-names>Hans-Olov</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-80089698" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
                    <given-names>Torbjörn</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-80089912" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Trolle Lagerros</surname>
                    <given-names>Ylva</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-54983840" contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6612-4749</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hedström</surname>
                    <given-names>Anna Karin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Medicine, Solna</institution>, <institution>Karolinska Institutet</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Stockholm</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Center of Rheumatology, Academic Specialist Center</institution>, <institution>Stockholm Health Services</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Stockholm</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Medical Epidemiology and Biostatistics</institution>, <institution>Karolinska Institutet</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Stockholm</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Statistics and Quantitative Methods</institution>, <institution>University of Milano-Bicocca</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Milan</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution content-type="department">Clinical Effectiveness Group, Institute of Health and Society</institution>, <institution>University of Oslo</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Oslo</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Clinical Neuroscience</institution>, <institution>Karolinska Institutet</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Stockholm</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution content-type="department">Stress Research, Stockholm University</institution>, <institution>Stockholm University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Stockholm</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution content-type="department">Clinical Epidemiology Division, Department of Medicine, Solna</institution>, <institution>Karolinska Institutet</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Stockholm</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><institution content-type="department">Center for Obesity, Academic Specialst Center</institution>, <institution>Stockholm Health Services</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Stockholm</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Louise Hedenstierna; <email>louise.hedenstierna@ki.se</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>7</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>7</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <elocation-id>e001379</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>22</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>10</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2021. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <ali:license_ref start_date="2021-01-06">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="rmdopen-2020-001379.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>Several, but not all studies, have shown a dose-dependent inverse association with alcohol consumption and rheumatoid arthritis (RA), whereas smoking is an established risk factor for RA. We aimed to study the association between alcohol consumption and RA incidence and investigate a potential interaction between alcohol and smoking habits, regarding RA incidence.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>We used a prospective cohort study, based on 41 068 participants with detailed assessment of alcohol intake, smoking and potential confounders at baseline in 1997. We ascertained a total of 577 incident cases of RA during a mean of 17.7 years of follow-up through linkage to nationwide and essentially complete databases. Multivariate Cox proportional hazards models were used to estimate HR with 95% CI. Interaction on the additive scale between alcohol and smoking was estimated by calculating the attributable proportion due to interaction (AP).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Overall, alcohol consumption was associated with a 30% reduced incidence of RA (HR 0.69, 95% CI 0.55 to 0.86) with a dose–response relationship (p value for trend &lt;0.001) which remained significant after stratification by age and smoking habits. The positive association between smoking and RA incidence was reduced with increasing alcohol consumption (p value for trend &lt;0.001). A synergistic effect was observed between alcohol and smoking (AP 0.40, 95% CI 0.15 to 0.64), indicating that 40% of the cases among the double exposed are due to the interaction per se.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Our findings suggest an inverse association between alcohol consumption and RA incidence, and a synergistic effect between alcohol and smoking.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>arthritis</kwd>
                <kwd>rheumatoid</kwd>
                <kwd>epidemiology</kwd>
                <kwd>arthritis</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group id="funding-1">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100006636</institution-id>
                      <institution>Forskningsrådet om Hälsa, Arbetsliv och Välfärd</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group id="funding-2">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004348</institution-id>
                      <institution>Stockholms Läns Landsting</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>special-feature</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>unlocked</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
              <caption>
                <title>Key messages</title>
              </caption>
              <sec>
                <title>What is already known about this subject?</title>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Previous studies indicate that moderate intake of alcohol is protective against developing rheumatoid arthritis (RA).</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>What does this study add?</title>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>In a large prospective cohort study, we replicate findings of an inverse association between alcohol consumption and RA risk following extensive adjustment for confounders.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>In addition, we show a synergistic effect between alcohol drinking and smoking with a substantial attenuation of the protective effect of alcohol among smokers.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>How might this impact on clinical practice?</title>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Further studies in order to increase the understanding of the underlying mechanisms behind our findings may contribute to define new ways to achieve protection against RA.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
            </boxed-text>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Rheumatoid arthritis (RA), a chronic inflammatory disease characterised by progressive joint damage and sometimes multisystem involvement, develops through interplay between genetic loci and environmental factors.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Alcohol consumption dose-dependently affects both innate and adaptive aspects of the immune system.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2 3</xref> However, the impact of alcohol consumption on RA risk remains poorly understood. Several studies have indicated an inverse relationship between alcohol consumption and RA risk,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4–7</xref> although results have not been consistent.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8 9</xref></p>
              <p>Smoking, the main environmental risk factor, is estimated to account for approximately 20% of the environmental risk for RA.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Because smoking is positively correlated with alcohol intake, these two risk factors are mutual confounders in studies of RA. As a corollary, a large case-control study showed a greater alcohol-related relative risk reduction among ever smokers than among never smokers.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> In a prospective cohort study, the increased risk of RA associated with smoking was reduced among alcohol consumers.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p>
              <p>However, there is still a paucity of prospective studies with enough statistical power to analyse effects of various amounts of alcohol intake with concurrent data on cigarette smoking and their possible interaction. Therefore, we have used a large prospective cohort to investigate the joint effects and potential interaction between alcohol-drinking and smoking in relation to RA risk.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>The study is based on the Swedish National March Cohort, a prospective cohort study with nearly 42 000 participants.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The study was established in September 1997 during a nationwide fundraising event for cancer research. During the event, participants were asked to fill in a 36 pages questionnaire for epidemiological research, and in total 43 863 persons volunteered. Due to the nature of the recruitment process, the number of individuals offered the questionnaire could not be assessed. The questionnaire provided information about demographics, lifestyle factors and medical information. Participants also provided their individually unique national registration number, assigned to all Swedish residents. This number enables follow-up through linkage to multiple nationwide, continuously updated registers including medical information.</p>
              <p>Individuals with incorrect national registration number were excluded (n=11), as were those who were younger than 18 years (n=1732) or had emigrated or died (n=55) before the start of follow-up. We also excluded subjects with a diagnosis of RA at baseline, defined as ICD-code M05-M06; diagnoses were obtained from the Swedish National Patient Registers. A previous validation of the accuracy of the diagnoses in the National Patient registers indicates that 90% of the registered patients, diagnosed with RA, fulfil either the ACR 1987 or the ACR/EULAR 2010 diagnostic criteria for RA.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Subsequently, individuals with incomplete information on alcohol use or smoking habits were excluded and the final study cohort included 41 068 individuals. We used record linkages (based on the national registration numbers) to nationwide, essentially complete and continuously updated health databases to calculate person-years and ascertain incident cases of RA. Participants were followed from baseline 1 October 1997, until diagnosis of RA (defined as above), death, emigration or 31 December 2016, whichever occurred first.</p>
              <p>Detailed information regarding alcohol consumption was obtained, which allowed quantification of the average alcohol intake in gram per week. Subjects were categorised into the following groups based on the sex-specific distribution of alcohol intake in gram per week: non-drinkers, low consumption (below or equal to the median), moderate consumption (above the median, but below or equal to the 75th percentile) and high consumption (above the 75th percentile). Low alcohol consumption was defined as &lt;30 g/week among women and &lt;51 g/week among men; moderate alcohol consumption as 30–65 g/week among women and 51–104 g/week among men and high alcohol consumption as &gt;65 g/week among women and &gt;104 g/week among men. Smoking was dichotomised into never or ever smokers.</p>
              <p>Information on confounding variables including sex, educational level,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> body mass index,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> physical activity,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> coffee consumption<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and cardiovascular disease were obtained from the questionnaire. Education was summarised into a binary variable, based on having reached a university degree. Body mass index was calculated by dividing weight in kilograms by height in metres squared and categorised into underweight (&lt;18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), normal weight (18.5–24.99 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), overweight (25–30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) or obese (&gt;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>). Estimates of physical activity were based on reported responses on weekly exercise levels ranging from none or light physical activity to vigorous physical activity and dichotomised into those active (more than 120 min/week) or inactive (120 min or less/week). Coffee consumption was categorised into 0, 1–4, 5–7 or &gt;7 cups of coffee per day. Information regarding diagnoses of cardiovascular disease (ICD-10 codes I00-I99) at baseline was obtained from the Swedish Patient Register and dichotomised into those who had a previous cardiovascular diagnosis and those who had not.</p>
              <sec id="s2-1">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Differences in baseline variables across categories of alcohol consumption were assessed using one-way analysis of variance or the Kruskal-Wallis test for continuous variables and χ² test for categorical variables. A Cox proportional hazards model with attained age as time-scale was used to estimate HR of developing RA with 95% CI among subjects with different alcohol consumption habits at baseline, compared with non-drinkers. The analysis was stratified by age (&lt;60 years or <underline>&gt;</underline>60 years at baseline) and smoking habits (ever or never smoking). We assessed the proportionality hazard assumption, based on the Schoenfeld residual plots and statistical tests, and found no indication of violation for any covariate. We analysed the dose–response relationship between alcohol consumption and RA incidence by using a categorical variable for the amount of alcohol consumed per week (non-drinkers, low, moderate or high alcohol consumers as defined above) in a Cox proportional hazards model.</p>
                <p>A potential interaction between alcohol and smoking was analysed using departure of additivity of effects as criterion of interaction and quantified by calculating the attributable proportion due to interaction (AP) with 95% CI. AP is the proportion of the incidence among individuals exposed to two interacting factors that is attributable to the interaction per se; thus, an AP greater than 0 indicates presence of interaction. When conducting the analyses of interaction, alcohol intake was recoded as a risk factor.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p>
                <p>The full Cox model was adjusted for potential confounding variables including sex, educational level,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> body mass index,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> physical activity,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> coffee consumption<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and cardiovascular disease. When appropriate, adjustment was also made for smoking.</p>
                <p>We also performed analyses to study the association between low and moderate/high intake of alcohol and RA incidence (ie, non-drinkers were excluded). Similarly, we studied the potential interaction between low alcohol consumption and smoking with regard to RA risk, with moderate/high consumers of alcohol who did not smoke as the reference group.</p>
                <p>The proportion of missing data in the potential confounding variables was 4.4% for body mass index, 1.7% for coffee consumption and less than 1% for educational status, physical activity and alcohol consumption. We conducted supplementary analyses after imputing missing data using the multiple imputation chained equation procedure. We also performed a sensitivity analysis in which we excluded participants who developed RA within 5 years after baseline, when preclinical health could influence lifestyle habits. In another sensitivity analysis, we excluded current smokers.</p>
                <p>A larger dataset than ours would be needed in order to perform the analyses stratified by gender. The majority of the cases were women, which was expected since RA is more common among women. However, when the analyses were restricted to women the results remained similar. All analyses were performed using Statistical Analysis System (SAS) 9.4.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Our analyses on alcohol consumption and RA incidence included 41 068 participants. Characteristics of participants at baseline, overall and by alcohol consumption habits, are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. Generally, alcohol consumers were younger and had a higher educational level than non-drinkers. They more often reported shift work and slightly shorter habitual sleep duration. Alcohol consumption and smoking were highly correlated (p&lt;0.001).</p>
              <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Baseline characteristics, overall and by alcohol consumption habits</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1"> Variable</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">P value</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 068</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5475</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 761</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9035</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8797</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age (SD)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5 (15.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.4 (17.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.6 (15.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.2 (14.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8 (15.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 613 (65)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3839 (70)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 353 (64)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5833 (65)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5588 (64)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">University degree, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 497 (28)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1086 (20)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4401 (25)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2904 (32)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3106 (35)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ever smokers, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 437 (40)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1040 (19)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6566 (37)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4130 (46)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4701 (53)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup> (SD)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6 (3.5)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9 (3.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7 (3.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5 (3.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4 (3.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low physical activity, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6320 (15)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">784 (14)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2631 (15)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1380 (15)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1525 (17)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration, hours/night (SD)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (1.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (1.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (1.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (1.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (1.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shift work, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2315 (5.6)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (4.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1065 (6.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">518 (5.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">501 (5.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease, n (%)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4539 (11)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">822 (15)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2109 (12)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">871 (10)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">737 (8.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="T1_FN1">
                    <p>Differences in baseline variables across categories of alcohol consumption were assessed using one-way ANOVA or Kruskal-Wallis test for continuous variables and χ² test for categorical variables. Alcohol consumption was categorised into low consumption (&lt;30 g/week among women and &lt;51 g/week among men), moderate consumption (30–65 g/week among women and 51–104 g/week among men) and high consumption (&gt;65 g/week among women and &gt;104 g/week among men).</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T1_FN2">
                    <p>ANOVA, analysis of variance; BMI, body mass index.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>During a mean follow-up time of 17.7 years (median 18 years), 577 participants were diagnosed with RA. The average age at the time of RA diagnosis was 66.8 years (SD 12.8).</p>
              <p>Overall, alcohol consumption was associated with a 30% reduced incidence of RA (HR 0.69, 95% CI 0.55 to 0.86) with an inverse dose–response relationship between weekly amount of alcohol consumption and RA incidence (p value for trend &lt;0.001, <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). After stratification by age (&lt;60 years and <underline>&gt;</underline>60 years at baseline), estimates remained similar in both groups (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). Among drinkers, 89% reported intake of more than one type of alcoholic beverage. While 9.9% reported exclusively intake of other alcoholic beverages than wine, 6.9% reported exclusively intake of wine. There was no significant difference between those who exclusively drank wine (HR 0.66, 95% CI 0.45 to 0.96) or other types of alcoholic beverages than wine (HR 0.69, 95% CI 0.56 to 0.86).</p>
              <table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>HR with 95% CI of developing RA among subjects with different alcohol consumption habits</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Person years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incident RA (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)*</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)†</td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5475</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 922</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (1.9)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 761</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311 888</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262 (1.5)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.65–1.03)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.76 (0.60–0.96</bold>)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9035</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 535</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (1.3)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.72 (0.55–0.95</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.65 (0.49–0.86</bold>)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8797</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 250</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (1.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.62 (0.47–0.83</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.54 (0.41–0.73</bold>)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend &lt;0.001</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="T2_FN1">
                    <p>Significant HRs are in bold.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T2_FN2">
                    <p>Low alcohol consumption (&lt;30 g/week among women and &lt;51 g/week among men); moderate alcohol consumption (30–65 g/week among women and 51–104 g/week among men); high alcohol consumption (&gt;65 g/week among women and &gt;104 g/week among men).</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T2_FN3">
                    <p>*Adjusted for gender.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T2_FN4">
                    <p>†Adjusted for gender, educational status, smoking, body mass index, physical activity and cardiovascular disease.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T2_FN5">
                    <p>RA, rheumatoid arthritis.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>HR with 95% CI of developing RA among subjects with different alcohol consumption habits, stratified by age and smoking habits</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age &lt;60 years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age <underline>&gt;</underline>60 years</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Person years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incident RA (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)*</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Person years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incident RA (%)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)*</td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2717</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 994</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (1.9)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2758</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 928</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (1.9)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 147</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207 777</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (1.3)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.72 (0.52–0.99</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6614</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 112</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (1.7)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.55–1.04)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6501</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 636</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (1.2)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.63 (0.44–0.91</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2534</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 890</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (1.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.66 (0.44–0.99</bold>)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6816</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 736</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (1.0)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.53 (0.36–0.77</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1981</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 514</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (1.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.55 (0.35–0.87</bold>)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend 0.01</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend 0.02</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Alcohol consumption</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Ever smokers</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Never smokers</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>N</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Person years</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Incident RA (%)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>HR (95% CI)†</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>N</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Person years</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Incident RA (%)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>HR (95% CI)†</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1040</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 920</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (3.4)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4435</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 002</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (1.5)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6566</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 202</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129 (2.0)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.60 (0.41–0.88</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 195</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 686</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (1.2)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.60–1.09)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4130</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 387</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (1.6)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.49 (0.32–0.73</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4905</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 149</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (1.0)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.49–1.03)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4701</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 869</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (1.2)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.38 (0.25–0.58</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4096</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 381</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (0.9)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.67 (0.44–0.99</bold>)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend 0.001</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend 0.03</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="T3_FN1">
                    <p>Significant HRs are in bold.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T3_FN2">
                    <p>Low alcohol consumption (&lt;30 g/week among women and &lt;51 g/week among men); moderate alcohol consumption (30–65 g/week among women and 51–104 g/week among men); high alcohol consumption (&gt;65 g/week among women and &gt;104 g/week among men).</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T3_FN3">
                    <p>*Adjusted for gender, educational status, smoking, body mass index, physical activity and cardiovascular disease.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T3_FN4">
                    <p>†Adjusted for gender, educational status, body mass index, physical activity and cardiovascular disease.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T3_FN5">
                    <p>RA, rheumatoid arthritis.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The impact of alcohol on RA incidence was more pronounced among ever smokers than among never smokers, although the inverse correlation between amount of alcohol consumption and RA incidence remained statistically significant also among never smokers (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). Smoking increased RA incidence with a HR of 2.80 (95% CI 1.96 to 4.01) among non-drinkers, whereas the corresponding HR was 1.45 (95% CI 1.21 to 1.74) among alcohol consumers.</p>
              <p>With regard to RA incidence, we found a significant interaction on the additive scale between alcohol and smoking (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">table 4</xref>). The AP was 0.40 (95% CI 0.15 to 0.64), indicating that the combined effect was 40% higher than the sum of the individual effects or equivalently, that 40% of the cases among the double exposed are due to the interaction per se. The result remained similar when participants who had developed RA during the first 5 years after baseline were excluded (AP 0.40, 95% CI 0.13 to 0.67). The interaction between smoking and alcohol also remained similar when the analysis was restricted to include past smokers (AP 0.44, 95% 0.16 to 0.72).</p>
              <table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 4</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>HR with 95% CI of developing RA among subjects with different combinations of alcohol consumption and smoking</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ever smoking</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Person years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incident RA</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)*</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)†</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP (95% CI)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 196</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363 215</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220 (1.1)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4435</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 002</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (1.5)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (0.97–1.68)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.95–1.64)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 397</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">271 459</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">254 (1.7)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.49 (1.24–1.79</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.45 (1.21–1.74</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1040</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 920</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (3.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.03 (2.12–4.33</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.80 (1.96–4.01</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.40 (0.15–0.64</bold>)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="T4_FN1">
                    <p>Significant HRs are in bold.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T4_FN2">
                    <p>*Adjusted for gender.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T4_FN3">
                    <p>†Adjusted for gender, educational status, body mass index, physical activity and cardiovascular disease</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T4_FN4">
                    <p>AP, attributable proportion due to interaction; RA, rheumatoid arthritis.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>Overall, high alcohol consumption versus low alcohol consumption rendered an HR of 0.71 (95% CI 0.56 to 0.91). The inverse dose–response relationship between the amount of alcohol consumption and RA incidence remained significant when non-drinkers were excluded (p value for trend &lt;0.001). An interaction was observed between low alcohol consumption and smoking with regard to RA risk (AP 0.22, 95% CI 0.02 to 0.52) (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">table 5</xref>). Our results remained almost identical following multiple imputed data (data not shown).</p>
              <table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table 5</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>HR with 95% CI of developing RA among drinkers with different combinations of weekly alcohol consumption and smoking</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ever smoking</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Person years</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incident RA</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)*</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)†</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP (95% CI)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate-high</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9001</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 529</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (1.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (reference)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 195</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 686</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (1.2)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.87–1.50)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.84–1.45)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate-high</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8831</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 256</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (1.4)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.37 (1.04–1.80</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.32 (1.00–1.74</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6566</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 202</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129 (2.0)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.94 (1.48–2.55</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.81 (1.37–2.38</bold>)</td>
                      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.22 (0.02–0.52</bold>)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="T5_FN1">
                    <p>Significant HRs are in bold.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T5_FN2">
                    <p>*Adjusted for gender.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T5_FN3">
                    <p>†Adjusted for gender, educational status, body mass index, physical activity and cardiovascular disease.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="T5_FN4">
                    <p>AP, attributable proportion due to interaction; RA, rheumatoid arthritis.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Our results confirm an inverse dose–response relationship between alcohol consumption and RA incidence as well as a positive association with smoking. The risk reduction associated with alcohol consumption was more pronounced among smokers. In addition, alcohol acted synergistically with smoking to increase RA incidence.</p>
              <p>When we analysed the association between alcohol and RA incidence, non-drinkers were used as the reference category in the main analyses. Because concerns have been raised regarding the possibility of uncontrolled or residual confounding when drinkers are compared with non-drinkers in observational studies,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20 21</xref> we also performed analyses restricted to drinkers. However, our findings of an inverse dose–response relationship between the amount of alcohol consumption and RA incidence, as well as the synergistic effect between alcohol consumption and smoking remained significant also when non-drinkers were excluded.</p>
              <p>No universally accepted classification system exists for low, moderate and high alcohol consumption. Our classification was based on the gender-specific distribution of alcohol at baseline. High alcohol consumption in our study (more than 66 g/week among women or 105 g/week among men) is indeed considered moderate by Statistics Sweden.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Relatively few participants in our study reported alcohol intake over the recommended level. We also examined other ways to classify alcohol exposure. However, using the same classification based on the distribution among all participants together, or applying the classification that is used by Statistics Sweden, only marginally changed our results. Several autoimmune diseases have been inversely associated with alcohol consumption, such as systemic lupus erythematosus,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> autoimmune thyroid diseases,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24 25</xref> type 1 diabetes mellitus<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> and multiple sclerosis.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> An interaction between drinking and smoking, similar to the one we found for RA, has been observed with regard to risk of multiple sclerosis,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> another complex Th1 driven inflammatory disease.</p>
              <p>Alcohol intake dose-dependently affects innate and adaptive aspects of the immune system.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2 3</xref> Previous studies have shown an alcohol induced alteration in cytokine production, where low to moderate alcohol consumption is associated with decreased production of pro-inflammatory cytokines such as IL-1, IL-6 and TNF.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2 3 28 29</xref> A recently published in vivo study on mice suggested that one mechanism might involve altered function of T-follicular helper cells (T-<sub>FH</sub> cells), leading to impaired antibody formation.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Alcohol-induced epigenetic changes, resulting in altered gene expression, may also affect immune homeostasis.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> However, the specific molecular mechanisms underlying ethanol’s impact on RA incidence remain poorly understood; knowledge concerning the molecular mechanisms underlying the specific interaction presented in this study is also limited.</p>
              <p>Strengths of this study include its prospective design, large sample size with long-term virtually complete follow-up through linkage to nationwide Swedish registers. Further, the study was performed in the context of the Swedish welfare system with equal access to medical services for all citizens. A possible limitation is the way the recruitment to the study was done, where the volunteers in the study might be healthier than the average population (a healthy volunteer bias). This might explain why the reported alcohol consumption was somewhat lower than expected. However, since many population-based studies struggle with low response rate and incomplete follow-up, the disadvantage of a non-representative sample must be weighed against the increased feasibility of the study, and the completeness of the answers with a remarkably low level of missing data. Although under-reporting alcohol consumption is possible, there is no reason to believe that participants who later developed RA would under-report alcohol to a greater extent. Therefore, differential misclassification of alcohol, as well as smoking, seems unlikely. Since few participants reported high alcohol consumption, according to the classification that is used by Statistics Sweden, we were not able to further analyse whether the inverse dose–response relationship was interrupted at a certain level of alcohol intake, which has been demonstrated previously.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4 11</xref></p>
              <p>Information on smoking habits, alcohol consumption as well as confounders was collected only at study baseline and might have changed during the follow-up. Such misclassification would usually be non-differential and entail attenuation of our risk estimates.</p>
              <p>Despite a large number of participants in the cohort, the prevalence of current smokers at baseline was too low for informative analyses by a more detailed characterisation of smoking history. However, when current smokers were excluded, the interaction between smoking and alcohol remained similar. This was expected, since the influence of smoking on RA risk persists during decades after smoking cessation.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> In turn, this indicates that there is a prolonged state of autoimmunity that proceeds the symptom onset in RA<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> and lifestyle habits probably influence the risk of disease long before the clinical onset.</p>
              <p>In conclusion, our findings suggest that alcohol consumption is inversely associated with RA incidence, which is in accordance with previous studies. A synergistic effect was observed between drinking and smoking with regard to RA incidence. Further studies are needed to understand the mechanisms behind the findings which may contribute to define ways to achieve protection against RA by other means than alcohol consumption.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>We want to thank all participants in the Swedish National March Cohort for their valuable contribution. We also thank Saedis Saevarsdottir, Lars Klareskog and Lars Alfredsson for contributing with valuable insights in the specific area and fruitful discussions in the process of forming the manuscript.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Contributors:</bold> AKH: study concept and design, statistical analysis. LH and AKH: drafting of the manuscript. RB and WY: data extraction. WY, RB, YTL, TÅ and H-OA: interpretation of data and critical revision of manuscript. All authors approved the final version of the manuscript to be published.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> LH was supported by research funding from Academic Specialist Center and a clinical research fund from Stockholm county (ALF-funding). AKH was supported by funding from the Swedish Research Council for health, working life and welfare.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not required.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> The study was approved by the Regional Ethics Committee in Stockholm and all participants provided written informed consent.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Data availability statement:</bold> Data are available on reasonable request. Please contact corresponding author at louise.hedenstierna@ki.se.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klareskog</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malmström</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Smoking, citrullination and genetic variability in the immunopathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Semin Immunol</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smim.2011.01.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21376627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21376627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Opposing effects of alcohol on the immune system</article-title>. <source>Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pnpbp.2015.09.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26375241?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26375241</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wärnberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Moderate alcohol consumption and the immune system: a review</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>98 Suppl 1</volume>:<fpage>S111</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114507838049</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17922947?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17922947</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaccardelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedlander</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Potential of lifestyle changes for reducing the risk of developing rheumatoid arthritis: is an ounce of prevention worth a pound of cure?</article-title><source>Clin Ther</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2019.04.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/31196646?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31196646</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Källberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption is associated with decreased risk of rheumatoid arthritis: results from two Scandinavian case-control studies</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>222</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.2007.086314</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18535114?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18535114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gowers</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption is inversely associated with risk and severity of rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>2140</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/keq202</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20667949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20667949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costenbader</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption and risk of incident rheumatoid arthritis in women: a prospective study</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheumatol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1998</fpage>–<lpage>2005</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.38634</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24729427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24729427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerhan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saag</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Criswell</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Blood transfusion, alcohol use, and anthropometric risk factors for rheumatoid arthritis in older women</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11838841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11838841</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez</surname><given-names>LAG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tolosa</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruigómez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Rheumatoid arthritis in UK primary care: incidence and prior morbidity</article-title>. <source>Scand J Rheumatol</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03009740802448825</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19117247?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19117247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klareskog</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregersen</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huizinga</surname><given-names>TWJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of autoimmune rheumatic disease: state of the art and future perspectives</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>2062</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.2010.142109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21097657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21097657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedström</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hössjer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klareskog</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Interplay between alcohol, smoking and HLA genes in RA aetiology</article-title>. <source>RMD Open</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<elocation-id>e 000893</elocation-id>:<fpage>e000893</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rmdopen-2019-000893</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/31168412?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giuseppe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bottai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Long term alcohol intake and risk of rheumatoid arthritis in women: a population based cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>345</volume>:<elocation-id>e4230</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.e4230</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22782847?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22782847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trolle Lagerros</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hantikainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mariosa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Cohort profile: the Swedish national March cohort</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>795e</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyw193</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27649800?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27649800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neovius</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Askling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Nationwide prevalence of rheumatoid arthritis and penetration of disease-modifying drugs in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>624</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.2010.133371</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21149495?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21149495</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nordmark</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klareskog</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic status and the risk of developing rheumatoid arthritis: results from the Swedish EIRA study</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1588</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.2004.031666</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15843455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15843455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Body mass index and the risk of rheumatoid arthritis: an updated dose-response meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res Int</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/3579081</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/31355257?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tedeschi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Long-Term physical activity and subsequent risk for rheumatoid arthritis among women: a prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheumatol</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1460</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.40899</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30920773?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30920773</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>S-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coffee or tea consumption and the risk of rheumatoid arthritis: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Clin Rheumatol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1575</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10067-014-2631-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24763752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24763752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knol</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>VanderWeele</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groenwold</surname><given-names>RHH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Estimating measures of interaction on an additive scale for preventive exposures</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10654-011-9554-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21344323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21344323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>To drink or not to drink?</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMe020163</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12519927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519927</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol and health: a drink a day won't keep the doctor away</article-title>. <source>Cleve Clin J Med</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>945</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3949/ccjm.70.11.945</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14650469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14650469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><article-title>Internet based information</article-title>. Available: <uri xlink:href="http://www.scb.se">http://www.scb.se</uri> [Accessed <comment>16 Nov, 2019</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Smoking history, alcohol consumption, and systemic lupus erythematosus: a case-control study</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.57.8.451</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9797548?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9797548</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlé</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Moderate alcohol consumption may protect against overt autoimmune hypothyroidism: a population-based case-control study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Endocrinol</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>167</volume>:<fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/EJE-12-0356</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22802427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22802427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlé</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bülow Pedersen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Graves′ hyperthyroidism and moderate alcohol consumption: evidence for disease prevention</article-title>. <source>Clin Endocrinol</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cen.12106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasouli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahlbom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption is associated with reduced risk of type 2 diabetes and autoimmune diabetes in adults: results from the Nord-Trøndelag health study</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1464-5491.2012.03713.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22612671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22612671</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedström</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hillert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Alcohol as a modifiable lifestyle factor affecting multiple sclerosis risk</article-title>. <source>JAMA Neurol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>300</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2013.5858</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24395432?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24395432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>I-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verdrengh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brisslert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Ethanol prevents development of destructive arthritis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0608620104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17185416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17185416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azizov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Ethanol consumption inhibits T<sub>FH</sub> cell responses and the development of autoimmune arthritis</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>1998</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-15855-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32332730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32332730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muralidharan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambade</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulham</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Moderate alcohol induces stress proteins HSF1 and Hsp70 and inhibits proinflammatory cytokines resulting in endotoxin tolerance</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>193</volume>:<fpage>1975</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1303468</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25024384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25024384</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandrekar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Moderate alcohol intake in humans attenuates monocyte inflammatory responses: inhibition of nuclear regulatory factor kappa B and induction of interleukin 10</article-title>. <source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1530-0277.2006.00012.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16433741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16433741</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strathdee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Relton</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of epigenetic alterations by dietary and other environmental factors</article-title>. <source>Adv Genet</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-380864-6.00001-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20933124?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20933124</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedström</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stawiarz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klareskog</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Smoking and susceptibility to rheumatoid arthritis in a Swedish population-based case-control study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10654-018-0360-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29387991?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29387991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rantapää-Dahlqvist</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What happens before the onset of rheumatoid arthritis?</article-title><source>Curr Opin Rheumatol</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BOR.0b013e32832a2e44</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19365265?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19365265</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
