<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-07T13:02:59Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7678333" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7678333</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-03</datestamp>
        <setSpec>sageopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Scand J Public Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Scand J Public Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJP</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsjp</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1403-4948</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1651-1905</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7678333</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7678333</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7678333</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32195635</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32195635</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1403494820911813</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1403494820911813</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Consequences of Sleep Disturbance</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Sleep disturbance and work-related mental strain: A national prospective cohort study of the prediction of subsequent long-term sickness absence, disability pension and mortality</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8049-8504</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
                    <given-names>Torbjörn</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1403494820911813"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mittendorfer-Rutz</surname>
                    <given-names>Ellenor</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4006-3327</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rahman</surname>
                    <given-names>Syed</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1-1403494820911813">Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institutet, Sweden</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="corresp1-1403494820911813">Torbjörn Åkerstedt, Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institutet, Frescati Hagväg 14A, 171 77 Stockholm, Sweden. E-mail: <email>torbjorn.akerstedt@ki.se</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>48</volume>
              <issue>8</issue>
              <fpage>888</fpage>
              <lpage>895</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>30</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder content-type="sage">Associations of Public Health in the Nordic Countries Regions</copyright-holder>
                <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits any use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <p><italic>Aims:</italic> Sleep disturbances and work-related mental strain are linked to increased sickness absence and disability pension (DP), but we have no information on synergy effects. The aim of this study was to examine the combined (and separate) association of the two predictors with subsequent long-term work disability and mortality. <italic>Methods:</italic> A total of 45,498 participants aged 16–64 years were interviewed in the Swedish Surveys of Living Conditions between 1997 and 2013, and were followed up on long-term sickness absence (LTSA; &gt;90 days/year), DP and mortality via national registers until 2016. Crude and multivariable Cox analyses were used to estimate hazard ratios (HR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI). <italic>Results:</italic> For LTSA, the HRs for sleep disturbances and work-related mental strain were 1.6 (95% CI 1.5–1.7) and 1.3 (95% CI 1.2–1.4), respectively. For DP, the HRs were 2.0 (95% CI 1.8–2.2) and 1.4 (95% CI 1.2–1.5). Mortality was only predicted by sleep disturbances (HR=1.2, 95% CI 1.1–1.4). No synergy effect was seen. <bold><italic>Conclusions:</italic> Work-related mental strain and, in particular, sleep disturbances were associated with a higher risk of subsequent LTSA and DP, but without synergy effects. Sleep disturbances were also associated with mortality. Exposure to interventions tackling sleep disturbance and prevention of workplace stress may reduce work disability.</bold></p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Work disability</kwd>
                <kwd>stress</kwd>
                <kwd>synergy</kwd>
                <kwd>death</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>typesetter</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>ts1</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-1403494820911813">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Stress is defined as physiological or mental activation/effort in response to demands [<xref rid="bibr1-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Stress at work is often seen as a response to work demands or to work strain. The latter is quantified as the ratio between work demands and work control [<xref rid="bibr2-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Work demands include items such as having to work fast, work hard, not having enough time or having to exert too much effort. This measure and particularly work strain are predictors of coronary heart disease [<xref rid="bibr3-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The present study focuses on a related concept: work-related mental strain.</p>
              <p>This concept has been used for more than 40 years in health surveys carried out by Statistics Sweden, but very little is known about its prospective association with health variables. However, there are indications that job strain predicts sickness absence (SA) [<xref rid="bibr5-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="bibr6-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr7-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The effect seems stronger in higher socio-economic groups [<xref rid="bibr8-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Disability pension (DP) is also linked to prior job strain [<xref rid="bibr9-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="bibr10-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr11-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], but the studies are few. With regard to work demands as a predictor of all-cause mortality such a link has been demonstrated in several studies [<xref rid="bibr12-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="bibr13-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr14-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], whereas other studies have failed to find such a link [<xref rid="bibr15-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="bibr16-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr17-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. No other studies seem to have focused on this outcome.</p>
              <p>In his early work on stress, Selye emphasised that ‘recovery’ was a prerequisite for preventing a gradual increase in activation in response to stress [<xref rid="bibr1-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Sleep is a major form of recovery, and sleep loss is frequently seen as a stressor [<xref rid="bibr18-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Moreover, disturbed or short sleep is prospectively related to metabolic disease such as diabetes [<xref rid="bibr19-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p>
              <p>Sleep disturbances predict increased SA [<xref rid="bibr20-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="bibr21-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and DP [<xref rid="bibr22-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="bibr23-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr24-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr25-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Sleep disturbances do not, however, seem to be related to mortality according to a recent meta-analysis [<xref rid="bibr26-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p>
              <p>Work-related mental strain and sleep disturbances are also prospectively linked to each other in a reciprocal way [<xref rid="bibr27-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–<xref rid="bibr28-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. While work-related mental stress may increase activation, resulting in disturbed sleep, the latter might reduce the capacity to handle demands and thus result in more strain. This raises the issue of the combined effects of disturbed sleep on work-related mental strain on LTSA, DP and mortality. We hypothesised that there may be synergy effects and that there is a possibility that good sleep buffers against the negative effects of stress.</p>
              <p>The purpose of the present study was to investigate the separate and combined associations of sleep disturbances and work-related mental strain with subsequent long-term sickness absence (LTSA), DP and mortality. To the best of our knowledge, no similar study has been carried out before.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="section2-1403494820911813">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="section3-1403494820911813">
                <title>Study population</title>
                <p>A cohort of 62,575 individuals aged 16–64 years at baseline who participated in the Swedish Surveys of Living Conditions between 1997 and 2013 were identified. Face-to-face interviews were conducted between 1997 and 2005, and telephone interviews between 2006 and 2013. After exclusion of non-responders to the questions on sleep and work-related mental strain (<italic>n</italic>=17,077), the study population included 45,498 individuals. In addition, those who died or emigrated (<italic>n</italic>=18) between the interview and the start of follow-up were also excluded, leaving a sample size of 45,480 participants. Further, a subsample that excluded persons on disability or age-related pension at baseline (<italic>n</italic>=2916) was created for analyses with LTSA (defined as &gt;90 net days of SA in one spell) or DP as the outcome. This research was carried out in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, and the study was approved by the Stockholm Regional Ethical Committee.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section4-1403494820911813">
                <title>Data sources</title>
                <p>Individual-level information on this cohort was linked by using the unique personal (de-identified) identification number from: (a) the national patient register and cause of death register held by the National Board of Health and Welfare (date and cause/diagnosis of inpatient and specialised outpatient care and date and cause of death, respectively); (b) the Micro Data for Analysis of the Social Insurance database held by the Social Insurance Agency which includes information on date, grade and diagnoses of SA and DP; and (c) the Longitudinal Integration Database for Health Insurance and Labour Market Studies held by Statistics Sweden which includes data on age, sex, country of birth, education level, family situation and type of living area.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section5-1403494820911813">
                <title>Exposure measures</title>
                <p>For exposure to sleep disturbances, individuals were asked: ‘Have you had trouble sleeping during the past two weeks?’ For work-related mental strain, the question was formulated as: ‘Is your work mentally straining?’ Note that the latter question was not time limited. They were measured once during the interview between 1997 and 2013. Up to 2007, the response options were only ‘yes/no’, but from 2008 onwards, participants could also answer ‘don’t know’ or ‘don’t want to answer’. Both the latter categories were categorised as non-response and were not included in any analyses.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section6-1403494820911813">
                <title>Outcome measures</title>
                <p>Work disability as an outcome was measured as (a) LTSA and (b) granting of DP. Measurement of LTSA and DP were performed separately. Net days were calculated based on the grade (full time and part time) and duration of SA during follow-up. Mortality as an outcome was considered as all-cause mortality during follow-up. The outcome variables were categorised as yes/no.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section7-1403494820911813">
                <title>Covariates</title>
                <p>Covariates (see categorisations in <xref rid="table1-1403494820911813" ref-type="table">Table I</xref>) included sociodemographic measures (sex, age, educational level, type of living area, country of birth, family situation), health-related factors (specialised health-care use, body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>), smoking), work-related factors (unemployment, job profile (2011–2013)) previous SA and interview method (with the categories telephone and face-to-face), and were measured at baseline.</p>
                <table-wrap id="table1-1403494820911813" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table I.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Characteristics of the participants of the main cohort of individuals with disturbed sleep, work-related mental strain and fatigue between 1997 and 2013 in Sweden (<italic>N</italic>=45,498).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <alternatives>
                    <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1403494820911813-table1"/>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                        <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      </colgroup>
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic>/%</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No disturbed sleep or strain, <italic>N</italic>=21,512</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both disturbed sleep and strain, <italic>N</italic>=5385</th>
                          <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <italic>p</italic>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sex</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,986/50.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,188/56.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2128/39.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,512/49.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9324/43.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3257/60.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Age</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 16–24</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5226/11.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2876/13.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">472/8.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 25–34</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,162/22.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4750/22.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1127/20.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 35–44</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,548/25.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5233/24.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1398/26.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45–54</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,163/24.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5082/23.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1458/27.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5564</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7426/16.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3571/16.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">930/17.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Education level</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0–9 years</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7243/15.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4142/19.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">661/12.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10–12 years</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,420/49.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,324/52.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2410/44.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;12 years</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,835/34.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6046/28.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2314/42.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Type of living area<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1403494820911813">a</xref></sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Large cities</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,338/35.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7352/34.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2174/40.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Medium cities</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,198/35.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7765/36.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1836/34.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rural areas</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,962/28.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6395/29.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1375/25.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Country of birth</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sweden</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40,614/89.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,415/90.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4624/85.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other Nordic countries</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1391/3.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">619/2.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205/3.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rest of the EU-25</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">905/2.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">364/1.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133/2.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rest of the world</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2588/5.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1114/5.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">423/2.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Family situation<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494820911813">b</xref></sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Married/cohabiting, no children</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6706/14.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3216/14.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">863/16.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single, no children</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009/41.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8852/41.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2147/39.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Married/cohabiting, with children</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,998/33.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7138/33.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,077/33.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single, with children</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2931/6.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1169/5.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">442/8.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Living with parents &lt;20 years</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1795/4.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1090/5.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124/2.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Missing</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59/0.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47/0.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/0.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Specialised health-care use</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-user</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,287/31.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6800/31.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1747/32.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Before start of follow-up</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,425/25.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5125/23.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1543/28.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> During the follow-up</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,786/43.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9587/44.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2095/38.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">BMI</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Under weight</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">634/1.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">288/1.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103/1.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0259</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal weight</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,799/54.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,762/54.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2893/53.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Overweight</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,471/34.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7431/34.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1798/33.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Obesity grade I</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3365/7.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1519/7.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">423/7.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Obesity grade II</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">551/1.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250/1.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68/1.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Obesity grade III</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113/0.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36/0.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/0.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Missing</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">565/1.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226/1.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75/0.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Daily smoker</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,877/83.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,127/84.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4330/80.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7621/16.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3385/15.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1054/19.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">LTSA</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No LTSA</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39,226/86.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,086/88.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4267/79.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Previous LTSA</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">790/1.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">277/1.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156/2.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ongoing LTSA</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">713/1.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/0.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/3.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LTSA during follow-up</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4769/10.5</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1950/9.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">763/14.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">DP</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No DP</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,794/91.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,185/93.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4622/85.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ongoing DP</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1494/3.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">518/2.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">317/5.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DP during follow-up</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2210/4.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">809/3.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">446/8.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Unemployment</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,007/90.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,132/89.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4906/91.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1–180 days</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3715/8.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1925/9.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408/7.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;180 days</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">717/1.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408/1.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69/1.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Death during follow-up<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1403494820911813">c</xref></sup></td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1701/3.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">825/3.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/4.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3613</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General anxiety/stress (yes)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7524/16.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1866/8.68</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2217/41.3</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disturbance</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9849/21.7</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work-related mental strain</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,513/42.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue (yes)</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,912/24.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6360/29.6</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3675/68.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Job profile<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1403494820911813">d</xref></sup></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White collar</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,022/56.8</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7072/49.0</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2631/66.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Blue collar</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6370/20.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3621/25.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">529/13.4</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Missing</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7359/20.1</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3741/25.9</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">801/20.2</td>
                          <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </alternatives>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="table-fn1-1403494820911813">
                      <label>a</label>
                      <p>Type of living area: big cities (Stockholm, Gothenburg and Malmö), medium-sized cities (cities with &gt;90,000 inhabitants within 30 km distance from the centre of the city) and small cities/villages.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="table-fn2-1403494820911813">
                      <label>b</label>
                      <p>Single=divorced/separated/widowed living with/without children.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="table-fn3-1403494820911813">
                      <label>c</label>
                      <p>12 died before follow-up.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="table-fn4-1403494820911813">
                      <label>d</label>
                      <p>Available since 2001.</p>
                    </fn>
                    <fn id="table-fn5-1403494820911813">
                      <p>BMI: body mass index; LTSA: long-term sickness absence; DP: disability pension.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec id="section8-1403494820911813">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Follow-up of participants began on 1 January following the interview year (between 1997 and 2013) and ended on 31 December 2016. Hazard ratios (HR) with 95% confidence intervals (CI) for mortality, LTSA and DP among the study population were estimated by Cox regression models after testing that the proportional hazard assumption was met. Individuals were followed until the date of LTSA, DP, death, emigration or the end of follow-up. Censoring was applied for death and emigration in case of an outcome other than death. Additionally, in the analyses for LTSA and DP as outcome, observations after turning 65 years of age (previous the mandatory retirement age) were censored. Moreover, in the analysis for LTSA as the outcome measure, censoring was applied for DP if granted during follow-up.</p>
                <p>In order to identify the synergistic effects between sleep disturbance and work-related mental strain with regard to subsequent LTSA, DP and mortality, the additive interaction between sleep disturbance and work-related mental strain at baseline with regard to subsequent LTSA, DP and mortality was measured by calculating the relative excess risk due to interaction (RERI) and the synergy index (S) [<xref rid="bibr29-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="section9-1403494820911813">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>The number of LTSAs during follow-up was 4769, and the number of DPs was 2210. Among the respondents, 21.6% reported sleep disturbances, and 42.9% were experiencing mental strain related to work (<xref rid="table1-1403494820911813" ref-type="table">Table I</xref>). Around 90% of the population did not have previous or ongoing work disability (i.e. LTSA or DP). During the follow-up period, 3.7% of the participants died, and 10.5% and 4.9% experienced LTSA and DP, respectively.</p>
              <p>A descriptive analysis of the excluded survey participants who did not respond or who responded ‘don’t know’ to the questions related to the exposure measures (data not shown) revealed that they were predominantly male (62% vs. 50.5% among the responders), younger (16–24 years: 26% vs. 20%) and with a lower educational level (0–9 years: 43% vs. 21%), and a substantially higher proportion belonged to the ‘rest of the world’ in relation to country of birth (24% vs. 8%). In parallel, a higher proportion of the non-responders died during follow-up (6% vs. 3.7%), a higher proportion of them were treated by specialised health-care provider before the start of follow-up (31% vs. 25.1%) and nearly one third of such non-responders were already on DP at inclusion (32% vs. 3.3%). In contrast, a lower proportion of the non-responders were on LTSA during follow-up compared to responders (4% vs. 10.5%, respectively).</p>
              <p>An association was observed between both exposure measures under study and LTSA in crude and adjusted models, but with higher HRs for sleep disturbances. We also observed similar associations with DP; the fully adjusted association for sleep disturbance with DP was stronger than that between work-related mental strain and DP (<xref rid="table2-1403494820911813" ref-type="table">Table II</xref>). For mortality, only sleep had a significant albeit modest association with mortality (<xref rid="table2-1403494820911813" ref-type="table">Table II</xref>). In sex-stratified analyses, the results were very similar in women and men (results not shown).</p>
              <table-wrap id="table2-1403494820911813" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table II.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Hazard ratios (HR) and 95% Confidence Intervals (CI) for long-term sickness absence (LTSA), disability pension (DP) and mortality. Individuals reporting sleep disturbances, or work-related mental strain.</p>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>
                  <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1403494820911813-table2"/>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sleep disturbances<hr/></th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Work-related mental strain<hr/></th>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1403494820911813">a</xref></sup></th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1403494820911813">b</xref></sup></th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1403494820911813">a</xref></sup></th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1403494820911813">b</xref></sup></th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="7" rowspan="1">LTSA (<italic>N</italic>=42,564)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,745 (79.3)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,229 (56.9)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8819 (20.7)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.7 (1.6–1.8)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.6 (1.5–1.7)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,335 (43.1)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.3 (1.2–1.3)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.3 (1.2-1.4)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="7" rowspan="1">DP (<italic>N</italic>=42,564)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,745 (79.3)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,229 (56.9)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8819 (20.7)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>2.1 (1.9–2.3)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>2.0 (1.8–2.2)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,335 (43.1)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.3 (1.2–1.4)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.3 (1.2–1.5)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Mortality (<italic>N</italic>=45,480)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35637 (78.4)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,970 (57.1)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9843 (21.6)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.2 (1.1–1.4)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.2 (1.1–1.4)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,510 (42.9)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.8–1.0)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.9–1.1)</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </alternatives>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="table-fn6-1403494820911813">
                    <p>Statistically significant values (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) are shown in bold. Individuals with ongoing DP (<italic>n</italic>=1235) or age-related pension (<italic>n</italic>=1423) or both (<italic>n</italic>=258) at start were excluded.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="table-fn7-1403494820911813">
                    <label>a</label>
                    <p>Crude model.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="table-fn8-1403494820911813">
                    <label>b</label>
                    <p>Adjusted for sex, age, educational level, type of living area, family situation, country of birth, previous health-care use, previous sickness absence, smoking status, BMI and unemployment benefit.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>In a sensitivity analysis, we also adjusted for work-related mental strain in the analysis of sleep disturbances, and vice versa. This did not change any of the estimates appreciably other than a minor reduction of the HR for LTSA and DP (not shown). For mortality, the HR for sleep disturbance was no longer significant when adjusted for work-related mental strain (HR=1.0, 95% CI=0.9–1.1).</p>
              <p>Synergistic effects between sleep disturbance and mental strain on LTSA, DP or mortality were not found. The RERI statistic was between 0.0 and 0.2, and the S statistic varied between 1 and 1.2 across the models, neither of which indicated statistical significance (data not shown). However, individuals experiencing both sleep disturbance and mental strain were at a significantly higher risk for LTSA and DP (<xref rid="table3-1403494820911813" ref-type="table">Table III</xref>) than those who reported only one of the exposures (compared to those who did not report any such exposures). Post-hoc power analyses (α=0.05 and 0.01) indicated 100% power for all three analyses of dependent variables.</p>
              <table-wrap id="table3-1403494820911813" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Table III.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Synergistic effect of sleep disturbances and work-related mental strain in relation to LTSA, DP and mortality.</p>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>
                  <graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1403494820911813-table3"/>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <colgroup span="1">
                      <col align="left" span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                      <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disturbance</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work-related mental strain</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-1403494820911813">a</xref></sup></th>
                        <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-1403494820911813">b</xref></sup></th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>LTSA</italic>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,303 (47.7)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3926 (9.2)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.7 (1.6–1.9)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.6 (1.5–1.7)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,442 (31.6)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.2 (1.1–1.3)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.3 (1.2–1.3)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4893 (11.5)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>2.0 (1.8–2.1)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.9 (1.8–2.1)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>DP</italic>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,303 (47.7)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3926 (9.2)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>2.1 (1.8–2.4)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>2.0 (1.7–2.3)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,442 (31.6)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.2 (1.1–1.3)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.3 (1.1–1.4)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4893 (11.5)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>2.3 (2.1–2.6)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>2.4 (2.2–2.7)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                          <italic>Mortality</italic>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,521 (47.3)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4458 (9.8)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.3 (1.1–1.5)</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.0–1.4)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,125 (31.1)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.8–0.9)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.9–1.1)</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5385 (11.8)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.0–1.4)</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>1.2 (1.1–1.4)</bold>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </alternatives>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="table-fn9-1403494820911813">
                    <p>Individuals with ongoing DP (<italic>n</italic>=1235) or age-related pension (<italic>n</italic>=1423) or both (<italic>n</italic>=258) at start were excluded. Statistically significant values (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) are shown in bold.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="table-fn10-1403494820911813">
                    <label>a</label>
                    <p>Crude model.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="table-fn11-1403494820911813">
                    <label>b</label>
                    <p>Adjusted for sex, age, educational level, type of living area, family situation, country of birth, previous health-care use, previous sickness absence, smoking status, BMI and unemployment benefit.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="section10-1403494820911813">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Sleep disturbances and work-related mental strain were significantly associated with higher risk of subsequent LTSA and DP. Mortality was weakly associated with sleep disturbances. No synergy effects were seen, but the two predictors combined yielded higher HRs for LTSA and DP than for either of them separately.</p>
              <p>The absence of synergy was unexpected in view of the clear associations with LTSA and DP of the two predictors separately. It may be the case that the association between sleep disturbances and work-related mental strain is too high to permit independent contributions. Still, the HR of the combined exposure to the two variables was higher than that of either of them alone. This should be followed up. Possibly, the effects might have been larger if the exposure had not been measured through a yes/no response alternative. More graded responses may have made possible a more optimal cut-off point with higher mental strain. This should be followed up in future studies.</p>
              <p>The significant association between sleep disturbances and long-term SA [<xref rid="bibr20-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–<xref rid="bibr21-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and DP [<xref rid="bibr22-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="bibr23-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr24-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr25-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] confirms previous work. One possible explanation for these findings may be that subjective health is reduced after disturbed sleep as it is after experimental sleep loss [<xref rid="bibr30-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. It should be noted that the sleep disturbances in the present study referred to the preceding two weeks only. A longer reference span may have yielded stronger results.</p>
              <p>The significant association between work-related mental strain and LTSA agrees with previous work with job strain as a predictor [<xref rid="bibr5-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="bibr6-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr7-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The present results on mental work strain and DP are also in line with studies of job strain and DP [<xref rid="bibr9-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="bibr10-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr11-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Work stress also shows similar links with DP [<xref rid="bibr31-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. A possible explanation for these findings may be the lower level of subjective health in individuals under high levels of work strain [<xref rid="bibr32-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p>
              <p>For both LTSA and DP, the HR associated with sleep disturbances was higher than for work-related mental strain. This suggests that disturbed sleep may be more important with respect to these measures of work disability. The former referred to the two recent weeks, while mental work strain did not have a temporal reference. This could have led to attenuation of the association of mental work strain. Still, it is quite clear that reporting sleep disturbances during the recent two weeks is a predictor of work disability.</p>
              <p>The lack of association between work-related mental strain and mortality agrees with some previous studies [<xref rid="bibr15-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="bibr16-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr17-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], but disagrees with others that found an association [<xref rid="bibr12-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="bibr13-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr14-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Apparently, it is not possible to draw any firm conclusions on the association between work-related mental strain and mortality. It might be that exposure to work-related mental strain shows a strong variation across time and that baseline exposure may not be representative for the accumulation across follow-up time. At present, there does not seem to be any previous work on such variation over time, apart from the observation that job demands decrease across eight years of aging in both blue- and white-collar workers [<xref rid="bibr33-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Such effects may also have been involved in the present study.</p>
              <p>The lack of association between disturbed sleep and mortality in the present study (after adjusting for mental work strain) agrees with a recent meta-analysis [<xref rid="bibr26-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This observation contrasts with what would be expected from the links between sleep disturbances and SA and DP in the present study, as well as with similar previous work [<xref rid="bibr22-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="bibr23-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr24-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr25-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. It also contrasts with the observations of both long and short sleep duration being associated with increased mortality risk [<xref rid="bibr34-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], even if poor sleep does not necessarily imply short sleep. It is also well established that sleep quality and duration vary over time [<xref rid="bibr35-1403494820911813" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and, as with work-related mental strain, it is possible that baseline measures may not be representative of exposure to that predictor during follow-up.</p>
              <p>Some of the limitations of the present study have been discussed above. One additional limitation is that cross-sectional measures of the exposure can create possibilities for reverse causality between the exposure and the outcome. For this purpose, we controlled our analyses for previous SA and use of specialised health care. Another limitation is that exposure was determined through self-report, but this may be difficult to avoid when focusing on the present types of exposure in a large sample. Furthermore, the exposure measurements were based on surveys, and participants are likely to be healthier than the general population. About 21% of the sample did not respond to the questions on exposure and covariates. A description of this group from the registers indicated that they showed more disease and more DP, and originated from other parts of the world than Sweden. This may have attenuated the links between exposures and outcomes.</p>
              <p>The strengths of this study include its base in data from high-quality Swedish population-based nationwide registers with longitudinal data linked at the individual level. The large sample size of more than 40,000 offers satisfactory statistical power and also represents a strength of the study. Additionally, information regarding the covariates and outcome were derived from nationwide registers. The use of register data eliminated the possibility of recall bias regarding outcome measures and avoided the loss to follow-up. Additionally, a wide range of socio-demographic, medical and work-related factors could be included as potential confounders.</p>
              <p>In conclusion, work-related mental strain and, in particular, sleep disturbances were associated with a higher risk of subsequent LTSA and DP, but no synergy effects were present. Sleep disturbances were also significantly related to mortality. Exposure to interventions tackling sleep disturbance and prevention of workplace stress may be key to reducing work disability. The conclusions should probably not be generalised to groups in poor health at the start or to immigrant groups.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <p>For the present cohort, Statistics Sweden is responsible for data linkage and provided the de-identified data. This project was evaluated and approved by the Regional Ethical Review Board of Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden. The data are not available for researchers not involved in the project. Further questions may be addressed to the person responsible for the project: Professor Kristina Alexanderson (<email>Kristina.alexanderson@ki.se</email>).</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>ORCID iDs:</bold> Torbjörn Åkerstedt <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1403494820911813-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8049-8504">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8049-8504</ext-link></p>
                <p>Syed Rahman <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1403494820911813-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4006-3327">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4006-3327</ext-link></p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bibr1-1403494820911813">
                <label>[1]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selye</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The general adaptation syndrome and the diseases of adaptation</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol</source><year>1946</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr2-1403494820911813">
                <label>[2]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karasek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Theorell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Healthy work: stress, productivity, and the reconstruction of working life</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Book</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr3-1403494820911813">
                <label>[3]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kivimäki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Batty</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Job strain as a risk factor for coronary heart disease: a collaborative meta-analysis of individual participant data</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>380</volume>:<fpage>1491</fpage>–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22981903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr4-1403494820911813">
                <label>[4]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jood</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvholm</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A systematic review of studies in the contributions of the work environment to ischaemic heart disease development</article-title>. <source>Eur J Public Health</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>470</fpage>–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27032996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr5-1403494820911813">
                <label>[5]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mutambudzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Theorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Job strain and long-term sickness absence from work: a ten-tear prospective study in German working population</article-title>. <source>J Occup Environ Med</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>–84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30540654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr6-1403494820911813">
                <label>[6]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dich</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Job strain and informal caregiving as predictors of long-term sickness absence: a longitudinal multi-cohort study</article-title>. <source>Scand J Work Environ Health</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27556905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr7-1403494820911813">
                <label>[7]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mykletun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moyner</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Job strain, health and sickness absence: results from the Hordaland Health Study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e96025</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24755878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr8-1403494820911813">
                <label>[8]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Virtanen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vahtera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pentti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Job strain and psychologic distress influence on sickness absence among Finnish employees</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17826576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr9-1403494820911813">
                <label>[9]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimeno</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Virtanen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Job strain as a predictor of disability pension: the Finnish Public Sector Study</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18768568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr10-1403494820911813">
                <label>[10]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantyniemi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oksanen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Salo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Job strain and the risk of disability pension due to musculoskeletal disorders, depression or coronary heart disease: a prospective cohort study of 69,842 employees</article-title>. <source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>574</fpage>–81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22573793</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr11-1403494820911813">
                <label>[11]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canivet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Karasek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Can high psychological job demands, low decision latitude, and high job strain predict disability pensions? A 12-year follow-up of middle-aged Swedish workers</article-title>. <source>Int Arch Occup Environ Health</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>–19.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22476722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr12-1403494820911813">
                <label>[12]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritzell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Work-related stress in midlife and all-cause mortality: can sense of coherence modify this association?</article-title><source>Eur J Public Health</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1055</fpage>–61.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27335331</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr13-1403494820911813">
                <label>[13]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillard</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Giving to others and the association between stress and mortality</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>1649</fpage>–55.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23327269</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr14-1403494820911813">
                <label>[14]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>What characterizes persons with high levels of perceived stress in Denmark? A national representative study</article-title>. <source>Scand J Public Health</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>369</fpage>–79.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18539691</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr15-1403494820911813">
                <label>[15]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Toker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkaly</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Work-based predictors of mortality: a 20-year follow-up of healthy employees</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>268</fpage>–75.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21553970</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr16-1403494820911813">
                <label>[16]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kivimaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pentti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deanfield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Work stress and mortality in people with cardiometabolic disease – authors’ reply</article-title>. <source>Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>767</fpage>–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30266185</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr17-1403494820911813">
                <label>[17]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garde</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtermann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Sleep duration and ischemic heart disease and all-cause mortality: prospective cohort study on effects of tranquilizers/hypnotics and perceived stress</article-title>. <source>Scand J Work Environ Health</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>550</fpage>–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23804297</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr18-1403494820911813">
                <label>[18]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Karatsoreos</surname><given-names>IN.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep deprivation and circadian disruption: stress, allostasis, and allostatic load</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med Clin</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055668</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr19-1403494820911813">
                <label>[19]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cappuccio</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Elia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Strazzullo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Quantity and quality of sleep and incidence of type 2 diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>414</fpage>–20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr20-1403494820911813">
                <label>[20]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kecklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Predicting long-term sickness absence from sleep and fatigue</article-title>. <source>J Sleep Res</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>–5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18036078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr21-1403494820911813">
                <label>[21]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lallukka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaikkonen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Harkanen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Sleep and sickness absence: a nationally representative register-based follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1413</fpage>–25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25142569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr22-1403494820911813">
                <label>[22]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Glozier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivertsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A comparison of insomnia and depression as predictors of disability pension: the HUNT Study</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>875</fpage>–80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18548833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr23-1403494820911813">
                <label>[23]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivertsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Overland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallesen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Insomnia and long sleep duration are risk factors for later work disability. The Hordaland Health Study</article-title>. <source>J Sleep Res</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19021852</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr24-1403494820911813">
                <label>[24]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lallukka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haaramo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahelma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Sleep problems and disability retirement: a register-based follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>173</volume>:<fpage>871</fpage>–81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21415034</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr25-1403494820911813">
                <label>[25]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haaramo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahkonen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahelma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The joint association of sleep duration and insomnia symptoms with disability retirement – a longitudinal, register-linked study</article-title>. <source>Scand J Work Environ Health</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>–35.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22234460</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr26-1403494820911813">
                <label>[26]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lovato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lack</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insomnia and mortality: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med Rev</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30529432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr27-1403494820911813">
                <label>[27]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Lange</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kompier</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taris</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A hard day’s night: a longitudinal study on the relationships among job demands and job control, sleep quality and fatigue</article-title>. <source>J Sleep Res</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>374</fpage>–83.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19493298</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr28-1403494820911813">
                <label>[28]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Predicting changes in sleep complaints from baseline values and changes in work demands, work control, and work preoccupation – the WOLF-project</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22177346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr29-1403494820911813">
                <label>[29]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knol</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>VanderWeele</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Groenwold</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Estimating measures of interaction on an additive scale for preventive exposures</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>–8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21344323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr30-1403494820911813">
                <label>[30]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lekander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreasson</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kecklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Subjective health perception in healthy young men changes in response to experimentally restricted sleep and subsequent recovery sleep</article-title>. <source>Brain Behav Immun</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23820239</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr31-1403494820911813">
                <label>[31]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ropponen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Svedberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Koskenvuo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Physical work load and psychological stress of daily activities as predictors of disability pension due to musculoskeletal disorders</article-title>. <source>Scand J Public Health</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>370</fpage>–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24608095</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr32-1403494820911813">
                <label>[32]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stadin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brostrom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Information and communication technology demands at work: the association with job strain, effort-reward imbalance and self-rated health in different socio-economic strata</article-title>. <source>Int Arch Occup Environ Health</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1049</fpage>–58.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27193569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr33-1403494820911813">
                <label>[33]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akerstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Discacciati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Habel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Psychosocial work demands and physical workload decrease with ageing in blue-collar and white-collar workers: a prospective study based on the SLOSH cohort</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e030918</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr34-1403494820911813">
                <label>[34]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cappuccio</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Elia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Strazzullo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Sleep duration and all-cause mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>585</fpage>–92.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20469800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bibr35-1403494820911813">
                <label>[35]</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buysse</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Night-to-night sleep variability in older adults with and without chronic insomnia</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19962939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
