<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2023-02-07T13:02:36Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7962724" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7962724</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-19</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bjsopen</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJS Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJS Open</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjsopen</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BJS Open</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2474-9842</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7962724</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7962724</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7962724</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33724336</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33724336</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjsopen/zraa029</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zraa029</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
                  <subject>Bjs/2</subject>
                  <subject>Bjs/3</subject>
                  <subject>Bjs/5</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection">
                  <subject>Bjs/12</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Prediction of cognitive response to surgery in elderly patients with primary hyperparathyroidism</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3196-7057</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Koman</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Endocrine Tumours and Sarcoma, Karolinska University Hospital</institution>, Stockholm, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Molecular Medicine and Surgery, Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
                  <xref rid="zraa029-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/>
                  <!--anna.koman@ki.se-->
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bränström</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Endocrine Tumours and Sarcoma, Karolinska University Hospital</institution>, Stockholm, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Molecular Medicine and Surgery, Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pernow</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Molecular Medicine and Surgery, Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bränström</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nilsson</surname>
                    <given-names>I -L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Endocrine Tumours and Sarcoma, Karolinska University Hospital</institution>, Stockholm, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
                  <aff><institution>Department of Molecular Medicine and Surgery, Karolinska Institutet</institution>, Stockholm, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="zraa029-cor1"><italic toggle="yes">Correspondence to:</italic> Department of Molecular Medicine and Surgery, Karolinska Institutet, SE-171 76 Stockholm, Sweden (e-mail: <email>anna.koman@ki.se</email>)</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2020-12-22">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>5</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <elocation-id>zraa029</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>28</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="editorial-decision">
                  <day>28</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of BJS Society Ltd.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:href="zraa029.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <sec id="s1">
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p>Primary hyperparathyroidism (pHPT) can be associated with potentially reversible cognitive impairment, which is occasionally mistaken for natural ageing and dementia. The aim was to evaluate short-term medical normalization of hypercalcaemia in surgical decision-making for elderly patients with mild cognitive deficiency.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2">
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>Patients with pHPT were included in a prospective observational study. A test panel including the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) and validated tools for estimation of psychological status (Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale, HADS), and muscle strength (timed-stands test, TST) was applied at baseline, after 4 weeks of calcimimetic treatment, and after parathyroidectomy. Mild cognitive impairment was defined by a MoCA score below 26. A longitudinal increase in MoCA score of at least 2 points 6 months after surgery was considered clinically meaningful.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Of 110 patients who underwent testing, 35 aged 50 years or more were identified to have mild cognitive dysfunction, including 19 who were aged at least 70 years (median MoCA score 23, i.q.r. 21–24). Calcimimetic treatment resulted in normalization of calcium levels, and improvements in MoCA and HADS scores, and TST time. Normal MoCA scores (at least 26) were reached in 17 patients by 6 months after surgery, of whom 10 were aged 70 years or older. Long-term increase in MoCA score correlated with the decrease in ionized calcium concentration (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = –0.536, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022). Baseline calcium concentration and improvement in MoCA with calcimimetic treatment were identified as independent predictors of favourable outcome after parathyroidectomy.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s4">
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>Medical normalization of hypercalcaemia can aid in predicting outcome after parathyroidectomy.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="teaser">
                <p>Cognitive impairment related to primary hyperparathyroidism in the elderly is sometimes mistaken for natural ageing or dementia. The aim of this study was to evaluate the ability of medical normalization of hypercalcaemia to predict individual outcome after parathyroidectomy. Half of the 35 patients with mild cognitive deficiency (Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) score below 26) had normal MoCA scores (at least 26) by 6 months after operation. The improvement in MoCA score during receipt of study medication was identified as independent predictor of favourable outcome after parathyroidectomy.</p>
                <p>Medical treatment predicts cognitive improvement after surgery</p>
              </abstract>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Stockholm County Council</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Karolinska Institutet</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Novo Nordic Foundation</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Amgen, Solna</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Magnus Bergvall Foundation</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Fredrik and Ingrid Thuring Foundation</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
                <award-group award-type="grant">
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Lisa and Johan Grönberg Foundation</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="5"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Primary hyperparathyroidism (pHPT) is characterized by a relative excess of parathyroid hormone with hypercalcaemia. The cause is most commonly a benign parathyroid adenoma, and the only curative treatment is parathyroidectomy. Conservative treatment can be adopted in asymptomatic disease, or calcimimetic treatment used to reduce symptoms of hypercalcaemia when surgery is contraindicated<xref rid="zraa029-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>. The incidence of pHPT increases with age and the disorder is three times more common in women. The prevalence is estimated to be around 1 per cent in the general Swedish population, but as high as 3–5 per cent among women aged over 50 years<xref rid="zraa029-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Many patients with pHPT exhibit biochemically mild disease without classical features such as renal stones or osteoporosis. Many are classified as asymptomatic, although, particularly in the elderly, cognitive impairment, muscular weakness, diffuse neuropsychiatric symptoms, and pain are often mistaken for other age-related conditions. According to current guidelines, the majority of elderly patients with non-specific symptoms only do not fulfil the criteria for parathyroidectomy and are consequently at risk of not being offered curative treatment<xref rid="zraa029-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zraa029-B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>. Persisting disease may lead to worsening symptoms and impaired quality of life (QoL) that potentially pose an increased risk of development of secondary chronic morbidity and disabilities. In the elderly patient with signs of cognitive deficiencies, the impact of parathyroidectomy on cognitive impairment and the potential of reversal is largely unknown.</p>
              <p>Previous studies have demonstrated that surgical cure rates and clinical outcomes, including morbidity and mortality, are similar in the elderly to those among younger patients. Besides increased fracture-free survival after parathyroidectomy, the majority of elderly patients with pHPT experience general symptomatic relief<xref rid="zraa029-B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zraa029-B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>. Although overall long-term recovery from non-specific symptoms after parathyroidectomy has been established in both normocalcaemic and hypercalcaemic patients with pHPT<xref rid="zraa029-B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>, with increasing age, elderly patients are less frequently referred for parathyroidectomy<xref rid="zraa029-B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Predicting the outcome of non-specific symptoms and cognitive performance after parathyroidectomy remains a crucial question.</p>
              <p>Short-term medical normalization of hypercalcaemia has been recognized as a feasible diagnostic method that might be used to predict the overall effects on QoL, cognition, and muscle strength after parathyroidectomy to aid in the decision to offer surgical treatment. A study<xref rid="zraa029-B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> confirmed that symptom relief achieved by medical normalization of hypercalcaemia correlated well with improvements after surgery. The calcium-lowering effect is almost immediate and reversed rapidly when the drug is discontinued. In a study<xref rid="zraa029-B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> of 22 patients with pHPT who received 30–50 mg cinacalcet twice daily, normal calcium levels were achieved after only the second dose on day 1, whereas another study<xref rid="zraa029-B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> with the same agent reported normalization of hypercalcaemia among 14 of 17 patients with intractable pHPT. Although adverse effects were common, a significant improvement in QoL and cognitive functioning was observed<xref rid="zraa029-B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>. There is, however, no convincing evidence for long-term effects of calcimimetic treatment on non-specific symptoms, or its effects on risk reduction for cardiovascular complications or prevention of osteoporosis. Based on its described properties, cinacalcet was considered to be a highly suitable drug for trial purposes to see whether short-term outcomes might predict long-term changes in cognitive function. This study therefore sought to evaluate short-term calcimimetic treatment as a diagnostic tool to predict outcome after parathyroidectomy in elderly patients with pHPT and mild cognitive impairment.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>Factors influencing recovery after normalization of hypercalcaemia were analysed in a prospective observational study of patients with pHPT, who were treated with a short-term calcimimetic as a diagnostic tool to predict outcome after parathyroidectomy (ClinicalTrials.gov, NCT00982722). Some of the results have been presented previously, including a detailed description of the study procedure<xref rid="zraa029-B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. Each patient gave written consent to participate in the study, which was approved by the Swedish Medical Products Agency and the regional ethics committee. This part of the study focused on patients in the cohort aged 50 years or more with mild cognitive impairment as defined below.</p>
              <p>Patients received calcimimetic treatment for 4 weeks, followed by parathyroidectomy. Treatment was initiated with 30 mg cinacalcet hydrochloride daily (Mimpara<sup><bold><sup>®</sup></bold></sup>; Amgen, Thousand Oaks, California, USA)<xref rid="zraa029-B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>. If hypercalcaemia persisted after 2 weeks of daily 30 mg cinacalcet, the dose was increased to 60 mg. Calcium levels and side-effects were monitored and recorded weekly during this treatment. BP and levels of ionized calcium were recorded at all other assessments as detailed below.</p>
              <p>A panel of validated tests to estimate cognitive function, mental status, and muscle strength was applied four times: at baseline, after 4 weeks of calcimimetic medication, and at 6 weeks and 6 months after parathyroidectomy. No specific length of time was mandated for the interval between cessation of calcimimetic treatment and the date of surgery. Test results were analysed longitudinally in order to compare the effect of normalization of hypercalcaemia with the result after parathyroidectomy. Positive (PPVs) and negative (NPVs) predictive values were calculated for each test.</p>
              <p>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA)<xref rid="zraa029-B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zraa029-B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>, a validated screening instrument for early screening of cognitive impairment, was used. Normative scores for the MoCA, based on a large Swedish population of individuals aged 65–85 years, have been published<xref rid="zraa029-B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>. Visuospatial and abstraction capacity, memory, executive capability, attention, language, and orientation in time and space are evaluated. The maximum score is 30 points. Age and education have an impact on the results. For individuals with 12 years or less of education, 1 point is added to the total score. A score of below 26 points is established as the cut-off value for indicating mild cognitive impairment. Alzheimer’s disease should be considered for a score of less than 22 points.</p>
              <p>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) questionnaire includes six items for the detection of depression (HADS D) and six for anxiety (HADS A)<xref rid="zraa029-B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>. Each item is scored on a scale of 0–4, lower scores being favourable.</p>
              <p>The timed-stands test (TST) is used to estimate proximal muscle strength by measuring the time required to complete 10 full stands from a sitting position as quickly as possible. The time is rounded off to the nearest tenth of a second. A reduction in time spent performing the test indicates an improvement in proximal muscle strength<xref rid="zraa029-B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>.</p>
              <p>Blood samples were collected with the patient in a fasting state before each visit. All biochemical analyses were performed using routine methods by the Karolinska University Laboratory in Stockholm. Blood analysed for ionized calcium was delivered within 1 h, and centrifuged within 2 h of collecting the sample.</p>
              <p>Glomerular filtration rate was calculated from preoperative baseline blood samples using the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease formula: 175×(serum creatinine/88.4)<sup>−1.154</sup>×(age)<sup>−0.203</sup>×(0.742 if female).</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>Based on the distribution, non-parametric methods were used and data presented as median (i.q.r.). All tests were two-tailed, and <italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt;<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>0.050 was considered statistically significant. Each patient served as their individual control. Wilcoxon signed-rank test was used for intraindividual comparisons. The Spearman rank-order test was used to analyse bivariable correlations. The improvements in each test were transformed into dichotomous variables. For the subgroup with mild cognitive impairment, cross-tabulation was used for calculating sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV for each test. The area under the curve was estimated by receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve analysis. A binary logistic regression model, including the whole study cohort, was used for analysis of predictors of long-term increase in MoCA score by at least 2 points, as defined by the test developer to be clinically significant<xref rid="zraa029-B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. Statistical analyses were done using SPSS<sup>®</sup> version 26 (IBM, Armonk, New York, USA)</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>Clinical characteristics of the study cohort and subgroups are shown in <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zraa029-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></italic>. Of 110 patients enrolled, mild cognitive dysfunction, defined by a MoCA score below 26 (median 23, i.q.r. 21–24), was identified in 35 patients aged 50 years or more (19 patients aged at least 70 years). Overall, 17 of 35 patients (10 aged at least 70 years) had normal MoCA scores of 26 or higher 6 months after surgery (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zraa029-F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref></italic>). A binary logistic regression model identified an increase in MoCA score during calcimimetic treatment and the baseline ionized calcium level, classified into tertiles, as independent predictors of long-term improvement in MoCA score (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref></italic>).</p>
              <fig position="float" id="zraa029-F1">
                <label>Fig. 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Montreal Cognitive Assessment score before and 6 months after parathyroidectomy in relation to age </p>
                  <p>Scores on or above dotted line are considered normal. MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment. </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="zraa029f1" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="zraa029-T1">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Clinical characteristics</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                    <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages and MoCA scores<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>†</sup></xref> (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>110)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA score &lt; 26, age ≥ 50 years (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>35)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA score  &lt; 26, age ≥ 70 years (<italic toggle="yes">n </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>19)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal reference range</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age (years</bold>)<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (53–72)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (62–79)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (72–82)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Sex ratio (F : M)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 : 19</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 : 4</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 : 2</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup></bold>)<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (23–29)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (23–30)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (21–30)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Biochemical measurements</bold>
                        <xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">
                          <sup>*</sup>
                        </xref>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Plasma calcium (mmol/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 (2.51–2.68)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62 (2.49–2.71)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67 (2.56–2.73)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15–2.50</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Serum ionized calcium (mmol/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 (1.38–1.46)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (1.39–1.48)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (1.38–1.48)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15–1.33</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Plasma albumin (g/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (36–39)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (35–39)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (34–39)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
36–48 (&lt; 41 years)
<break/>36–45 (41–70 years)
<break/>34–45 (&gt; 70 years)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Plasma parathytroid hormone (pmol/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 (7.9–13.0)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 (8.8–14.2)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 (8.1–14.0)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6–6.0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Plasma phosphate (mmol/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.78–0.95)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.78–0.95)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (0.78–0.93)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8–1.5</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Plasma creatinine (μmol/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (62–78)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (61–81)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (60–81)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
&lt; 90 (F)
<break/>&lt; 100 (M)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Serum 25-hydroxy vitamin D (nmol/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (52–81)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (49–73)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (50–76)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50–250</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Thyroid-stimulating hormone (mEq/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (1.2–2.6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (1.1–2.6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.1–2.4)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3–4.2</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fasting blood glucose (mmol/l)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 (5.3–5.9)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 (5.2–6.1)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (5.0–6.4)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0–6.0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Systolic BP (mmHg)</bold>
                        <xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">
                          <sup>*</sup>
                        </xref>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (130–154)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (139–175)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (134–180)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Diastolic BP (mmHg)</bold>
                        <xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">
                          <sup>*</sup>
                        </xref>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (82–96)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (84–100)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (80–100)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Increased dose of calcimimetic</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Adenoma weight (mg)</bold>
                        <xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">
                          <sup>*</sup>
                        </xref>
                      </td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">356 (260–633)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">468 (300–1000)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">370 (322–925)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="tblfn1">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Values are median (i.q.r.).</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="tblfn2">
                    <label>†</label>
                    <p>Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) score 26 (i.q.r. 24–28). </p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>All but three of the 35 patients with mild cognitive impairment completed the study. Two patients stopped the medication because of gastrointestinal side-effects and one discontinued medication after an upper respiratory tract infection. Parathyroidectomy was performed at a median of 6 (i.q.r. 4–12) weeks after the last dose of study medication.</p>
              <p>A total of 15 patients (9 aged at least 70 years) required higher-dose calcimimetic treatment (60 mg/day) to achieve normal calcium levels. No serious adverse event related to the study medication was observed. Calcimimetic treatment resulted in normalization of calcium levels and improvements in MoCA score (change compared with baseline in patients aged 50 years or more: median 2, i.q.r. 0–3; <italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt;<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>0.001), HADS score (–2, 0 to –3; <italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>0.020) and TST (–3 (0 to -9) s; <italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>0.004) (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zraa029-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></italic>). The baseline MoCA score correlated inversely with age (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = –0.430, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010) but not with the ionized calcium level (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.079, <italic toggle="yes">P </italic>=<italic toggle="yes"> </italic>0.651).</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="zraa029-T2">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Test results in patients aged at least 50 years with a Montreal Cognitive Assessment score below 26 at baseline</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                    <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="(" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="(" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="(" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">△I–II</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> (I <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> II)</bold>
                        <xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn">
                          <sup>*</sup>
                        </xref>
                      </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">△I–IV</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> (△I–II <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> △I–IV)</bold>
                        <xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn">
                          <sup>*</sup>
                        </xref>
                      </th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Age ≥ 70 years (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (20–24)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0–3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0–4)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Timed-stands test (s)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (26–45)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–3 (1 to –9)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–4 (–2 to –15)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS anxiety score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2–10)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1 (0 to –3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.505</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1 (0 to –3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.189</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS depression score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1–8)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1 (0 to –3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1 (0 to –3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.189</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS total score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5–15)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2 (0 to –3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–3 (0 to –6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Age ≥ 50 years (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 35)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (21–24)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0–3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1–4)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Timed-stands test (s)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (28–40)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–3 (0 to –9)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–5 (–2 to –10)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS anxiety score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4–10)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1 (0 to –2)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2 (0 to –3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS depression score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1–6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–1 (0 to –2)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–3 (0 to –6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS total score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (6–16)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–2 (0 to –3)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–3 (0 to –6)</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="tblfn3">
                    <p>Values are median (i.q.r.). Intraindividual changes are shown: ΔI–II, change between baseline (measurement I) and after 4 weeks of calcimimetic treatment (measurement II); ΔI–IV, change between baseline and 6 months after parathyroidectomy. MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale.</p>
                  </fn>
                  <fn id="tblfn4">
                    <label>*</label>
                    <p>Wilcoxon signed-rank test.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The predictive values of tests in the panel are presented in <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zraa029-T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></italic>. HADS had the highest accuracy with PPV and NPV around 90 per cent. MoCA and TST had PPV values around 80 per cent, but an NPV of no more than 33 per cent.</p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="zraa029-T3">
                <label>Table 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Prediction of improvement at follow-up 6 months after parathyroidectomy in patients aged at least 50 years and with a Montreal Cognitive Assessment score below 26 at baseline</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                    <col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                    <col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPV (%)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPV (%)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity (%)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity (%)</th>
                      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AUC for</bold>Δ<bold>I–II</bold></th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Age ≥ 70 years (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.596 (0.263, 0.929)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Timed-stands test</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.569 (0.209, 0.930)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS anxiety score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669 (0.394, 0.945)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS depression score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833 (0.629, 1.000)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS total score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.944 (0.891, 1.000)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
                        <bold>Age ≥ 50 years (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 35)</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.560 (0.273, 0.847)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Timed-stands test</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745 (0.474, 1.000)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS anxiety score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.791 (0.626, 0.956)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS depression score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.775 (0.603, 0.946)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS total score</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.846 (0.700, 0.991)</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="tblfn5">
                    <p>Values in parentheses are 95 per cent confidence intervals. The predictive values of the different components of the test protocol were evaluated dichotomously based on improvement or not. Sensitivity, specificity, and positive (PPV) and (NPV) predictive values were calculated by cross-tabulation. AUC, area under the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve; ΔI–II, change between baseline and after 4 weeks of calcimimetic treatment; MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>For patients aged at least 70 years, long-term improvement in MoCA score after parathyroidectomy correlated with the decrease in ionized calcium level (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = –0.536, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022) (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zraa029-F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref></italic>).</p>
              <fig position="float" id="zraa029-F2">
                <label>Fig. 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Change in Montreal Cognitive Assessment score 6 months after parathyroidectomy in relation to decrease in ionized calcium level</p>
                  <p>MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; ΔI–IV, change between baseline and 6 months after parathyroidectomy.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="zraa029f2" position="float"/>
              </fig>
              <p>The decrease in HADS during calcimimetic treatment correlated with an increase in MoCA score 6 months after parathyroidectomy (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = –0.488, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.047) (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="zraa029-F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref></italic>).</p>
              <fig position="float" id="zraa029-F3">
                <label>Fig. 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Change in Montreal Cognitive Assessment score 6 months after parathyroidectomy in relation to change in Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale score during calcimimetic treatment</p>
                  <p>MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale; ΔI–II, change between baseline and after 4 weeks of calcimimetic treatment; ΔI–IV, change between baseline and 6 months after parathyroidectomy.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="zraa029f3" position="float"/>
              </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Preservation of cognition, psychological functioning, and muscular strength are important in maintaining QoL and health in the elderly. Exclusion of patients from surgery who exhibit these non-specific manifestations of pHPT is of concern.</p>
              <p>It is well recognized that calcimimetic treatment is effective in normalizing calcium levels in pHPT<xref rid="zraa029-B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>, but adverse effects are frequent and the effect on the calcium concentration lasts only during continuous medication. Short-term normalization of hypercalcaemia has been suggested as a feasible diagnostic tool to predict outcomes after parathyroidectomy. The present study has confirmed that short-term improvements in cognitive function achieved in this way can be maintained for at least 6 months after surgery.</p>
              <p>All assessments included in the test panel were performed easily and generated high predictive values regarding long-term benefits of parathyroidectomy. The MoCA screening test, which has been well validated for the detection of cognitive deficiency, and considered appropriate as a repeatable brief measure of longitudinal cognitive change<xref rid="zraa029-B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zraa029-B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>, indicated that half of the patients with a baseline score of less than 26 had normal scores 6 months after operation, irrespective of age. These results demonstrate the potential benefit on cognitive function, and underline the importance of establishing a correct indication for parathyroidectomy.</p>
              <p>The short-term improvement in depression and anxiety after medical normalization of hypercalcaemia was also found to be associated with long-term effects on cognitive function 6 months after parathyroidectomy. This adds further support for consideration of non-specific symptoms in future guidelines for parathyroid surgery.</p>
              <p>Ionized calcium is considered to be the most appropriate measure of hypercalcaemia and was the modality used primarily in the present analysis. The study cohort included patients with pHPT with a range of calcium levels, but the majority had mild hypercalcaemia. Only 3 of 19 patients aged 70 years or more had a calcium level that alone was considered an indication for parathyroidectomy according to the guidelines<xref rid="zraa029-B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref>. The MoCA score at baseline was related to age, but did not correlate with the level of hypercalcaemia. On the other hand, the baseline calcium level was identified as an independent predictor of long-term increase in MoCA score after parathyroidectomy in the whole cohort, as well as in the older age group in whom the long-term increase in MoCA score correlated with the decrease in calcium level.</p>
              <p>The study has limitations. The cohort of elderly patients was relatively small. The presence of co-morbidities could have affected the results through changes in other conditions. Before inclusion, all patients had been selected for parathyroidectomy and the outcome could have been affected by patients’ expectations of improvement. The MoCA score also has limitations. Being primarily a screening assessment tool for detecting cognitive deficiencies, the score cannot constitute a basis for detailed neurodegenerative diagnostics. This study model permits limited conclusions about the causality of the cognitive processes related to pHPT.</p>
              <p>The results of the present study, however, indicate that there are complex interrelationships between physical, psychological, and cognitive symptoms, and this test panel provides a useful way of predicting outcome after parathyroidectomy. The results emphasize the importance of paying greater attention to a wider assessment of domains that contribute to health-related QoL and the benefits that can be gained after parathyroidectomy, particularly in the elderly. Medical normalization of hypercalcaemia can, regardless of age, help in predicting outcomes after parathyroidectomy and is worthy of wider assessment as an aid to patient selection for surgery.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>Novo Nordisk Foundation</p>
              <p>Amgen, Solna</p>
              <p>Magnus Bergvall Foundation</p>
              <p>Fredrik and Ingrid Thuring Foundation</p>
              <p>Lisa and Johan Grönberg Foundation</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <label>zraa029_Supplementary_Data</label>
                <media xlink:href="zraa029_supplementary_data.docx">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack id="ack1">
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>The research team thank the participating patients for their cooperation; staff at the Department of Endocrine Tumours and Sarcoma, Karolinska University Hospital, for enhancing recruitment of study patients; and R. Hallbeck, research nurse, who assisted in most of the practical testing, and monitored and kept in touch with the study patients throughout the study. This study was funded by Stockholm County Council, Karolinska Institutet, the Novo Nordic Foundation, Amgen, Solna, the Magnus Bergvall Foundation, the Fredrik and Ingrid Thuring Foundation, and the Lisa and Johan Grönberg Foundation.</p>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">Disclosure.</italic> The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Supplementary material</title>
                <p><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">BJS Open</italic> online.</p>
              </sec>
            </ack>
            <ref-list id="ref1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="zraa029-B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rizzoli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bollerslev</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rejnmark</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>Primary hyperparathyroidism: review and recommendations on evaluation, diagnosis, and management. A Canadian and international consensus</article-title>. <source>Osteoporos Int</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Siilin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rastad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ljunggren</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group> 
 <article-title>Disturbances of calcium homeostasis consistent with mild primary hyperparathyroidism in premenopausal women and associated morbidity</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>  <year>2008</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18042652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bilezikian</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brandi</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silverberg</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Udelsman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcocci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>Guidelines for the management of asymptomatic primary hyperparathyroidism: summary statement from the Fourth International Workshop</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>  <year>2014</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>3561</fpage>–<lpage>3569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25162665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ituarte</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pasternak</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>Surgery for primary hyperparathyroidism: are the consensus guidelines being followed?</article-title>  <source>Ann Surg</source>  <year>2012</year>;<volume>255</volume>:<fpage>1179</fpage>–<lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22584631</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haigh</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ituarte</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>Underutilization of parathyroidectomy in elderly patients with primary hyperparathyroidism</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>  <year>2010</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>4324</fpage>–<lpage>4330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20610600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Calò</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Medas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pisano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sorrenti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erdas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>Parathyroidectomy for primary hyperparathyroidism in the elderly: experience of a single endocrine surgery center</article-title>. <source>Aging Clin Exp Res</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>29(Suppl</volume>):<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27837463</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bannani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guerin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sebag</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathonnet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>Effect of parathyroidectomy on quality of life and non-specific symptoms in normocalcaemic primary hyperparathyroidism</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>  <year>2018</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29405278</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Koman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohlsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Branstrom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pernow</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Branstrom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>IL.</given-names></string-name></person-group> 
 <article-title>Short-term medical treatment of hypercalcaemia in primary hyperparathyroidism predicts symptomatic response after parathyroidectomy</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>  <year>2019</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1810</fpage>–<lpage>1818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31595982</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shoback</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bilezikian</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCary</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> 
 <article-title>The calcimimetic cinacalcet normalizes serum calcium in subjects with primary hyperparathyroidism</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>  <year>2003</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>5644</fpage>–<lpage>5649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14671147</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marcocci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chanson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shoback</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bilezikian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez-Cruz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orgiazzi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>Cinacalcet reduces serum calcium concentrations in patients with intractable primary hyperparathyroidism</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>  <year>2009</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>2766</fpage>–<lpage>2772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19470620</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Amgen</collab>. <italic toggle="yes">Highlights of Prescribing Information</italic>. 2004, <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.pi.amgen.com/&amp;sim;/media/amgen/repositorysites/pi-amgen-com/sensipar/sensipa" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.pi.amgen.com/∼/media/amgen/repositorysites/pi-amgen-com/sensipar/sensipa</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nasreddine</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bedirian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charbonneau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment. <italic toggle="yes">J</italic></article-title>  <source>Am Geriatr Soc</source>  <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dalrymple-Alford</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacAskill</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakas</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crucian</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>The MoCA: well-suited screen for cognitive impairment in Parkinson disease</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>  <year>2010</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>1717</fpage>–<lpage>1725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21060094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Borland</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minthon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palmqvist</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group> 
 <article-title>The Montreal cognitive assessment: normative data from a large Swedish population-based cohort</article-title>. <source>J Alzheimers Dis</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28697562</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zigmond</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Snaith</surname><given-names>RP.</given-names></string-name></person-group> 
 <article-title>The hospital anxiety and depression scale</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatrica Scand</source>  <year>1983</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Csuka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>DJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group> 
 <article-title>Simple method for measurement of lower extremity muscle strength</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source>  <year>1985</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nasreddine</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>BB.</given-names></string-name></person-group> 
 <article-title>Validation of Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA, Alternate French Versions</article-title>. <source>Can J Neurol Sci</source>  <year>2016</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27670209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EM.</given-names></string-name></person-group> 
 <article-title>Clinical utility of calcimimetics targeting the extracellular calcium-sensing receptor (CaSR)</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source>  <year>2010</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20382129</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rossetti</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hynan</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falkowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lacritz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>Changes in Montreal Cognitive Assessment scores over time</article-title>. <source>Assessment</source>  <year>2017</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>777</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27318033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="zraa029-B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asa</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duh</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <etal>et al</etal> 
 <article-title>The American Association of Endocrine Surgeons Guidelines for Definitive Management of Primary Hyperparathyroidism</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surg</source>  <year>2016</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>959</fpage>–<lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27532368</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
